The Project Gutenberg eBook, Tess of the d'Urbervilles, by Thomas Hardy

This eBook is for the use of anyone anywhere at no cost and with

almost no restrictions whatsoever. You may copy it, give it away or

re-use it under the terms of the Project Gutenberg License included

with this eBook or online at www.gutenberg.net

Title: Tess of the d'Urbervilles

A Pure Woman

Author: Thomas Hardy

Release Date: February, 1994 [eBook #110]

This edition 11 released June 17, 2005

Language: English

Character set encoding: ISO-8859-1

***START OF THE PROJECT GUTENBERG EBOOK TESS OF THE D'URBERVILLES***

E-text transcribed by Steve Menyhert, proof-read by Meredith Ricker and

John Hamm, and revised by Joseph E. Loewenstein, M.D.

TESS OF THE D'URBERVILLES

A Pure Woman

Faithfully presented by

THOMAS HARDY

Contents

Phase the First: The Maiden, I-XI

Phase the Second: Maiden No More, XII-XV

Phase the Third: The Rally, XVI-XXIV

Phase the Fourth: The Consequence, XXV-XXXIV

Phase the Fifth: The Woman Pays, XXXV-XLIV

Phase the Sixth: The Convert, XLV-LII

Phase the Seventh: Fulfilment, LIII-LIX

Phase the First: The Maiden

I

On an evening in the latter part of May a middle-aged man was walking

homeward from Shaston to the village of Marlott, in the adjoining

Vale of Blakemore, or Blackmoor. The pair of legs that carried him

were rickety, and there was a bias in his gait which inclined him

somewhat to the left of a straight line. He occasionally gave a

smart nod, as if in confirmation of some opinion, though he was not

thinking of anything in particular. An empty egg-basket was slung

upon his arm, the nap of his hat was ruffled, a patch being quite

worn away at its brim where his thumb came in taking it off.

Presently he was met by an elderly parson astride on a gray mare,

who, as he rode, hummed a wandering tune.

"Good night t'ee," said the man with the basket.

"Good night, Sir John," said the parson.

The pedestrian, after another pace or two, halted, and turned round.

"Now, sir, begging your pardon; we met last market-day on this road

about this time, and I said 'Good night,' and you made reply '_Good

night, Sir John_,' as now."

"I did," said the parson.

"And once before that--near a month ago."

"I may have."

"Then what might your meaning be in calling me 'Sir John' these

different times, when I be plain Jack Durbeyfield, the haggler?"

The parson rode a step or two nearer.

"It was only my whim," he said; and, after a moment's hesitation: "It

was on account of a discovery I made some little time ago, whilst I

was hunting up pedigrees for the new county history. I am Parson

Tringham, the antiquary, of Stagfoot Lane. Don't you really know,

Durbeyfield, that you are the lineal representative of the ancient

and knightly family of the d'Urbervilles, who derive their descent

from Sir Pagan d'Urberville, that renowned knight who came from

Normandy with William the Conqueror, as appears by Battle Abbey

Roll?"

"Never heard it before, sir!"

"Well it's true. Throw up your chin a moment, so that I may catch

the profile of your face better. Yes, that's the d'Urberville nose

and chin--a little debased. Your ancestor was one of the twelve

knights who assisted the Lord of Estremavilla in Normandy in his

conquest of Glamorganshire. Branches of your family held manors over

all this part of England; their names appear in the Pipe Rolls in the

time of King Stephen. In the reign of King John one of them was rich

enough to give a manor to the Knights Hospitallers; and in Edward the

Second's time your forefather Brian was summoned to Westminster to

attend the great Council there. You declined a little in Oliver

Cromwell's time, but to no serious extent, and in Charles the

Second's reign you were made Knights of the Royal Oak for your

loyalty. Aye, there have been generations of Sir Johns among

you, and if knighthood were hereditary, like a baronetcy, as it

practically was in old times, when men were knighted from father

to son, you would be Sir John now."

"Ye don't say so!"

"In short," concluded the parson, decisively smacking his leg with

his switch, "there's hardly such another family in England."

"Daze my eyes, and isn't there?" said Durbeyfield. "And here have I

been knocking about, year after year, from pillar to post, as if I

was no more than the commonest feller in the parish... And how long

hev this news about me been knowed, Pa'son Tringham?"

The clergyman explained that, as far as he was aware, it had quite

died out of knowledge, and could hardly be said to be known at all.

His own investigations had begun on a day in the preceding spring

when, having been engaged in tracing the vicissitudes of the

d'Urberville family, he had observed Durbeyfield's name on his

waggon, and had thereupon been led to make inquiries about his

father and grandfather till he had no doubt on the subject.

"At first I resolved not to disturb you with such a useless piece of

information," said he. "However, our impulses are too strong for our

judgement sometimes. I thought you might perhaps know something of

it all the while."

"Well, I have heard once or twice, 'tis true, that my family had seen

better days afore they came to Blackmoor. But I took no notice o't,

thinking it to mean that we had once kept two horses where we now

keep only one. I've got a wold silver spoon, and a wold graven seal

at home, too; but, Lord, what's a spoon and seal? ... And to think

that I and these noble d'Urbervilles were one flesh all the time.

'Twas said that my gr't-granfer had secrets, and didn't care to talk

of where he came from... And where do we raise our smoke, now,

parson, if I may make so bold; I mean, where do we d'Urbervilles

live?"

"You don't live anywhere. You are extinct--as a county family."

"That's bad."

"Yes--what the mendacious family chronicles call extinct in the male

line--that is, gone down--gone under."

"Then where do we lie?"

"At Kingsbere-sub-Greenhill: rows and rows of you in your vaults,

with your effigies under Purbeck-marble canopies."

"And where be our family mansions and estates?"

"You haven't any."

"Oh? No lands neither?"

"None; though you once had 'em in abundance, as I said, for you

family consisted of numerous branches. In this county there was a

seat of yours at Kingsbere, and another at Sherton, and another in

Millpond, and another at Lullstead, and another at Wellbridge."

"And shall we ever come into our own again?"

"Ah--that I can't tell!"

"And what had I better do about it, sir?" asked Durbeyfield, after a

pause.

"Oh--nothing, nothing; except chasten yourself with the thought of

'how are the mighty fallen.' It is a fact of some interest to the

local historian and genealogist, nothing more. There are several

families among the cottagers of this county of almost equal lustre.

Good night."

"But you'll turn back and have a quart of beer wi' me on the strength

o't, Pa'son Tringham? There's a very pretty brew in tap at The Pure

Drop--though, to be sure, not so good as at Rolliver's."

"No, thank you--not this evening, Durbeyfield. You've had enough

already." Concluding thus, the parson rode on his way, with doubts

as to his discretion in retailing this curious bit of lore.

When he was gone, Durbeyfield walked a few steps in a profound

reverie, and then sat down upon the grassy bank by the roadside,

depositing his basket before him. In a few minutes a youth appeared

in the distance, walking in the same direction as that which had been

pursued by Durbeyfield. The latter, on seeing him, held up his hand,

and the lad quickened his pace and came near.

"Boy, take up that basket! I want 'ee to go on an errand for me."

The lath-like stripling frowned. "Who be you, then, John

Durbeyfield, to order me about and call me 'boy'? You know my

name as well as I know yours!"

"Do you, do you? That's the secret--that's the secret! Now obey my

orders, and take the message I'm going to charge 'ee wi'... Well,

Fred, I don't mind telling you that the secret is that I'm one of a

noble race--it has been just found out by me this present afternoon,

P.M." And as he made the announcement, Durbeyfield, declining from

his sitting position, luxuriously stretched himself out upon the bank

among the daisies.

The lad stood before Durbeyfield, and contemplated his length from

crown to toe.

"Sir John d'Urberville--that's who I am," continued the prostrate

man. "That is if knights were baronets--which they be. 'Tis

recorded in history all about me. Dost know of such a place, lad,

as Kingsbere-sub-Greenhill?"

"Ees. I've been there to Greenhill Fair."

"Well, under the church of that city there lie--"

"'Tisn't a city, the place I mean; leastwise 'twaddn' when I was

there--'twas a little one-eyed, blinking sort o' place."

"Never you mind the place, boy, that's not the question before us.

Under the church of that there parish lie my ancestors--hundreds of

'em--in coats of mail and jewels, in gr't lead coffins weighing tons

and tons. There's not a man in the county o' South-Wessex that's

got grander and nobler skillentons in his family than I."

"Oh?"

"Now take up that basket, and goo on to Marlott, and when you've come

to The Pure Drop Inn, tell 'em to send a horse and carriage to me

immed'ately, to carry me hwome. And in the bottom o' the carriage

they be to put a noggin o' rum in a small bottle, and chalk it up

to my account. And when you've done that goo on to my house with

the basket, and tell my wife to put away that washing, because she

needn't finish it, and wait till I come hwome, as I've news to tell

her."

As the lad stood in a dubious attitude, Durbeyfield put his hand in

his pocket, and produced a shilling, one of the chronically few that

he possessed.

"Here's for your labour, lad."

This made a difference in the young man's estimate of the position.

"Yes, Sir John. Thank 'ee. Anything else I can do for 'ee, Sir

John?"

"Tell 'em at hwome that I should like for supper,--well, lamb's fry

if they can get it; and if they can't, black-pot; and if they can't

get that, well chitterlings will do."

"Yes, Sir John."

The boy took up the basket, and as he set out the notes of a brass

band were heard from the direction of the village.

"What's that?" said Durbeyfield. "Not on account o' I?"

"'Tis the women's club-walking, Sir John. Why, your da'ter is one o'

the members."

"To be sure--I'd quite forgot it in my thoughts of greater things!

Well, vamp on to Marlott, will ye, and order that carriage, and

maybe I'll drive round and inspect the club."

The lad departed, and Durbeyfield lay waiting on the grass and

daisies in the evening sun. Not a soul passed that way for a long

while, and the faint notes of the band were the only human sounds

audible within the rim of blue hills.

II

The village of Marlott lay amid the north-eastern undulations of the

beautiful Vale of Blakemore, or Blackmoor, aforesaid, an engirdled

and secluded region, for the most part untrodden as yet by tourist or

landscape-painter, though within a four hours' journey from London.

It is a vale whose acquaintance is best made by viewing it from the

summits of the hills that surround it--except perhaps during the

droughts of summer. An unguided ramble into its recesses in bad

weather is apt to engender dissatisfaction with its narrow, tortuous,

and miry ways.

This fertile and sheltered tract of country, in which the fields are

never brown and the springs never dry, is bounded on the south by the

bold chalk ridge that embraces the prominences of Hambledon Hill,

Bulbarrow, Nettlecombe-Tout, Dogbury, High Stoy, and Bubb Down. The

traveller from the coast, who, after plodding northward for a score

of miles over calcareous downs and corn-lands, suddenly reaches

the verge of one of these escarpments, is surprised and delighted

to behold, extended like a map beneath him, a country differing

absolutely from that which he has passed through. Behind him the

hills are open, the sun blazes down upon fields so large as to give

an unenclosed character to the landscape, the lanes are white, the

hedges low and plashed, the atmosphere colourless. Here, in the

valley, the world seems to be constructed upon a smaller and more

delicate scale; the fields are mere paddocks, so reduced that from

this height their hedgerows appear a network of dark green threads

overspreading the paler green of the grass. The atmosphere beneath

is languorous, and is so tinged with azure that what artists call the

middle distance partakes also of that hue, while the horizon beyond

is of the deepest ultramarine. Arable lands are few and limited;

with but slight exceptions the prospect is a broad rich mass of grass

and trees, mantling minor hills and dales within the major. Such is

the Vale of Blackmoor.

The district is of historic, no less than of topographical interest.

The Vale was known in former times as the Forest of White Hart, from

a curious legend of King Henry III's reign, in which the killing by

a certain Thomas de la Lynd of a beautiful white hart which the king

had run down and spared, was made the occasion of a heavy fine.

In those days, and till comparatively recent times, the country was

densely wooded. Even now, traces of its earlier condition are to be

found in the old oak copses and irregular belts of timber that yet

survive upon its slopes, and the hollow-trunked trees that shade so

many of its pastures.

The forests have departed, but some old customs of their shades

remain. Many, however, linger only in a metamorphosed or disguised

form. The May-Day dance, for instance, was to be discerned on

the afternoon under notice, in the guise of the club revel, or

"club-walking," as it was there called.

It was an interesting event to the younger inhabitants of Marlott,

though its real interest was not observed by the participators in the

ceremony. Its singularity lay less in the retention of a custom of

walking in procession and dancing on each anniversary than in the

members being solely women. In men's clubs such celebrations were,

though expiring, less uncommon; but either the natural shyness of the

softer sex, or a sarcastic attitude on the part of male relatives,

had denuded such women's clubs as remained (if any other did) or this

their glory and consummation. The club of Marlott alone lived to

uphold the local Cerealia. It had walked for hundreds of years, if

not as benefit-club, as votive sisterhood of some sort; and it walked

still.

The banded ones were all dressed in white gowns--a gay survival from

Old Style days, when cheerfulness and May-time were synonyms--days

before the habit of taking long views had reduced emotions to a

monotonous average. Their first exhibition of themselves was in a

processional march of two and two round the parish. Ideal and real

clashed slightly as the sun lit up their figures against the green

hedges and creeper-laced house-fronts; for, though the whole troop

wore white garments, no two whites were alike among them. Some

approached pure blanching; some had a bluish pallor; some worn by the

older characters (which had possibly lain by folded for many a year)

inclined to a cadaverous tint, and to a Georgian style.

In addition to the distinction of a white frock, every woman and girl

carried in her right hand a peeled willow wand, and in her left a

bunch of white flowers. The peeling of the former, and the selection

of the latter, had been an operation of personal care.

There were a few middle-aged and even elderly women in the train,

their silver-wiry hair and wrinkled faces, scourged by time and

trouble, having almost a grotesque, certainly a pathetic, appearance

in such a jaunty situation. In a true view, perhaps, there was more

to be gathered and told of each anxious and experienced one, to whom

the years were drawing nigh when she should say, "I have no pleasure

in them," than of her juvenile comrades. But let the elder be passed

over here for those under whose bodices the life throbbed quick and

warm.

The young girls formed, indeed, the majority of the band, and their

heads of luxuriant hair reflected in the sunshine every tone of gold,

and black, and brown. Some had beautiful eyes, others a beautiful

nose, others a beautiful mouth and figure: few, if any, had all. A

difficulty of arranging their lips in this crude exposure to public

scrutiny, an inability to balance their heads, and to dissociate

self-consciousness from their features, was apparent in them, and

showed that they were genuine country girls, unaccustomed to many

eyes.

And as each and all of them were warmed without by the sun, so each

had a private little sun for her soul to bask in; some dream, some

affection, some hobby, at least some remote and distant hope which,

though perhaps starving to nothing, still lived on, as hopes will.

They were all cheerful, and many of them merry.

They came round by The Pure Drop Inn, and were turning out of the

high road to pass through a wicket-gate into the meadows, when one of

the women said--

"The Load-a-Lord! Why, Tess Durbeyfield, if there isn't thy father

riding hwome in a carriage!"

A young member of the band turned her head at the exclamation.

She was a fine and handsome girl--not handsomer than some others,

possibly--but her mobile peony mouth and large innocent eyes added

eloquence to colour and shape. She wore a red ribbon in her hair,

and was the only one of the white company who could boast of such

a pronounced adornment. As she looked round Durbeyfield was seen

moving along the road in a chaise belonging to The Pure Drop, driven

by a frizzle-headed brawny damsel with her gown-sleeves rolled above

her elbows. This was the cheerful servant of that establishment,

who, in her part of factotum, turned groom and ostler at times.

Durbeyfield, leaning back, and with his eyes closed luxuriously, was

waving his hand above his head, and singing in a slow recitative--

"I've-got-a-gr't-family-vault-at-Kingsbere--and

knighted-forefathers-in-lead-coffins-there!"

The clubbists tittered, except the girl called Tess--in whom a slow

heat seemed to rise at the sense that her father was making himself

foolish in their eyes.

"He's tired, that's all," she said hastily, "and he has got a lift

home, because our own horse has to rest to-day."

"Bless thy simplicity, Tess," said her companions. "He's got his

market-nitch. Haw-haw!"

"Look here; I won't walk another inch with you, if you say any jokes

about him!" Tess cried, and the colour upon her cheeks spread over

her face and neck. In a moment her eyes grew moist, and her glance

drooped to the ground. Perceiving that they had really pained her

they said no more, and order again prevailed. Tess's pride would not

allow her to turn her head again, to learn what her father's meaning

was, if he had any; and thus she moved on with the whole body to the

enclosure where there was to be dancing on the green. By the time

the spot was reached she has recovered her equanimity, and tapped her

neighbour with her wand and talked as usual.

Tess Durbeyfield at this time of her life was a mere vessel of

emotion untinctured by experience. The dialect was on her tongue

to some extent, despite the village school: the characteristic

intonation of that dialect for this district being the voicing

approximately rendered by the syllable UR, probably as rich an

utterance as any to be found in human speech. The pouted-up deep red

mouth to which this syllable was native had hardly as yet settled

into its definite shape, and her lower lip had a way of thrusting the

middle of her top one upward, when they closed together after a word.

Phases of her childhood lurked in her aspect still. As she walked

along to-day, for all her bouncing handsome womanliness, you could

sometimes see her twelfth year in her cheeks, or her ninth sparkling

from her eyes; and even her fifth would flit over the curves of her

mouth now and then.

Yet few knew, and still fewer considered this. A small minority,

mainly strangers, would look long at her in casually passing by, and

grow momentarily fascinated by her freshness, and wonder if they

would ever see her again: but to almost everybody she was a fine and

picturesque country girl, and no more.

Nothing was seen or heard further of Durbeyfield in his triumphal

chariot under the conduct of the ostleress, and the club having

entered the allotted space, dancing began. As there were no men in

the company, the girls danced at first with each other, but when the

hour for the close of labour drew on, the masculine inhabitants of

the village, together with other idlers and pedestrians, gathered

round the spot, and appeared inclined to negotiate for a partner.

Among these on-lookers were three young men of a superior class,

carrying small knapsacks strapped to their shoulders, and stout

sticks in their hands. Their general likeness to each other, and

their consecutive ages, would almost have suggested that they might

be, what in fact they were, brothers. The eldest wore the white tie,

high waistcoat, and thin-brimmed hat of the regulation curate; the

second was the normal undergraduate; the appearance of the third and

youngest would hardly have been sufficient to characterize him; there

was an uncribbed, uncabined aspect in his eyes and attire, implying

that he had hardly as yet found the entrance to his professional

groove. That he was a desultory tentative student of something and

everything might only have been predicted of him.

These three brethren told casual acquaintance that they were spending

their Whitsun holidays in a walking tour through the Vale of

Blackmoor, their course being south-westerly from the town of Shaston

on the north-east.

They leant over the gate by the highway, and inquired as to the

meaning of the dance and the white-frocked maids. The two elder of

the brothers were plainly not intending to linger more than a moment,

but the spectacle of a bevy of girls dancing without male partners

seemed to amuse the third, and make him in no hurry to move on. He

unstrapped his knapsack, put it, with his stick, on the hedge-bank,

and opened the gate.

"What are you going to do, Angel?" asked the eldest.

"I am inclined to go and have a fling with them. Why not all of

us--just for a minute or two--it will not detain us long?"

"No--no; nonsense!" said the first. "Dancing in public with a troop

of country hoydens--suppose we should be seen! Come along, or it

will be dark before we get to Stourcastle, and there's no place we

can sleep at nearer than that; besides, we must get through another

chapter of _A Counterblast to Agnosticism_ before we turn in, now I

have taken the trouble to bring the book."

"All right--I'll overtake you and Cuthbert in five minutes; don't

stop; I give my word that I will, Felix."

The two elder reluctantly left him and walked on, taking their

brother's knapsack to relieve him in following, and the youngest

entered the field.

"This is a thousand pities," he said gallantly, to two or three of

the girls nearest him, as soon as there was a pause in the dance.

"Where are your partners, my dears?"

"They've not left off work yet," answered one of the boldest.

"They'll be here by and by. Till then, will you be one, sir?"

"Certainly. But what's one among so many!"

"Better than none. 'Tis melancholy work facing and footing it to one

of your own sort, and no clipsing and colling at all. Now, pick and

choose."

"'Ssh--don't be so for'ard!" said a shyer girl.

The young man, thus invited, glanced them over, and attempted some

discrimination; but, as the group were all so new to him, he could

not very well exercise it. He took almost the first that came to

hand, which was not the speaker, as she had expected; nor did it

happen to be Tess Durbeyfield. Pedigree, ancestral skeletons,

monumental record, the d'Urberville lineaments, did not help Tess in

her life's battle as yet, even to the extent of attracting to her a

dancing-partner over the heads of the commonest peasantry. So much

for Norman blood unaided by Victorian lucre.

The name of the eclipsing girl, whatever it was, has not been handed

down; but she was envied by all as the first who enjoyed the luxury

of a masculine partner that evening. Yet such was the force of

example that the village young men, who had not hastened to enter

the gate while no intruder was in the way, now dropped in quickly,

and soon the couples became leavened with rustic youth to a marked

extent, till at length the plainest woman in the club was no longer

compelled to foot it on the masculine side of the figure.

The church clock struck, when suddenly the student said that he must

leave--he had been forgetting himself--he had to join his companions.

As he fell out of the dance his eyes lighted on Tess Durbeyfield,

whose own large orbs wore, to tell the truth, the faintest aspect of

reproach that he had not chosen her. He, too, was sorry then that,

owing to her backwardness, he had not observed her; and with that in

his mind he left the pasture.

On account of his long delay he started in a flying-run down the lane

westward, and had soon passed the hollow and mounted the next rise.

He had not yet overtaken his brothers, but he paused to get breath,

and looked back. He could see the white figures of the girls in the

green enclosure whirling about as they had whirled when he was among

them. They seemed to have quite forgotten him already.

All of them, except, perhaps, one. This white shape stood apart

by the hedge alone. From her position he knew it to be the pretty

maiden with whom he had not danced. Trifling as the matter was, he

yet instinctively felt that she was hurt by his oversight. He wished

that he had asked her; he wished that he had inquired her name. She

was so modest, so expressive, she had looked so soft in her thin

white gown that he felt he had acted stupidly.

However, it could not be helped, and turning, and bending himself to

a rapid walk, he dismissed the subject from his mind.

III

As for Tess Durbeyfield, she did not so easily dislodge the incident

from her consideration. She had no spirit to dance again for a long

time, though she might have had plenty of partners; but ah! they did

not speak so nicely as the strange young man had done. It was not

till the rays of the sun had absorbed the young stranger's retreating

figure on the hill that she shook off her temporary sadness and

answered her would-be partner in the affirmative.

She remained with her comrades till dusk, and participated with a

certain zest in the dancing; though, being heart-whole as yet, she

enjoyed treading a measure purely for its own sake; little divining

when she saw "the soft torments, the bitter sweets, the pleasing

pains, and the agreeable distresses" of those girls who had been

wooed and won, what she herself was capable of in that kind. The

struggles and wrangles of the lads for her hand in a jig were an

amusement to her--no more; and when they became fierce she rebuked

them.

She might have stayed even later, but the incident of her father's

odd appearance and manner returned upon the girl's mind to make her

anxious, and wondering what had become of him she dropped away from

the dancers and bent her steps towards the end of the village at

which the parental cottage lay.

While yet many score yards off, other rhythmic sounds than those she

had quitted became audible to her; sounds that she knew well--so

well. They were a regular series of thumpings from the interior of

the house, occasioned by the violent rocking of a cradle upon a stone

floor, to which movement a feminine voice kept time by singing, in a

vigorous gallopade, the favourite ditty of "The Spotted Cow"--

I saw her lie do'-own in yon'-der green gro'-ove;

Come, love!' and I'll tell' you where!'

The cradle-rocking and the song would cease simultaneously for a

moment, and an exclamation at highest vocal pitch would take the

place of the melody.

"God bless thy diment eyes! And thy waxen cheeks! And thy cherry

mouth! And thy Cubit's thighs! And every bit o' thy blessed body!"

After this invocation the rocking and the singing would recommence,

and the "Spotted Cow" proceed as before. So matters stood when Tess

opened the door and paused upon the mat within it, surveying the

scene.

The interior, in spite of the melody, struck upon the girl's senses

with an unspeakable dreariness. From the holiday gaieties of the

field--the white gowns, the nosegays, the willow-wands, the whirling

movements on the green, the flash of gentle sentiment towards the

stranger--to the yellow melancholy of this one-candled spectacle,

what a step! Besides the jar of contrast there came to her a chill

self-reproach that she had not returned sooner, to help her mother

in these domesticities, instead of indulging herself out-of-doors.

There stood her mother amid the group of children, as Tess had left

her, hanging over the Monday washing-tub, which had now, as always,

lingered on to the end of the week. Out of that tub had come the day

before--Tess felt it with a dreadful sting of remorse--the very white

frock upon her back which she had so carelessly greened about the

skirt on the damping grass--which had been wrung up and ironed by her

mother's own hands.

As usual, Mrs Durbeyfield was balanced on one foot beside the tub,

the other being engaged in the aforesaid business of rocking her

youngest child. The cradle-rockers had done hard duty for so many

years, under the weight of so many children, on that flagstone floor,

that they were worn nearly flat, in consequence of which a huge jerk

accompanied each swing of the cot, flinging the baby from side to

side like a weaver's shuttle, as Mrs Durbeyfield, excited by her

song, trod the rocker with all the spring that was left in her after

a long day's seething in the suds.

Nick-knock, nick-knock, went the cradle; the candle-flame stretched

itself tall, and began jigging up and down; the water dribbled from

the matron's elbows, and the song galloped on to the end of the

verse, Mrs Durbeyfield regarding her daughter the while. Even now,

when burdened with a young family, Joan Durbeyfield was a passionate

lover of tune. No ditty floated into Blackmoor Vale from the outer

world but Tess's mother caught up its notation in a week.

There still faintly beamed from the woman's features something of

the freshness, and even the prettiness, of her youth; rendering it

probable that the personal charms which Tess could boast of were in

main part her mother's gift, and therefore unknightly, unhistorical.

"I'll rock the cradle for 'ee, mother," said the daughter gently.

"Or I'll take off my best frock and help you wring up? I thought you

had finished long ago."

Her mother bore Tess no ill-will for leaving the housework to her

single-handed efforts for so long; indeed, Joan seldom upbraided

her thereon at any time, feeling but slightly the lack of Tess's

assistance whilst her instinctive plan for relieving herself of her

labours lay in postponing them. To-night, however, she was even in a

blither mood than usual. There was a dreaminess, a pre-occupation,

an exaltation, in the maternal look which the girl could not

understand.

"Well, I'm glad you've come," her mother said, as soon as the last

note had passed out of her. "I want to go and fetch your father;

but what's more'n that, I want to tell 'ee what have happened. Y'll

be fess enough, my poppet, when th'st know!" (Mrs Durbeyfield

habitually spoke the dialect; her daughter, who had passed the Sixth

Standard in the National School under a London-trained mistress,

spoke two languages: the dialect at home, more or less; ordinary

English abroad and to persons of quality.)

"Since I've been away?" Tess asked.

"Ay!"

"Had it anything to do with father's making such a mommet of himself

in thik carriage this afternoon? Why did 'er? I felt inclined to

sink into the ground with shame!"

"That wer all a part of the larry! We've been found to be the

greatest gentlefolk in the whole county--reaching all back long

before Oliver Grumble's time--to the days of the Pagan Turks--with

monuments, and vaults, and crests, and 'scutcheons, and the Lord

knows what all. In Saint Charles's days we was made Knights o' the

Royal Oak, our real name being d'Urberville! ... Don't that make

your bosom plim? 'Twas on this account that your father rode home

in the vlee; not because he'd been drinking, as people supposed."

"I'm glad of that. Will it do us any good, mother?"

"O yes! 'Tis thoughted that great things may come o't. No doubt a

mampus of volk of our own rank will be down here in their carriages

as soon as 'tis known. Your father learnt it on his way hwome

from Shaston, and he has been telling me the whole pedigree of the

matter."

"Where is father now?" asked Tess suddenly.

Her mother gave irrelevant information by way of answer: "He called

to see the doctor to-day in Shaston. It is not consumption at all,

it seems. It is fat round his heart, 'a says. There, it is like

this." Joan Durbeyfield, as she spoke, curved a sodden thumb

and forefinger to the shape of the letter C, and used the other

forefinger as a pointer. "'At the present moment,' he says to your

father, 'your heart is enclosed all round there, and all round

there; this space is still open,' 'a says. 'As soon as it do

meet, so,'"--Mrs Durbeyfield closed her fingers into a circle

complete--"'off you will go like a shadder, Mr Durbeyfield,' 'a says.

'You mid last ten years; you mid go off in ten months, or ten days.'"

Tess looked alarmed. Her father possibly to go behind the eternal

cloud so soon, notwithstanding this sudden greatness!

"But where IS father?" she asked again.

Her mother put on a deprecating look. "Now don't you be bursting out

angry! The poor man--he felt so rafted after his uplifting by the

pa'son's news--that he went up to Rolliver's half an hour ago. He do

want to get up his strength for his journey to-morrow with that load

of beehives, which must be delivered, family or no. He'll have to

start shortly after twelve to-night, as the distance is so long."

"Get up his strength!" said Tess impetuously, the tears welling to

her eyes. "O my God! Go to a public-house to get up his strength!

And you as well agreed as he, mother!"

Her rebuke and her mood seemed to fill the whole room, and to impart

a cowed look to the furniture, and candle, and children playing

about, and to her mother's face.

"No," said the latter touchily, "I be not agreed. I have been

waiting for 'ee to bide and keep house while I go fetch him."

"I'll go."

"O no, Tess. You see, it would be no use."

Tess did not expostulate. She knew what her mother's objection

meant. Mrs Durbeyfield's jacket and bonnet were already hanging

slily upon a chair by her side, in readiness for this contemplated

jaunt, the reason for which the matron deplored more than its

necessity.

"And take the _Compleat Fortune-Teller_ to the outhouse," Joan

continued, rapidly wiping her hands, and donning the garments.

The _Compleat Fortune-Teller_ was an old thick volume, which lay on a

table at her elbow, so worn by pocketing that the margins had reached

the edge of the type. Tess took it up, and her mother started.

This going to hunt up her shiftless husband at the inn was one of

Mrs Durbeyfield's still extant enjoyments in the muck and muddle of

rearing children. To discover him at Rolliver's, to sit there for

an hour or two by his side and dismiss all thought and care of the

children during the interval, made her happy. A sort of halo, an

occidental glow, came over life then. Troubles and other realities

took on themselves a metaphysical impalpability, sinking to mere

mental phenomena for serene contemplation, and no longer stood as

pressing concretions which chafed body and soul. The youngsters,

not immediately within sight, seemed rather bright and desirable

appurtenances than otherwise; the incidents of daily life were not

without humorousness and jollity in their aspect there. She felt a

little as she had used to feel when she sat by her now wedded husband

in the same spot during his wooing, shutting her eyes to his defects

of character, and regarding him only in his ideal presentation as

lover.

Tess, being left alone with the younger children, went first to the

outhouse with the fortune-telling book, and stuffed it into the

thatch. A curious fetishistic fear of this grimy volume on the part

of her mother prevented her ever allowing it to stay in the house all

night, and hither it was brought back whenever it had been consulted.

Between the mother, with her fast-perishing lumber of superstitions,

folk-lore, dialect, and orally transmitted ballads, and the daughter,

with her trained National teachings and Standard knowledge under an

infinitely Revised Code, there was a gap of two hundred years as

ordinarily understood. When they were together the Jacobean and the

Victorian ages were juxtaposed.

Returning along the garden path Tess mused on what the mother could

have wished to ascertain from the book on this particular day. She

guessed the recent ancestral discovery to bear upon it, but did not

divine that it solely concerned herself. Dismissing this, however,

she busied herself with sprinkling the linen dried during the

day-time, in company with her nine-year-old brother Abraham, and her

sister Eliza-Louisa of twelve and a half, called "'Liza-Lu," the

youngest ones being put to bed. There was an interval of four years

and more between Tess and the next of the family, the two who had

filled the gap having died in their infancy, and this lent her a

deputy-maternal attitude when she was alone with her juniors. Next

in juvenility to Abraham came two more girls, Hope and Modesty; then

a boy of three, and then the baby, who had just completed his first

year.

All these young souls were passengers in the Durbeyfield

ship--entirely dependent on the judgement of the two Durbeyfield

adults for their pleasures, their necessities, their health, even

their existence. If the heads of the Durbeyfield household chose

to sail into difficulty, disaster, starvation, disease, degradation,

death, thither were these half-dozen little captives under hatches

compelled to sail with them--six helpless creatures, who had never

been asked if they wished for life on any terms, much less if they

wished for it on such hard conditions as were involved in being of

the shiftless house of Durbeyfield. Some people would like to know

whence the poet whose philosophy is in these days deemed as profound

and trustworthy as his song is breezy and pure, gets his authority

for speaking of "Nature's holy plan."

It grew later, and neither father nor mother reappeared. Tess looked

out of the door, and took a mental journey through Marlott. The

village was shutting its eyes. Candles and lamps were being put

out everywhere: she could inwardly behold the extinguisher and the

extended hand.

Her mother's fetching simply meant one more to fetch. Tess began to

perceive that a man in indifferent health, who proposed to start on a

journey before one in the morning, ought not to be at an inn at this

late hour celebrating his ancient blood.

"Abraham," she said to her little brother, "do you put on your

hat--you bain't afraid?--and go up to Rolliver's, and see what has

gone wi' father and mother."

The boy jumped promptly from his seat, and opened the door, and the

night swallowed him up. Half an hour passed yet again; neither man,

woman, nor child returned. Abraham, like his parents, seemed to have

been limed and caught by the ensnaring inn.

"I must go myself," she said.

'Liza-Lu then went to bed, and Tess, locking them all in, started on

her way up the dark and crooked lane or street not made for hasty

progress; a street laid out before inches of land had value, and when

one-handed clocks sufficiently subdivided the day.

IV

Rolliver's inn, the single alehouse at this end of the long and

broken village, could only boast of an off-licence; hence, as

nobody could legally drink on the premises, the amount of overt

accommodation for consumers was strictly limited to a little board

about six inches wide and two yards long, fixed to the garden palings

by pieces of wire, so as to form a ledge. On this board thirsty

strangers deposited their cups as they stood in the road and drank,

and threw the dregs on the dusty ground to the pattern of Polynesia,

and wished they could have a restful seat inside.

Thus the strangers. But there were also local customers who felt the

same wish; and where there's a will there's a way.

In a large bedroom upstairs, the window of which was thickly

curtained with a great woollen shawl lately discarded by the

landlady, Mrs Rolliver, were gathered on this evening nearly a dozen

persons, all seeking beatitude; all old inhabitants of the nearer

end of Marlott, and frequenters of this retreat. Not only did the

distance to the The Pure Drop, the fully-licensed tavern at the

further part of the dispersed village, render its accommodation

practically unavailable for dwellers at this end; but the far more

serious question, the quality of the liquor, confirmed the prevalent

opinion that it was better to drink with Rolliver in a corner of the

housetop than with the other landlord in a wide house.

A gaunt four-post bedstead which stood in the room afforded

sitting-space for several persons gathered round three of its sides;

a couple more men had elevated themselves on a chest of drawers;

another rested on the oak-carved "cwoffer"; two on the wash-stand;

another on the stool; and thus all were, somehow, seated at their

ease. The stage of mental comfort to which they had arrived at this

hour was one wherein their souls expanded beyond their skins, and

spread their personalities warmly through the room. In this process

the chamber and its furniture grew more and more dignified and

luxurious; the shawl hanging at the window took upon itself the

richness of tapestry; the brass handles of the chest of drawers were

as golden knockers; and the carved bedposts seemed to have some

kinship with the magnificent pillars of Solomon's temple.

Mrs Durbeyfield, having quickly walked hitherward after parting from

Tess, opened the front door, crossed the downstairs room, which was

in deep gloom, and then unfastened the stair-door like one whose

fingers knew the tricks of the latches well. Her ascent of the

crooked staircase was a slower process, and her face, as it rose into

the light above the last stair, encountered the gaze of all the party

assembled in the bedroom.

"--Being a few private friends I've asked in to keep up club-walking

at my own expense," the landlady exclaimed at the sound of footsteps,

as glibly as a child repeating the Catechism, while she peered over

the stairs. "Oh, 'tis you, Mrs Durbeyfield--Lard--how you frightened

me!--I thought it might be some gaffer sent by Gover'ment."

Mrs Durbeyfield was welcomed with glances and nods by the remainder

of the conclave, and turned to where her husband sat. He was humming

absently to himself, in a low tone: "I be as good as some folks here

and there! I've got a great family vault at Kingsbere-sub-Greenhill,

and finer skillentons than any man in Wessex!"

"I've something to tell 'ee that's come into my head about that--a

grand projick!" whispered his cheerful wife. "Here, John, don't 'ee

see me?" She nudged him, while he, looking through her as through a

window-pane, went on with his recitative.

"Hush! Don't 'ee sing so loud, my good man," said the landlady; "in

case any member of the Gover'ment should be passing, and take away my

licends."

"He's told 'ee what's happened to us, I suppose?" asked Mrs

Durbeyfield.

"Yes--in a way. D'ye think there's any money hanging by it?"

"Ah, that's the secret," said Joan Durbeyfield sagely. "However,

'tis well to be kin to a coach, even if you don't ride in 'en." She

dropped her public voice, and continued in a low tone to her husband:

"I've been thinking since you brought the news that there's a great

rich lady out by Trantridge, on the edge o' The Chase, of the name of

d'Urberville."

"Hey--what's that?" said Sir John.

She repeated the information. "That lady must be our relation," she

said. "And my projick is to send Tess to claim kin."

"There IS a lady of the name, now you mention it," said Durbeyfield.

"Pa'son Tringham didn't think of that. But she's nothing beside

we--a junior branch of us, no doubt, hailing long since King Norman's

day."

While this question was being discussed neither of the pair noticed,

in their preoccupation, that little Abraham had crept into the room,

and was awaiting an opportunity of asking them to return.

"She is rich, and she'd be sure to take notice o' the maid,"

continued Mrs Durbeyfield; "and 'twill be a very good thing. I don't

see why two branches o' one family should not be on visiting terms."

"Yes; and we'll all claim kin!" said Abraham brightly from under the

bedstead. "And we'll all go and see her when Tess has gone to live

with her; and we'll ride in her coach and wear black clothes!"

"How do you come here, child? What nonsense be ye talking! Go away,

and play on the stairs till father and mother be ready! ... Well,

Tess ought to go to this other member of our family. She'd be sure

to win the lady--Tess would; and likely enough 'twould lead to some

noble gentleman marrying her. In short, I know it."

"How?"

"I tried her fate in the _Fortune-Teller_, and it brought out that

very thing! ... You should ha' seen how pretty she looked to-day;

her skin is as sumple as a duchess'."

"What says the maid herself to going?"

"I've not asked her. She don't know there is any such lady-relation

yet. But it would certainly put her in the way of a grand marriage,

and she won't say nay to going."

"Tess is queer."

"But she's tractable at bottom. Leave her to me."

Though this conversation had been private, sufficient of its import

reached the understandings of those around to suggest to them that

the Durbeyfields had weightier concerns to talk of now than common

folks had, and that Tess, their pretty eldest daughter, had fine

prospects in store.

"Tess is a fine figure o' fun, as I said to myself to-day when I zeed

her vamping round parish with the rest," observed one of the elderly

boozers in an undertone. "But Joan Durbeyfield must mind that she

don't get green malt in floor." It was a local phrase which had a

peculiar meaning, and there was no reply.

The conversation became inclusive, and presently other footsteps were

heard crossing the room below.

"--Being a few private friends asked in to-night to keep up

club-walking at my own expense." The landlady had rapidly re-used

the formula she kept on hand for intruders before she recognized that

the newcomer was Tess.

Even to her mother's gaze the girl's young features looked sadly

out of place amid the alcoholic vapours which floated here as

no unsuitable medium for wrinkled middle-age; and hardly was a

reproachful flash from Tess's dark eyes needed to make her father

and mother rise from their seats, hastily finish their ale, and

descend the stairs behind her, Mrs Rolliver's caution following

their footsteps.

"No noise, please, if ye'll be so good, my dears; or I mid lose my

licends, and be summons'd, and I don't know what all! 'Night t'ye!"

They went home together, Tess holding one arm of her father, and Mrs

Durbeyfield the other. He had, in truth, drunk very little--not a

fourth of the quantity which a systematic tippler could carry to

church on a Sunday afternoon without a hitch in his eastings or

genuflections; but the weakness of Sir John's constitution made

mountains of his petty sins in this kind. On reaching the fresh

air he was sufficiently unsteady to incline the row of three at one

moment as if they were marching to London, and at another as if they

were marching to Bath--which produced a comical effect, frequent

enough in families on nocturnal homegoings; and, like most comical

effects, not quite so comic after all. The two women valiantly

disguised these forced excursions and countermarches as well as they

could from Durbeyfield, their cause, and from Abraham, and from

themselves; and so they approached by degrees their own door, the

head of the family bursting suddenly into his former refrain as he

drew near, as if to fortify his soul at sight of the smallness of

his present residence--

"I've got a fam--ily vault at Kingsbere!"

"Hush--don't be so silly, Jacky," said his wife. "Yours is not the

only family that was of 'count in wold days. Look at the Anktells,

and Horseys, and the Tringhams themselves--gone to seed a'most as

much as you--though you was bigger folks than they, that's true.

Thank God, I was never of no family, and have nothing to be ashamed

of in that way!"

"Don't you be so sure o' that. From you nater 'tis my belief you've

disgraced yourselves more than any o' us, and was kings and queens

outright at one time."

Tess turned the subject by saying what was far more prominent in her

own mind at the moment than thoughts of her ancestry--"I am afraid

father won't be able to take the journey with the beehives to-morrow

so early."

"I? I shall be all right in an hour or two," said Durbeyfield.

It was eleven o'clock before the family were all in bed, and

two o'clock next morning was the latest hour for starting with

the beehives if they were to be delivered to the retailers in

Casterbridge before the Saturday market began, the way thither lying

by bad roads over a distance of between twenty and thirty miles, and

the horse and waggon being of the slowest. At half-past one Mrs

Durbeyfield came into the large bedroom where Tess and all her

little brothers and sisters slept.

"The poor man can't go," she said to her eldest daughter, whose great

eyes had opened the moment her mother's hand touched the door.

Tess sat up in bed, lost in a vague interspace between a dream and

this information.

"But somebody must go," she replied. "It is late for the hives

already. Swarming will soon be over for the year; and it we put off

taking 'em till next week's market the call for 'em will be past, and

they'll be thrown on our hands."

Mrs Durbeyfield looked unequal to the emergency. "Some young feller,

perhaps, would go? One of them who were so much after dancing with

'ee yesterday," she presently suggested.

"O no--I wouldn't have it for the world!" declared Tess proudly.

"And letting everybody know the reason--such a thing to be ashamed

of! I think _I_ could go if Abraham could go with me to kip me

company."

Her mother at length agreed to this arrangement. Little Abraham was

aroused from his deep sleep in a corner of the same apartment, and

made to put on his clothes while still mentally in the other world.

Meanwhile Tess had hastily dressed herself; and the twain, lighting

a lantern, went out to the stable. The rickety little waggon was

already laden, and the girl led out the horse, Prince, only a degree

less rickety than the vehicle.

The poor creature looked wonderingly round at the night, at the

lantern, at their two figures, as if he could not believe that at

that hour, when every living thing was intended to be in shelter and

at rest, he was called upon to go out and labour. They put a stock

of candle-ends into the lantern, hung the latter to the off-side of

the load, and directed the horse onward, walking at his shoulder at

first during the uphill parts of the way, in order not to overload

an animal of so little vigour. To cheer themselves as well as they

could, they made an artificial morning with the lantern, some bread

and butter, and their own conversation, the real morning being far

from come. Abraham, as he more fully awoke (for he had moved in a

sort of trance so far), began to talk of the strange shapes assumed

by the various dark objects against the sky; of this tree that looked

like a raging tiger springing from a lair; of that which resembled a

giant's head.

When they had passed the little town of Stourcastle, dumbly somnolent

under its thick brown thatch, they reached higher ground. Still

higher, on their left, the elevation called Bulbarrow, or Bealbarrow,

well-nigh the highest in South Wessex, swelled into the sky,

engirdled by its earthen trenches. From hereabout the long road was

fairly level for some distance onward. They mounted in front of the

waggon, and Abraham grew reflective.

"Tess!" he said in a preparatory tone, after a silence.

"Yes, Abraham."

"Bain't you glad that we've become gentlefolk?"

"Not particular glad."

"But you be glad that you 'm going to marry a gentleman?"

"What?" said Tess, lifting her face.

"That our great relation will help 'ee to marry a gentleman."

"I? Our great relation? We have no such relation. What has put

that into your head?"

"I heard 'em talking about it up at Rolliver's when I went to find

father. There's a rich lady of our family out at Trantridge, and

mother said that if you claimed kin with the lady, she'd put 'ee in

the way of marrying a gentleman."

His sister became abruptly still, and lapsed into a pondering

silence. Abraham talked on, rather for the pleasure of utterance

than for audition, so that his sister's abstraction was of no

account. He leant back against the hives, and with upturned face

made observations on the stars, whose cold pulses were beating

amid the black hollows above, in serene dissociation from these two

wisps of human life. He asked how far away those twinklers were,

and whether God was on the other side of them. But ever and anon

his childish prattle recurred to what impressed his imagination

even more deeply than the wonders of creation. If Tess were made

rich by marrying a gentleman, would she have money enough to buy a

spyglass so large that it would draw the stars as near to her as

Nettlecombe-Tout?

The renewed subject, which seemed to have impregnated the whole

family, filled Tess with impatience.

"Never mind that now!" she exclaimed.

"Did you say the stars were worlds, Tess?"

"Yes."

"All like ours?"

"I don't know; but I think so. They sometimes seem to be like the

apples on our stubbard-tree. Most of them splendid and sound--a few

blighted."

"Which do we live on--a splendid one or a blighted one?"

"A blighted one."

"'Tis very unlucky that we didn't pitch on a sound one, when there

were so many more of 'em!"

"Yes."

"Is it like that REALLY, Tess?" said Abraham, turning to her much

impressed, on reconsideration of this rare information. "How would

it have been if we had pitched on a sound one?"

"Well, father wouldn't have coughed and creeped about as he does,

and wouldn't have got too tipsy to go on this journey; and mother

wouldn't have been always washing, and never getting finished."

"And you would have been a rich lady ready-made, and not have had to

be made rich by marrying a gentleman?"

"O Aby, don't--don't talk of that any more!"

Left to his reflections Abraham soon grew drowsy. Tess was not

skilful in the management of a horse, but she thought that she could

take upon herself the entire conduct of the load for the present and

allow Abraham to go to sleep if he wished to do so. She made him a

sort of nest in front of the hives, in such a manner that he could

not fall, and, taking the reins into her own hands, jogged on as

before.

Prince required but slight attention, lacking energy for superfluous

movements of any sort. With no longer a companion to distract her,

Tess fell more deeply into reverie than ever, her back leaning

against the hives. The mute procession past her shoulders of trees

and hedges became attached to fantastic scenes outside reality, and

the occasional heave of the wind became the sigh of some immense sad

soul, conterminous with the universe in space, and with history in

time.

Then, examining the mesh of events in her own life, she seemed to see

the vanity of her father's pride; the gentlemanly suitor awaiting

herself in her mother's fancy; to see him as a grimacing personage,

laughing at her poverty and her shrouded knightly ancestry.

Everything grew more and more extravagant, and she no longer knew how

time passed. A sudden jerk shook her in her seat, and Tess awoke

from the sleep into which she, too, had fallen.

They were a long way further on than when she had lost consciousness,

and the waggon had stopped. A hollow groan, unlike anything she had

ever heard in her life, came from the front, followed by a shout of

"Hoi there!"

The lantern hanging at her waggon had gone out, but another was

shining in her face--much brighter than her own had been. Something

terrible had happened. The harness was entangled with an object

which blocked the way.

In consternation Tess jumped down, and discovered the dreadful truth.

The groan had proceeded from her father's poor horse Prince. The

morning mail-cart, with its two noiseless wheels, speeding along

these lanes like an arrow, as it always did, had driven into her slow

and unlighted equipage. The pointed shaft of the cart had entered

the breast of the unhappy Prince like a sword, and from the wound his

life's blood was spouting in a stream, and falling with a hiss into

the road.

In her despair Tess sprang forward and put her hand upon the hole,

with the only result that she became splashed from face to skirt with

the crimson drops. Then she stood helplessly looking on. Prince

also stood firm and motionless as long as he could; till he suddenly

sank down in a heap.

By this time the mail-cart man had joined her, and began dragging and

unharnessing the hot form of Prince. But he was already dead, and,

seeing that nothing more could be done immediately, the mail-cart man

returned to his own animal, which was uninjured.

"You was on the wrong side," he said. "I am bound to go on with the

mail-bags, so that the best thing for you to do is bide here with

your load. I'll send somebody to help you as soon as I can. It is

getting daylight, and you have nothing to fear."

He mounted and sped on his way; while Tess stood and waited. The

atmosphere turned pale, the birds shook themselves in the hedges,

arose, and twittered; the lane showed all its white features, and

Tess showed hers, still whiter. The huge pool of blood in front of

her was already assuming the iridescence of coagulation; and when the

sun rose a hundred prismatic hues were reflected from it. Prince lay

alongside, still and stark; his eyes half open, the hole in his chest

looking scarcely large enough to have let out all that had animated

him.

"'Tis all my doing--all mine!" the girl cried, gazing at the

spectacle. "No excuse for me--none. What will mother and father

live on now? Aby, Aby!" She shook the child, who had slept soundly

through the whole disaster. "We can't go on with our load--Prince

is killed!"

When Abraham realized all, the furrows of fifty years were

extemporized on his young face.

"Why, I danced and laughed only yesterday!" she went on to herself.

"To think that I was such a fool!"

"'Tis because we be on a blighted star, and not a sound one, isn't

it, Tess?" murmured Abraham through his tears.

In silence they waited through an interval which seemed endless. At

length a sound, and an approaching object, proved to them that the

driver of the mail-car had been as good as his word. A farmer's

man from near Stourcastle came up, leading a strong cob. He was

harnessed to the waggon of beehives in the place of Prince, and the

load taken on towards Casterbridge.

The evening of the same day saw the empty waggon reach again the

spot of the accident. Prince had lain there in the ditch since the

morning; but the place of the blood-pool was still visible in the

middle of the road, though scratched and scraped over by passing

vehicles. All that was left of Prince was now hoisted into the

waggon he had formerly hauled, and with his hoofs in the air, and his

shoes shining in the setting sunlight, he retraced the eight or nine

miles to Marlott.

Tess had gone back earlier. How to break the news was more than she

could think. It was a relief to her tongue to find from the faces of

her parents that they already knew of their loss, though this did not

lessen the self-reproach which she continued to heap upon herself for

her negligence.

But the very shiftlessness of the household rendered the misfortune

a less terrifying one to them than it would have been to a thriving

family, though in the present case it meant ruin, and in the other it

would only have meant inconvenience. In the Durbeyfield countenances

there was nothing of the red wrath that would have burnt upon the

girl from parents more ambitious for her welfare. Nobody blamed Tess

as she blamed herself.

When it was discovered that the knacker and tanner would give only a

very few shillings for Prince's carcase because of his decrepitude,

Durbeyfield rose to the occasion.

"No," said he stoically, "I won't sell his old body. When we

d'Urbervilles was knights in the land, we didn't sell our chargers

for cat's meat. Let 'em keep their shillings! He've served me well

in his lifetime, and I won't part from him now."

He worked harder the next day in digging a grave for Prince in the

garden than he had worked for months to grow a crop for his family.

When the hole was ready, Durbeyfield and his wife tied a rope round

the horse and dragged him up the path towards it, the children

following in funeral train. Abraham and 'Liza-Lu sobbed, Hope and

Modesty discharged their griefs in loud blares which echoed from the

walls; and when Prince was tumbled in they gathered round the grave.

The bread-winner had been taken away from them; what would they do?

"Is he gone to heaven?" asked Abraham, between the sobs.

Then Durbeyfield began to shovel in the earth, and the children cried

anew. All except Tess. Her face was dry and pale, as though she

regarded herself in the light of a murderess.

V

The haggling business, which had mainly depended on the horse, became

disorganized forthwith. Distress, if not penury, loomed in the

distance. Durbeyfield was what was locally called a slack-twisted

fellow; he had good strength to work at times; but the times could

not be relied on to coincide with the hours of requirement; and,

having been unaccustomed to the regular toil of the day-labourer,

he was not particularly persistent when they did so coincide.

Tess, meanwhile, as the one who had dragged her parents into this

quagmire, was silently wondering what she could do to help them out

of it; and then her mother broached her scheme.

"We must take the ups wi' the downs, Tess," said she; "and never

could your high blood have been found out at a more called-for

moment. You must try your friends. Do ye know that there is a very

rich Mrs d'Urberville living on the outskirts o' The Chase, who must

be our relation? You must go to her and claim kin, and ask for some

help in our trouble."

"I shouldn't care to do that," says Tess. "If there is such a lady,

'twould be enough for us if she were friendly--not to expect her to

give us help."

"You could win her round to do anything, my dear. Besides, perhaps

there's more in it than you know of. I've heard what I've heard,

good-now."

The oppressive sense of the harm she had done led Tess to be more

deferential than she might otherwise have been to the maternal

wish; but she could not understand why her mother should find such

satisfaction in contemplating an enterprise of, to her, such doubtful

profit. Her mother might have made inquiries, and have discovered

that this Mrs d'Urberville was a lady of unequalled virtues and

charity. But Tess's pride made the part of poor relation one of

particular distaste to her.

"I'd rather try to get work," she murmured.

"Durbeyfield, you can settle it," said his wife, turning to where he

sat in the background. "If you say she ought to go, she will go."

"I don't like my children going and making themselves beholden to

strange kin," murmured he. "I'm the head of the noblest branch o'

the family, and I ought to live up to it."

His reasons for staying away were worse to Tess than her own

objections to going. "Well, as I killed the horse, mother," she said

mournfully, "I suppose I ought to do something. I don't mind going

and seeing her, but you must leave it to me about asking for help.

And don't go thinking about her making a match for me--it is silly."

"Very well said, Tess!" observed her father sententiously.

"Who said I had such a thought?" asked Joan.

"I fancy it is in your mind, mother. But I'll go."

Rising early next day she walked to the hill-town called Shaston,

and there took advantage of a van which twice in the week ran from

Shaston eastward to Chaseborough, passing near Trantridge, the parish

in which the vague and mysterious Mrs d'Urberville had her residence.

Tess Durbeyfield's route on this memorable morning lay amid the

north-eastern undulations of the Vale in which she had been born, and

in which her life had unfolded. The Vale of Blackmoor was to her the

world, and its inhabitants the races thereof. From the gates and

stiles of Marlott she had looked down its length in the wondering

days of infancy, and what had been mystery to her then was not

much less than mystery to her now. She had seen daily from her

chamber-window towers, villages, faint white mansions; above all,

the town of Shaston standing majestically on its height; its windows

shining like lamps in the evening sun. She had hardly ever visited

the place, only a small tract even of the Vale and its environs being

known to her by close inspection. Much less had she been far outside

the valley. Every contour of the surrounding hills was as personal

to her as that of her relatives' faces; but for what lay beyond, her

judgment was dependent on the teaching of the village school, where

she had held a leading place at the time of her leaving, a year or

two before this date.

In those early days she had been much loved by others of her own

sex and age, and had used to be seen about the village as one of

three--all nearly of the same year--walking home from school side

by side; Tess the middle one--in a pink print pinafore, of a finely

reticulated pattern, worn over a stuff frock that had lost its

original colour for a nondescript tertiary--marching on upon long

stalky legs, in tight stockings which had little ladder-like holes

at the knees, torn by kneeling in the roads and banks in search of

vegetable and mineral treasures; her then earth-coloured hair hanging

like pot-hooks; the arms of the two outside girls resting round the

waist of Tess; her arms on the shoulders of the two supporters.

As Tess grew older, and began to see how matters stood, she felt

quite a Malthusian towards her mother for thoughtlessly giving her so

many little sisters and brothers, when it was such a trouble to nurse

and provide for them. Her mother's intelligence was that of a happy

child: Joan Durbeyfield was simply an additional one, and that not

the eldest, to her own long family of waiters on Providence.

However, Tess became humanely beneficent towards the small ones,

and to help them as much as possible she used, as soon as she left

school, to lend a hand at haymaking or harvesting on neighbouring

farms; or, by preference, at milking or butter-making processes,

which she had learnt when her father had owned cows; and being

deft-fingered it was a kind of work in which she excelled.

Every day seemed to throw upon her young shoulders more of the

family burdens, and that Tess should be the representative of the

Durbeyfields at the d'Urberville mansion came as a thing of course.

In this instance it must be admitted that the Durbeyfields were

putting their fairest side outward.

She alighted from the van at Trantridge Cross, and ascended on foot

a hill in the direction of the district known as The Chase, on the

borders of which, as she had been informed, Mrs d'Urberville's seat,

The Slopes, would be found. It was not a manorial home in the

ordinary sense, with fields, and pastures, and a grumbling farmer,

out of whom the owner had to squeeze an income for himself and his

family by hook or by crook. It was more, far more; a country-house

built for enjoyment pure and simple, with not an acre of troublesome

land attached to it beyond what was required for residential

purposes, and for a little fancy farm kept in hand by the owner, and

tended by a bailiff.

The crimson brick lodge came first in sight, up to its eaves in dense

evergreens. Tess thought this was the mansion itself till, passing

through the side wicket with some trepidation, and onward to a point

at which the drive took a turn, the house proper stood in full view.

It was of recent erection--indeed almost new--and of the same rich

red colour that formed such a contrast with the evergreens of the

lodge. Far behind the corner of the house--which rose like a

geranium bloom against the subdued colours around--stretched the soft

azure landscape of The Chase--a truly venerable tract of forest land,

one of the few remaining woodlands in England of undoubted primaeval

date, wherein Druidical mistletoe was still found on aged oaks, and

where enormous yew-trees, not planted by the hand of man grew as

they had grown when they were pollarded for bows. All this sylvan

antiquity, however, though visible from The Slopes, was outside the

immediate boundaries of the estate.

Everything on this snug property was bright, thriving, and well kept;

acres of glass-houses stretched down the inclines to the copses at

their feet. Everything looked like money--like the last coin issued

from the Mint. The stables, partly screened by Austrian pines

and evergreen oaks, and fitted with every late appliance, were

as dignified as Chapels-of-Ease. On the extensive lawn stood an

ornamental tent, its door being towards her.

Simple Tess Durbeyfield stood at gaze, in a half-alarmed attitude,

on the edge of the gravel sweep. Her feet had brought her onward to

this point before she had quite realized where she was; and now all

was contrary to her expectation.

"I thought we were an old family; but this is all new!" she said, in

her artlessness. She wished that she had not fallen in so readily

with her mother's plans for "claiming kin," and had endeavoured to

gain assistance nearer home.

The d'Urbervilles--or Stoke-d'Urbervilles, as they at first called

themselves--who owned all this, were a somewhat unusual family to

find in such an old-fashioned part of the country. Parson Tringham

had spoken truly when he said that our shambling John Durbeyfield was

the only really lineal representative of the old d'Urberville family

existing in the county, or near it; he might have added, what he knew

very well, that the Stoke-d'Urbervilles were no more d'Urbervilles of

the true tree then he was himself. Yet it must be admitted that this

family formed a very good stock whereon to regraft a name which sadly

wanted such renovation.

When old Mr Simon Stoke, latterly deceased, had made his fortune as

an honest merchant (some said money-lender) in the North, he decided

to settle as a county man in the South of England, out of hail of

his business district; and in doing this he felt the necessity of

recommencing with a name that would not too readily identify him with

the smart tradesman of the past, and that would be less commonplace

than the original bald, stark words. Conning for an hour in the

British Museum the pages of works devoted to extinct, half-extinct,

obscured, and ruined families appertaining to the quarter of England

in which he proposed to settle, he considered that _d'Urberville_

looked and sounded as well as any of them: and d'Urberville

accordingly was annexed to his own name for himself and his heirs

eternally. Yet he was not an extravagant-minded man in this, and in

constructing his family tree on the new basis was duly reasonable in

framing his inter-marriages and aristocratic links, never inserting

a single title above a rank of strict moderation.

Of this work of imagination poor Tess and her parents were naturally

in ignorance--much to their discomfiture; indeed, the very

possibility of such annexations was unknown to them; who supposed

that, though to be well-favoured might be the gift of fortune, a

family name came by nature.

Tess still stood hesitating like a bather about to make his plunge,

hardly knowing whether to retreat or to persevere, when a figure came

forth from the dark triangular door of the tent. It was that of a

tall young man, smoking.

He had an almost swarthy complexion, with full lips, badly moulded,

though red and smooth, above which was a well-groomed black moustache

with curled points, though his age could not be more than three- or

four-and-twenty. Despite the touches of barbarism in his contours,

there was a singular force in the gentleman's face, and in his bold

rolling eye.

"Well, my Beauty, what can I do for you?" said he, coming forward.

And perceiving that she stood quite confounded: "Never mind me. I am

Mr d'Urberville. Have you come to see me or my mother?"

This embodiment of a d'Urberville and a namesake differed even more

from what Tess had expected than the house and grounds had differed.

She had dreamed of an aged and dignified face, the sublimation of

all the d'Urberville lineaments, furrowed with incarnate memories

representing in hieroglyphic the centuries of her family's and

England's history. But she screwed herself up to the work in hand,

since she could not get out of it, and answered--

"I came to see your mother, sir."

"I am afraid you cannot see her--she is an invalid," replied the

present representative of the spurious house; for this was Mr Alec,

the only son of the lately deceased gentleman. "Cannot I answer your

purpose? What is the business you wish to see her about?"

"It isn't business--it is--I can hardly say what!"

"Pleasure?"

"Oh no. Why, sir, if I tell you, it will seem--"

Tess's sense of a certain ludicrousness in her errand was now

so strong that, notwithstanding her awe of him, and her general

discomfort at being here, her rosy lips curved towards a smile,

much to the attraction of the swarthy Alexander.

"It is so very foolish," she stammered; "I fear can't tell you!"

"Never mind; I like foolish things. Try again, my dear," said he

kindly.

"Mother asked me to come," Tess continued; "and, indeed, I was in the

mind to do so myself likewise. But I did not think it would be like

this. I came, sir, to tell you that we are of the same family as

you."

"Ho! Poor relations?"

"Yes."

"Stokes?"

"No; d'Urbervilles."

"Ay, ay; I mean d'Urbervilles."

"Our names are worn away to Durbeyfield; but we have several proofs

that we are d'Urbervilles. Antiquarians hold we are,--and--and we

have an old seal, marked with a ramping lion on a shield, and a

castle over him. And we have a very old silver spoon, round in the

bowl like a little ladle, and marked with the same castle. But it

is so worn that mother uses it to stir the pea-soup."

"A castle argent is certainly my crest," said he blandly. "And my

arms a lion rampant."

"And so mother said we ought to make ourselves beknown to you--as

we've lost our horse by a bad accident, and are the oldest branch o'

the family."

"Very kind of your mother, I'm sure. And I, for one, don't regret

her step." Alec looked at Tess as he spoke, in a way that made her

blush a little. "And so, my pretty girl, you've come on a friendly

visit to us, as relations?"

"I suppose I have," faltered Tess, looking uncomfortable again.

"Well--there's no harm in it. Where do you live? What are you?"

She gave him brief particulars; and responding to further inquiries

told him that she was intending to go back by the same carrier who

had brought her.

"It is a long while before he returns past Trantridge Cross.

Supposing we walk round the grounds to pass the time, my pretty Coz?"

Tess wished to abridge her visit as much as possible; but the young

man was pressing, and she consented to accompany him. He conducted

her about the lawns, and flower-beds, and conservatories; and thence

to the fruit-garden and greenhouses, where he asked her if she liked

strawberries.

"Yes," said Tess, "when they come."

"They are already here." D'Urberville began gathering specimens

of the fruit for her, handing them back to her as he stooped; and,

presently, selecting a specially fine product of the "British Queen"

variety, he stood up and held it by the stem to her mouth.

"No--no!" she said quickly, putting her fingers between his hand and

her lips. "I would rather take it in my own hand."

"Nonsense!" he insisted; and in a slight distress she parted her lips

and took it in.

They had spent some time wandering desultorily thus, Tess eating in

a half-pleased, half-reluctant state whatever d'Urberville offered

her. When she could consume no more of the strawberries he filled

her little basket with them; and then the two passed round to the

rose-trees, whence he gathered blossoms and gave her to put in her

bosom. She obeyed like one in a dream, and when she could affix no

more he himself tucked a bud or two into her hat, and heaped her

basket with others in the prodigality of his bounty. At last,

looking at his watch, he said, "Now, by the time you have had

something to eat, it will be time for you to leave, if you want to

catch the carrier to Shaston. Come here, and I'll see what grub I

can find."

Stoke d'Urberville took her back to the lawn and into the tent, where

he left her, soon reappearing with a basket of light luncheon, which

he put before her himself. It was evidently the gentleman's wish not

to be disturbed in this pleasant _tte--tte_ by the servantry.

"Do you mind my smoking?" he asked.

"Oh, not at all, sir."

He watched her pretty and unconscious munching through the skeins of

smoke that pervaded the tent, and Tess Durbeyfield did not divine,

as she innocently looked down at the roses in her bosom, that there

behind the blue narcotic haze was potentially the "tragic mischief"

of her drama--one who stood fair to be the blood-red ray in the

spectrum of her young life. She had an attribute which amounted

to a disadvantage just now; and it was this that caused Alec

d'Urberville's eyes to rivet themselves upon her. It was a

luxuriance of aspect, a fulness of growth, which made her appear more

of a woman than she really was. She had inherited the feature from

her mother without the quality it denoted. It had troubled her mind

occasionally, till her companions had said that it was a fault which

time would cure.

She soon had finished her lunch. "Now I am going home, sir," she

said, rising.

"And what do they call you?" he asked, as he accompanied her along

the drive till they were out of sight of the house.

"Tess Durbeyfield, down at Marlott."

"And you say your people have lost their horse?"

"I--killed him!" she answered, her eyes filling with tears as she

gave particulars of Prince's death. "And I don't know what to do

for father on account of it!"

"I must think if I cannot do something. My mother must find a berth

for you. But, Tess, no nonsense about 'd'Urberville';--'Durbeyfield'

only, you know--quite another name."

"I wish for no better, sir," said she with something of dignity.

For a moment--only for a moment--when they were in the turning of the

drive, between the tall rhododendrons and conifers, before the lodge

became visible, he inclined his face towards her as if--but, no: he

thought better of it, and let her go.

Thus the thing began. Had she perceived this meeting's import she

might have asked why she was doomed to be seen and coveted that day

by the wrong man, and not by some other man, the right and desired

one in all respects--as nearly as humanity can supply the right

and desired; yet to him who amongst her acquaintance might have

approximated to this kind, she was but a transient impression, half

forgotten.

In the ill-judged execution of the well-judged plan of things the

call seldom produces the comer, the man to love rarely coincides with

the hour for loving. Nature does not often say "See!" to her poor

creature at a time when seeing can lead to happy doing; or reply

"Here!" to a body's cry of "Where?" till the hide-and-seek has become

an irksome, outworn game. We may wonder whether at the acme and

summit of the human progress these anachronisms will be corrected by

a finer intuition, a closer interaction of the social machinery than

that which now jolts us round and along; but such completeness is not

to be prophesied, or even conceived as possible. Enough that in the

present case, as in millions, it was not the two halves of a perfect

whole that confronted each other at the perfect moment; a missing

counterpart wandered independently about the earth waiting in

crass obtuseness till the late time came. Out of which maladroit

delay sprang anxieties, disappointments, shocks, catastrophes, and

passing-strange destinies.

When d'Urberville got back to the tent he sat down astride on a

chair, reflecting, with a pleased gleam in his face. Then he broke

into a loud laugh.

"Well, I'm damned! What a funny thing! Ha-ha-ha! And what a crumby

girl!"

VI

Tess went down the hill to Trantridge Cross, and inattentively waited

to take her seat in the van returning from Chaseborough to Shaston.

She did not know what the other occupants said to her as she entered,

though she answered them; and when they had started anew she rode

along with an inward and not an outward eye.

One among her fellow-travellers addressed her more pointedly than

any had spoken before: "Why, you be quite a posy! And such roses in

early June!"

Then she became aware of the spectacle she presented to their

surprised vision: roses at her breasts; roses in her hat; roses

and strawberries in her basket to the brim. She blushed, and

said confusedly that the flowers had been given to her. When the

passengers were not looking she stealthily removed the more prominent

blooms from her hat and placed them in the basket, where she covered

them with her handkerchief. Then she fell to reflecting again, and

in looking downwards a thorn of the rose remaining in her breast

accidentally pricked her chin. Like all the cottagers in Blackmoor

Vale, Tess was steeped in fancies and prefigurative superstitions;

she thought this an ill omen--the first she had noticed that day.

The van travelled only so far as Shaston, and there were several

miles of pedestrian descent from that mountain-town into the vale to

Marlott. Her mother had advised her to stay here for the night, at

the house of a cottage-woman they knew, if she should feel too tired

to come on; and this Tess did, not descending to her home till the

following afternoon.

When she entered the house she perceived in a moment from her

mother's triumphant manner that something had occurred in the

interim.

"Oh yes; I know all about it! I told 'ee it would be all right, and

now 'tis proved!"

"Since I've been away? What has?" said Tess rather wearily.

Her mother surveyed the girl up and down with arch approval, and went

on banteringly: "So you've brought 'em round!"

"How do you know, mother?"

"I've had a letter."

Tess then remembered that there would have been time for this.

"They say--Mrs d'Urberville says--that she wants you to look after a

little fowl-farm which is her hobby. But this is only her artful way

of getting 'ee there without raising your hopes. She's going to own

'ee as kin--that's the meaning o't."

"But I didn't see her."

"You zid somebody, I suppose?"

"I saw her son."

"And did he own 'ee?"

"Well--he called me Coz."

"An' I knew it! Jacky--he called her Coz!" cried Joan to her

husband. "Well, he spoke to his mother, of course, and she do want

'ee there."

"But I don't know that I am apt at tending fowls," said the dubious

Tess.

"Then I don't know who is apt. You've be'n born in the business, and

brought up in it. They that be born in a business always know more

about it than any 'prentice. Besides, that's only just a show of

something for you to do, that you midn't feel beholden."

"I don't altogether think I ought to go," said Tess thoughtfully.

"Who wrote the letter? Will you let me look at it?"

"Mrs d'Urberville wrote it. Here it is."

The letter was in the third person, and briefly informed Mrs

Durbeyfield that her daughter's services would be useful to that lady

in the management of her poultry-farm, that a comfortable room would

be provided for her if she could come, and that the wages would be on

a liberal scale if they liked her.

"Oh--that's all!" said Tess.

"You couldn't expect her to throw her arms round 'ee, an' to kiss and

to coll 'ee all at once."

Tess looked out of the window.

"I would rather stay here with father and you," she said.

"But why?"

"I'd rather not tell you why, mother; indeed, I don't quite know

why."

A week afterwards she came in one evening from an unavailing search

for some light occupation in the immediate neighbourhood. Her idea

had been to get together sufficient money during the summer to

purchase another horse. Hardly had she crossed the threshold before

one of the children danced across the room, saying, "The gentleman's

been here!"

Her mother hastened to explain, smiles breaking from every inch of

her person. Mrs d'Urberville's son had called on horseback, having

been riding by chance in the direction of Marlott. He had wished

to know, finally, in the name of his mother, if Tess could really

come to manage the old lady's fowl-farm or not; the lad who had

hitherto superintended the birds having proved untrustworthy. "Mr

d'Urberville says you must be a good girl if you are at all as you

appear; he knows you must be worth your weight in gold. He is very

much interested in 'ee--truth to tell."

Tess seemed for the moment really pleased to hear that she had won

such high opinion from a stranger when, in her own esteem, she had

sunk so low.

"It is very good of him to think that," she murmured; "and if I was

quite sure how it would be living there, I would go any-when."

"He is a mighty handsome man!"

"I don't think so," said Tess coldly.

"Well, there's your chance, whether or no; and I'm sure he wears a

beautiful diamond ring!"

"Yes," said little Abraham, brightly, from the window-bench; "and

I seed it! and it did twinkle when he put his hand up to his

mistarshers. Mother, why did our grand relation keep on putting his

hand up to his mistarshers?"

"Hark at that child!" cried Mrs Durbeyfield, with parenthetic

admiration.

"Perhaps to show his diamond ring," murmured Sir John, dreamily, from

his chair.

"I'll think it over," said Tess, leaving the room.

"Well, she's made a conquest o' the younger branch of us, straight

off," continued the matron to her husband, "and she's a fool if she

don't follow it up."

"I don't quite like my children going away from home," said the

haggler. "As the head of the family, the rest ought to come to me."

"But do let her go, Jacky," coaxed his poor witless wife. "He's

struck wi' her--you can see that. He called her Coz! He'll marry

her, most likely, and make a lady of her; and then she'll be what

her forefathers was."

John Durbeyfield had more conceit than energy or health, and this

supposition was pleasant to him.

"Well, perhaps that's what young Mr d'Urberville means," he admitted;

"and sure enough he mid have serious thoughts about improving his

blood by linking on to the old line. Tess, the little rogue! And

have she really paid 'em a visit to such an end as this?"

Meanwhile Tess was walking thoughtfully among the gooseberry-bushes

in the garden, and over Prince's grave. When she came in her mother

pursued her advantage.

"Well, what be you going to do?" she asked.

"I wish I had seen Mrs d'Urberville," said Tess.

"I think you mid as well settle it. Then you'll see her soon

enough."

Her father coughed in his chair.

"I don't know what to say!" answered the girl restlessly. "It is for

you to decide. I killed the old horse, and I suppose I ought to do

something to get ye a new one. But--but--I don't quite like Mr

d'Urberville being there!"

The children, who had made use of this idea of Tess being taken up by

their wealthy kinsfolk (which they imagined the other family to be)

as a species of dolorifuge after the death of the horse, began to cry

at Tess's reluctance, and teased and reproached her for hesitating.

"Tess won't go-o-o and be made a la-a-dy of!--no, she says she

wo-o-on't!" they wailed, with square mouths. "And we shan't have a

nice new horse, and lots o' golden money to buy fairlings! And Tess

won't look pretty in her best cloze no mo-o-ore!"

Her mother chimed in to the same tune: a certain way she had of

making her labours in the house seem heavier than they were by

prolonging them indefinitely, also weighed in the argument. Her

father alone preserved an attitude of neutrality.

"I will go," said Tess at last.

Her mother could not repress her consciousness of the nuptial vision

conjured up by the girl's consent.

"That's right! For such a pretty maid as 'tis, this is a fine

chance!"

Tess smiled crossly.

"I hope it is a chance for earning money. It is no other kind of

chance. You had better say nothing of that silly sort about parish."

Mrs Durbeyfield did not promise. She was not quite sure that she did

not feel proud enough, after the visitor's remarks, to say a good

deal.

Thus it was arranged; and the young girl wrote, agreeing to be ready

to set out on any day on which she might be required. She was duly

informed that Mrs d'Urberville was glad of her decision, and that a

spring-cart should be sent to meet her and her luggage at the top

of the Vale on the day after the morrow, when she must hold herself

prepared to start. Mrs d'Urberville's handwriting seemed rather

masculine.

"A cart?" murmured Joan Durbeyfield doubtingly. "It might have been

a carriage for her own kin!"

Having at last taken her course Tess was less restless and

abstracted, going about her business with some self-assurance in the

thought of acquiring another horse for her father by an occupation

which would not be onerous. She had hoped to be a teacher at the

school, but the fates seemed to decide otherwise. Being mentally

older than her mother she did not regard Mrs Durbeyfield's

matrimonial hopes for her in a serious aspect for a moment. The

light-minded woman had been discovering good matches for her daughter

almost from the year of her birth.

VII

On the morning appointed for her departure Tess was awake before

dawn--at the marginal minute of the dark when the grove is still

mute, save for one prophetic bird who sings with a clear-voiced

conviction that he at least knows the correct time of day, the rest

preserving silence as if equally convinced that he is mistaken. She

remained upstairs packing till breakfast-time, and then came down in

her ordinary week-day clothes, her Sunday apparel being carefully

folded in her box.

Her mother expostulated. "You will never set out to see your folks

without dressing up more the dand than that?"

"But I am going to work!" said Tess.

"Well, yes," said Mrs Durbeyfield; and in a private tone, "at first

there mid be a little pretence o't ... But I think it will be wiser

of 'ee to put your best side outward," she added.

"Very well; I suppose you know best," replied Tess with calm

abandonment.

And to please her parent the girl put herself quite in Joan's hands,

saying serenely--"Do what you like with me, mother."

Mrs Durbeyfield was only too delighted at this tractability.

First she fetched a great basin, and washed Tess's hair with such

thoroughness that when dried and brushed it looked twice as much as

at other times. She tied it with a broader pink ribbon than usual.

Then she put upon her the white frock that Tess had worn at the

club-walking, the airy fulness of which, supplementing her enlarged

_coiffure_, imparted to her developing figure an amplitude which

belied her age, and might cause her to be estimated as a woman when

she was not much more than a child.

"I declare there's a hole in my stocking-heel!" said Tess.

"Never mind holes in your stockings--they don't speak! When I was a

maid, so long as I had a pretty bonnet the devil might ha' found me

in heels."

Her mother's pride in the girl's appearance led her to step back,

like a painter from his easel, and survey her work as a whole.

"You must zee yourself!" she cried. "It is much better than you was

t'other day."

As the looking-glass was only large enough to reflect a very small

portion of Tess's person at one time, Mrs Durbeyfield hung a black

cloak outside the casement, and so made a large reflector of the

panes, as it is the wont of bedecking cottagers to do. After this

she went downstairs to her husband, who was sitting in the lower

room.

"I'll tell 'ee what 'tis, Durbeyfield," said she exultingly; "he'll

never have the heart not to love her. But whatever you do, don't zay

too much to Tess of his fancy for her, and this chance she has got.

She is such an odd maid that it mid zet her against him, or against

going there, even now. If all goes well, I shall certainly be for

making some return to pa'son at Stagfoot Lane for telling us--dear,

good man!"

However, as the moment for the girl's setting out drew nigh, when the

first excitement of the dressing had passed off, a slight misgiving

found place in Joan Durbeyfield's mind. It prompted the matron to

say that she would walk a little way--as far as to the point where

the acclivity from the valley began its first steep ascent to

the outer world. At the top Tess was going to be met with the

spring-cart sent by the Stoke-d'Urbervilles, and her box had already

been wheeled ahead towards this summit by a lad with trucks, to be in

readiness.

Seeing their mother put on her bonnet, the younger children clamoured

to go with her.

"I do want to walk a little-ways wi' Sissy, now she's going to marry

our gentleman-cousin, and wear fine cloze!"

"Now," said Tess, flushing and turning quickly, "I'll hear no more o'

that! Mother, how could you ever put such stuff into their heads?"

"Going to work, my dears, for our rich relation, and help get enough

money for a new horse," said Mrs Durbeyfield pacifically.

"Goodbye, father," said Tess, with a lumpy throat.

"Goodbye, my maid," said Sir John, raising his head from his breast

as he suspended his nap, induced by a slight excess this morning in

honour of the occasion. "Well, I hope my young friend will like such

a comely sample of his own blood. And tell'n, Tess, that being sunk,

quite, from our former grandeur, I'll sell him the title--yes, sell

it--and at no onreasonable figure."

"Not for less than a thousand pound!" cried Lady Durbeyfield.

"Tell'n--I'll take a thousand pound. Well, I'll take less, when

I come to think o't. He'll adorn it better than a poor lammicken

feller like myself can. Tell'n he shall hae it for a hundred. But

I won't stand upon trifles--tell'n he shall hae it for fifty--for

twenty pound! Yes, twenty pound--that's the lowest. Dammy, family

honour is family honour, and I won't take a penny less!"

Tess's eyes were too full and her voice too choked to utter the

sentiments that were in her. She turned quickly, and went out.

So the girls and their mother all walked together, a child on each

side of Tess, holding her hand and looking at her meditatively from

time to time, as at one who was about to do great things; her mother

just behind with the smallest; the group forming a picture of honest

beauty flanked by innocence, and backed by simple-souled vanity.

They followed the way till they reached the beginning of the ascent,

on the crest of which the vehicle from Trantridge was to receive her,

this limit having been fixed to save the horse the labour of the last

slope. Far away behind the first hills the cliff-like dwellings

of Shaston broke the line of the ridge. Nobody was visible in the

elevated road which skirted the ascent save the lad whom they had

sent on before them, sitting on the handle of the barrow that

contained all Tess's worldly possessions.

"Bide here a bit, and the cart will soon come, no doubt," said Mrs

Durbeyfield. "Yes, I see it yonder!"

It had come--appearing suddenly from behind the forehead of the

nearest upland, and stopping beside the boy with the barrow. Her

mother and the children thereupon decided to go no farther, and

bidding them a hasty goodbye, Tess bent her steps up the hill.

They saw her white shape draw near to the spring-cart, on which her

box was already placed. But before she had quite reached it another

vehicle shot out from a clump of trees on the summit, came round the

bend of the road there, passed the luggage-cart, and halted beside

Tess, who looked up as if in great surprise.

Her mother perceived, for the first time, that the second vehicle was

not a humble conveyance like the first, but a spick-and-span gig or

dog-cart, highly varnished and equipped. The driver was a young man

of three- or four-and-twenty, with a cigar between his teeth; wearing

a dandy cap, drab jacket, breeches of the same hue, white neckcloth,

stick-up collar, and brown driving-gloves--in short, he was the

handsome, horsey young buck who had visited Joan a week or two before

to get her answer about Tess.

Mrs Durbeyfield clapped her hands like a child. Then she looked

down, then stared again. Could she be deceived as to the meaning of

this?

"Is dat the gentleman-kinsman who'll make Sissy a lady?" asked the

youngest child.

Meanwhile the muslined form of Tess could be seen standing still,

undecided, beside this turn-out, whose owner was talking to her.

Her seeming indecision was, in fact, more than indecision: it was

misgiving. She would have preferred the humble cart. The young

man dismounted, and appeared to urge her to ascend. She turned her

face down the hill to her relatives, and regarded the little group.

Something seemed to quicken her to a determination; possibly the

thought that she had killed Prince. She suddenly stepped up; he

mounted beside her, and immediately whipped on the horse. In a

moment they had passed the slow cart with the box, and disappeared

behind the shoulder of the hill.

Directly Tess was out of sight, and the interest of the matter as a

drama was at an end, the little ones' eyes filled with tears. The

youngest child said, "I wish poor, poor Tess wasn't gone away to be a

lady!" and, lowering the corners of his lips, burst out crying. The

new point of view was infectious, and the next child did likewise,

and then the next, till the whole three of them wailed loud.

There were tears also in Joan Durbeyfield's eyes as she turned to

go home. But by the time she had got back to the village she was

passively trusting to the favour of accident. However, in bed that

night she sighed, and her husband asked her what was the matter.

"Oh, I don't know exactly," she said. "I was thinking that perhaps

it would ha' been better if Tess had not gone."

"Oughtn't ye to have thought of that before?"

"Well, 'tis a chance for the maid--Still, if 'twere the doing again,

I wouldn't let her go till I had found out whether the gentleman

is really a good-hearted young man and choice over her as his

kinswoman."

"Yes, you ought, perhaps, to ha' done that," snored Sir John.

Joan Durbeyfield always managed to find consolation somewhere: "Well,

as one of the genuine stock, she ought to make her way with 'en, if

she plays her trump card aright. And if he don't marry her afore he

will after. For that he's all afire wi' love for her any eye can

see."

"What's her trump card? Her d'Urberville blood, you mean?"

"No, stupid; her face--as 'twas mine."

VIII

Having mounted beside her, Alec d'Urberville drove rapidly along

the crest of the first hill, chatting compliments to Tess as they

went, the cart with her box being left far behind. Rising still, an

immense landscape stretched around them on every side; behind, the

green valley of her birth, before, a gray country of which she knew

nothing except from her first brief visit to Trantridge. Thus they

reached the verge of an incline down which the road stretched in a

long straight descent of nearly a mile.

Ever since the accident with her father's horse Tess Durbeyfield,

courageous as she naturally was, had been exceedingly timid on

wheels; the least irregularity of motion startled her. She began to

get uneasy at a certain recklessness in her conductor's driving.

"You will go down slow, sir, I suppose?" she said with attempted

unconcern.

D'Urberville looked round upon her, nipped his cigar with the tips of

his large white centre-teeth, and allowed his lips to smile slowly of

themselves.

"Why, Tess," he answered, after another whiff or two, "it isn't a

brave bouncing girl like you who asks that? Why, I always go down at

full gallop. There's nothing like it for raising your spirits."

"But perhaps you need not now?"

"Ah," he said, shaking his head, "there are two to be reckoned with.

It is not me alone. Tib has to be considered, and she has a very

queer temper."

"Who?"

"Why, this mare. I fancy she looked round at me in a very grim way

just then. Didn't you notice it?"

"Don't try to frighten me, sir," said Tess stiffly.

"Well, I don't. If any living man can manage this horse I can: I

won't say any living man can do it--but if such has the power, I am

he."

"Why do you have such a horse?"

"Ah, well may you ask it! It was my fate, I suppose. Tib has killed

one chap; and just after I bought her she nearly killed me. And

then, take my word for it, I nearly killed her. But she's touchy

still, very touchy; and one's life is hardly safe behind her

sometimes."

They were just beginning to descend; and it was evident that the

horse, whether of her own will or of his (the latter being the more

likely), knew so well the reckless performance expected of her that

she hardly required a hint from behind.

Down, down, they sped, the wheels humming like a top, the dog-cart

rocking right and left, its axis acquiring a slightly oblique set

in relation to the line of progress; the figure of the horse rising

and falling in undulations before them. Sometimes a wheel was off

the ground, it seemed, for many yards; sometimes a stone was sent

spinning over the hedge, and flinty sparks from the horse's hoofs

outshone the daylight. The aspect of the straight road enlarged with

their advance, the two banks dividing like a splitting stick; one

rushing past at each shoulder.

The wind blew through Tess's white muslin to her very skin, and her

washed hair flew out behind. She was determined to show no open

fear, but she clutched d'Urberville's rein-arm.

"Don't touch my arm! We shall be thrown out if you do! Hold on

round my waist!"

She grasped his waist, and so they reached the bottom.

"Safe, thank God, in spite of your fooling!" said she, her face on

fire.

"Tess--fie! that's temper!" said d'Urberville.

"'Tis truth."

"Well, you need not let go your hold of me so thanklessly the moment

you feel yourself our of danger."

She had not considered what she had been doing; whether he were man

or woman, stick or stone, in her involuntary hold on him. Recovering

her reserve, she sat without replying, and thus they reached the

summit of another declivity.

"Now then, again!" said d'Urberville.

"No, no!" said Tess. "Show more sense, do, please."

"But when people find themselves on one of the highest points in the

county, they must get down again," he retorted.

He loosened rein, and away they went a second time. D'Urberville

turned his face to her as they rocked, and said, in playful raillery:

"Now then, put your arms round my waist again, as you did before, my

Beauty."

"Never!" said Tess independently, holding on as well as she could

without touching him.

"Let me put one little kiss on those holmberry lips, Tess, or even on

that warmed cheek, and I'll stop--on my honour, I will!"

Tess, surprised beyond measure, slid farther back still on her seat,

at which he urged the horse anew, and rocked her the more.

"Will nothing else do?" she cried at length, in desperation, her

large eyes staring at him like those of a wild animal. This dressing

her up so prettily by her mother had apparently been to lamentable

purpose.

"Nothing, dear Tess," he replied.

"Oh, I don't know--very well; I don't mind!" she panted miserably.

He drew rein, and as they slowed he was on the point of imprinting

the desired salute, when, as if hardly yet aware of her own modesty,

she dodged aside. His arms being occupied with the reins there was

left him no power to prevent her manoeuvre.

"Now, damn it--I'll break both our necks!" swore her capriciously

passionate companion. "So you can go from your word like that, you

young witch, can you?"

"Very well," said Tess, "I'll not move since you be so determined!

But I--thought you would be kind to me, and protect me, as my

kinsman!"

"Kinsman be hanged! Now!"

"But I don't want anybody to kiss me, sir!" she implored, a big

tear beginning to roll down her face, and the corners of her mouth

trembling in her attempts not to cry. "And I wouldn't ha' come if

I had known!"

He was inexorable, and she sat still, and d'Urberville gave her the

kiss of mastery. No sooner had he done so than she flushed with

shame, took out her handkerchief, and wiped the spot on her cheek

that had been touched by his lips. His ardour was nettled at the

sight, for the act on her part had been unconsciously done.

"You are mighty sensitive for a cottage girl!" said the young man.

Tess made no reply to this remark, of which, indeed, she did not

quite comprehend the drift, unheeding the snub she had administered

by her instinctive rub upon her cheek. She had, in fact, undone the

kiss, as far as such a thing was physically possible. With a dim

sense that he was vexed she looked steadily ahead as they trotted on

near Melbury Down and Wingreen, till she saw, to her consternation,

that there was yet another descent to be undergone.

"You shall be made sorry for that!" he resumed, his injured tone

still remaining, as he flourished the whip anew. "Unless, that is,

you agree willingly to let me do it again, and no handkerchief."

She sighed. "Very well, sir!" she said. "Oh--let me get my hat!"

At the moment of speaking her hat had blown off into the road, their

present speed on the upland being by no means slow. D'Urberville

pulled up, and said he would get it for her, but Tess was down on the

other side.

She turned back and picked up the article.

"You look prettier with it off, upon my soul, if that's possible," he

said, contemplating her over the back of the vehicle. "Now then, up

again! What's the matter?"

The hat was in place and tied, but Tess had not stepped forward.

"No, sir," she said, revealing the red and ivory of her mouth as her

eye lit in defiant triumph; "not again, if I know it!"

"What--you won't get up beside me?"

"No; I shall walk."

"'Tis five or six miles yet to Trantridge."

"I don't care if 'tis dozens. Besides, the cart is behind."

"You artful hussy! Now, tell me--didn't you make that hat blow off

on purpose? I'll swear you did!"

Her strategic silence confirmed his suspicion.

Then d'Urberville cursed and swore at her, and called her everything

he could think of for the trick. Turning the horse suddenly he tried

to drive back upon her, and so hem her in between the gig and the

hedge. But he could not do this short of injuring her.

"You ought to be ashamed of yourself for using such wicked words!"

cried Tess with spirit, from the top of the hedge into which she had

scrambled. "I don't like 'ee at all! I hate and detest you! I'll

go back to mother, I will!"

D'Urberville's bad temper cleared up at sight of hers; and he laughed

heartily.

"Well, I like you all the better," he said. "Come, let there be

peace. I'll never do it any more against your will. My life upon

it now!"

Still Tess could not be induced to remount. She did not, however,

object to his keeping his gig alongside her; and in this manner, at

a slow pace, they advanced towards the village of Trantridge. From

time to time d'Urberville exhibited a sort of fierce distress at

the sight of the tramping he had driven her to undertake by his

misdemeanour. She might in truth have safely trusted him now; but he

had forfeited her confidence for the time, and she kept on the ground

progressing thoughtfully, as if wondering whether it would be wiser

to return home. Her resolve, however, had been taken, and it seemed

vacillating even to childishness to abandon it now, unless for graver

reasons. How could she face her parents, get back her box, and

disconcert the whole scheme for the rehabilitation of her family on

such sentimental grounds?

A few minutes later the chimneys of The Slopes appeared in view, and

in a snug nook to the right the poultry-farm and cottage of Tess'

destination.

IX

The community of fowls to which Tess had been appointed as

supervisor, purveyor, nurse, surgeon, and friend made its

headquarters in an old thatched cottage standing in an enclosure that

had once been a garden, but was now a trampled and sanded square.

The house was overrun with ivy, its chimney being enlarged by the

boughs of the parasite to the aspect of a ruined tower. The lower

rooms were entirely given over to the birds, who walked about them

with a proprietary air, as though the place had been built by

themselves, and not by certain dusty copyholders who now lay east

and west in the churchyard. The descendants of these bygone owners

felt it almost as a slight to their family when the house which had

so much of their affection, had cost so much of their forefathers'

money, and had been in their possession for several generations

before the d'Urbervilles came and built here, was indifferently

turned into a fowl-house by Mrs Stoke-d'Urberville as soon as the

property fell into hand according to law. "'Twas good enough for

Christians in grandfather's time," they said.

The rooms wherein dozens of infants had wailed at their nursing now

resounded with the tapping of nascent chicks. Distracted hens in

coops occupied spots where formerly stood chairs supporting sedate

agriculturists. The chimney-corner and once-blazing hearth was now

filled with inverted beehives, in which the hens laid their eggs;

while out of doors the plots that each succeeding householder had

carefully shaped with his spade were torn by the cocks in wildest

fashion.

The garden in which the cottage stood was surrounded by a wall, and

could only be entered through a door.

When Tess had occupied herself about an hour the next morning in

altering and improving the arrangements, according to her skilled

ideas as the daughter of a professed poulterer, the door in the wall

opened and a servant in white cap and apron entered. She had come

from the manor-house.

"Mrs d'Urberville wants the fowls as usual," she said; but perceiving

that Tess did not quite understand, she explained, "Mis'ess is a old

lady, and blind."

"Blind!" said Tess.

Almost before her misgiving at the news could find time to shape

itself she took, under her companion's direction, two of the

most beautiful of the Hamburghs in her arms, and followed the

maid-servant, who had likewise taken two, to the adjacent mansion,

which, though ornate and imposing, showed traces everywhere on this

side that some occupant of its chambers could bend to the love of

dumb creatures--feathers floating within view of the front, and

hen-coops standing on the grass.

In a sitting-room on the ground-floor, ensconced in an armchair with

her back to the light, was the owner and mistress of the estate, a

white-haired woman of not more than sixty, or even less, wearing a

large cap. She had the mobile face frequent in those whose sight

has decayed by stages, has been laboriously striven after, and

reluctantly let go, rather than the stagnant mien apparent in persons

long sightless or born blind. Tess walked up to this lady with her

feathered charges--one sitting on each arm.

"Ah, you are the young woman come to look after my birds?" said Mrs

d'Urberville, recognizing a new footstep. "I hope you will be kind

to them. My bailiff tells me you are quite the proper person.

Well, where are they? Ah, this is Strut! But he is hardly so

lively to-day, is he? He is alarmed at being handled by a stranger,

I suppose. And Phena too--yes, they are a little frightened--aren't

you, dears? But they will soon get used to you."

While the old lady had been speaking Tess and the other maid, in

obedience to her gestures, had placed the fowls severally in her lap,

and she had felt them over from head to tail, examining their beaks,

their combs, the manes of the cocks, their wings, and their claws.

Her touch enabled her to recognize them in a moment, and to discover

if a single feather were crippled or draggled. She handled their

crops, and knew what they had eaten, and if too little or too much;

her face enacting a vivid pantomime of the criticisms passing in her

mind.

The birds that the two girls had brought in were duly returned to the

yard, and the process was repeated till all the pet cocks and hens

had been submitted to the old woman--Hamburghs, Bantams, Cochins,

Brahmas, Dorkings, and such other sorts as were in fashion just

then--her perception of each visitor being seldom at fault as she

received the bird upon her knees.

It reminded Tess of a Confirmation, in which Mrs d'Urberville was the

bishop, the fowls the young people presented, and herself and the

maid-servant the parson and curate of the parish bringing them up.

At the end of the ceremony Mrs d'Urberville abruptly asked Tess,

wrinkling and twitching her face into undulations, "Can you whistle?"

"Whistle, Ma'am?"

"Yes, whistle tunes."

Tess could whistle like most other country-girls, though the

accomplishment was one which she did not care to profess in genteel

company. However, she blandly admitted that such was the fact.

"Then you will have to practise it every day. I had a lad who did it

very well, but he has left. I want you to whistle to my bullfinches;

as I cannot see them, I like to hear them, and we teach 'em airs

that way. Tell her where the cages are, Elizabeth. You must begin

to-morrow, or they will go back in their piping. They have been

neglected these several days."

"Mr d'Urberville whistled to 'em this morning, ma'am," said

Elizabeth.

"He! Pooh!"

The old lady's face creased into furrows of repugnance, and she made

no further reply.

Thus the reception of Tess by her fancied kinswoman terminated, and

the birds were taken back to their quarters. The girl's surprise at

Mrs d'Urberville's manner was not great; for since seeing the size of

the house she had expected no more. But she was far from being aware

that the old lady had never heard a word of the so-called kinship.

She gathered that no great affection flowed between the blind woman

and her son. But in that, too, she was mistaken. Mrs d'Urberville

was not the first mother compelled to love her offspring resentfully,

and to be bitterly fond.

In spite of the unpleasant initiation of the day before, Tess

inclined to the freedom and novelty of her new position in the

morning when the sun shone, now that she was once installed there;

and she was curious to test her powers in the unexpected direction

asked of her, so as to ascertain her chance of retaining her post.

As soon as she was alone within the walled garden she sat herself

down on a coop, and seriously screwed up her mouth for the

long-neglected practice. She found her former ability to have

degenerated to the production of a hollow rush of wind through the

lips, and no clear note at all.

She remained fruitlessly blowing and blowing, wondering how she

could have so grown out of the art which had come by nature, till

she became aware of a movement among the ivy-boughs which cloaked

the garden-wall no less then the cottage. Looking that way she

beheld a form springing from the coping to the plot. It was Alec

d'Urberville, whom she had not set eyes on since he had conducted

her the day before to the door of the gardener's cottage where she

had lodgings.

"Upon my honour!" cried he, "there was never before such a beautiful

thing in Nature or Art as you look, 'Cousin' Tess ('Cousin' had a

faint ring of mockery). I have been watching you from over the

wall--sitting like IM-patience on a monument, and pouting up that

pretty red mouth to whistling shape, and whooing and whooing, and

privately swearing, and never being able to produce a note. Why,

you are quite cross because you can't do it."

"I may be cross, but I didn't swear."

"Ah! I understand why you are trying--those bullies! My mother

wants you to carry on their musical education. How selfish of her!

As if attending to these curst cocks and hens here were not enough

work for any girl. I would flatly refuse, if I were you."

"But she wants me particularly to do it, and to be ready by to-morrow

morning."

"Does she? Well then--I'll give you a lesson or two."

"Oh no, you won't!" said Tess, withdrawing towards the door.

"Nonsense; I don't want to touch you. See--I'll stand on this side

of the wire-netting, and you can keep on the other; so you may feel

quite safe. Now, look here; you screw up your lips too harshly.

There 'tis--so."

He suited the action to the word, and whistled a line of "Take, O

take those lips away." But the allusion was lost upon Tess.

"Now try," said d'Urberville.

She attempted to look reserved; her face put on a sculptural

severity. But he persisted in his demand, and at last, to get rid of

him, she did put up her lips as directed for producing a clear note;

laughing distressfully, however, and then blushing with vexation that

she had laughed.

He encouraged her with "Try again!"

Tess was quite serious, painfully serious by this time; and she

tried--ultimately and unexpectedly emitting a real round sound.

The momentary pleasure of success got the better of her; her eyes

enlarged, and she involuntarily smiled in his face.

"That's it! Now I have started you--you'll go on beautifully.

There--I said I would not come near you; and, in spite of such

temptation as never before fell to mortal man, I'll keep my

word... Tess, do you think my mother a queer old soul?"

"I don't know much of her yet, sir."

"You'll find her so; she must be, to make you learn to whistle to her

bullfinches. I am rather out of her books just now, but you will be

quite in favour if you treat her live-stock well. Good morning. If

you meet with any difficulties and want help here, don't go to the

bailiff, come to me."

It was in the economy of this _rgime_ that Tess Durbeyfield had

undertaken to fill a place. Her first day's experiences were fairly

typical of those which followed through many succeeding days. A

familiarity with Alec d'Urberville's presence--which that young man

carefully cultivated in her by playful dialogue, and by jestingly

calling her his cousin when they were alone--removed much of her

original shyness of him, without, however, implanting any feeling

which could engender shyness of a new and tenderer kind. But she was

more pliable under his hands than a mere companionship would have

made her, owing to her unavoidable dependence upon his mother, and,

through that lady's comparative helplessness, upon him.

She soon found that whistling to the bullfinches in Mrs

d'Urberville's room was no such onerous business when she had

regained the art, for she had caught from her musical mother numerous

airs that suited those songsters admirably. A far more satisfactory

time than when she practised in the garden was this whistling by the

cages each morning. Unrestrained by the young man's presence she

threw up her mouth, put her lips near the bars, and piped away in

easeful grace to the attentive listeners.

Mrs d'Urberville slept in a large four-post bedstead hung with heavy

damask curtains, and the bullfinches occupied the same apartment,

where they flitted about freely at certain hours, and made little

white spots on the furniture and upholstery. Once while Tess was at

the window where the cages were ranged, giving her lesson as usual,

she thought she heard a rustling behind the bed. The old lady was

not present, and turning round the girl had an impression that

the toes of a pair of boots were visible below the fringe of the

curtains. Thereupon her whistling became so disjointed that the

listener, if such there were, must have discovered her suspicion of

his presence. She searched the curtains every morning after that,

but never found anybody within them. Alec d'Urberville had evidently

thought better of his freak to terrify her by an ambush of that kind.

X

Every village has its idiosyncrasy, its constitution, often its own

code of morality. The levity of some of the younger women in and

about Trantridge was marked, and was perhaps symptomatic of the

choice spirit who ruled The Slopes in that vicinity. The place had

also a more abiding defect; it drank hard. The staple conversation

on the farms around was on the uselessness of saving money; and

smock-frocked arithmeticians, leaning on their ploughs or hoes, would

enter into calculations of great nicety to prove that parish relief

was a fuller provision for a man in his old age than any which could

result from savings out of their wages during a whole lifetime.

The chief pleasure of these philosophers lay in going every Saturday

night, when work was done, to Chaseborough, a decayed market-town two

or three miles distant; and, returning in the small hours of the next

morning, to spend Sunday in sleeping off the dyspeptic effects of the

curious compounds sold to them as beer by the monopolizers of the

once-independent inns.

For a long time Tess did not join in the weekly pilgrimages. But

under pressure from matrons not much older than herself--for a

field-man's wages being as high at twenty-one as at forty, marriage

was early here--Tess at length consented to go. Her first experience

of the journey afforded her more enjoyment than she had expected,

the hilariousness of the others being quite contagious after her

monotonous attention to the poultry-farm all the week. She went again

and again. Being graceful and interesting, standing moreover on the

momentary threshold of womanhood, her appearance drew down upon her

some sly regards from loungers in the streets of Chaseborough; hence,

though sometimes her journey to the town was made independently, she

always searched for her fellows at nightfall, to have the protection

of their companionship homeward.

This had gone on for a month or two when there came a Saturday in

September, on which a fair and a market coincided; and the pilgrims

from Trantridge sought double delights at the inns on that account.

Tess's occupations made her late in setting out, so that her comrades

reached the town long before her. It was a fine September evening,

just before sunset, when yellow lights struggle with blue shades in

hairlike lines, and the atmosphere itself forms a prospect without

aid from more solid objects, except the innumerable winged insects

that dance in it. Through this low-lit mistiness Tess walked

leisurely along.

She did not discover the coincidence of the market with the fair till

she had reached the place, by which time it was close upon dusk. Her

limited marketing was soon completed; and then as usual she began to

look about for some of the Trantridge cottagers.

At first she could not find them, and she was informed that most of

them had gone to what they called a private little jig at the house

of a hay-trusser and peat-dealer who had transactions with their

farm. He lived in an out-of-the-way nook of the townlet, and in

trying to find her course thither her eyes fell upon Mr d'Urberville

standing at a street corner.

"What--my Beauty? You here so late?" he said.

She told him that she was simply waiting for company homeward.

"I'll see you again," said he over her shoulder as she went on down

the back lane.

Approaching the hay-trussers, she could hear the fiddled notes of

a reel proceeding from some building in the rear; but no sound of

dancing was audible--an exceptional state of things for these parts,

where as a rule the stamping drowned the music. The front door being

open she could see straight through the house into the garden at the

back as far as the shades of night would allow; and nobody appearing

to her knock, she traversed the dwelling and went up the path to the

outhouse whence the sound had attracted her.

It was a windowless erection used for storage, and from the open door

there floated into the obscurity a mist of yellow radiance, which at

first Tess thought to be illuminated smoke. But on drawing nearer

she perceived that it was a cloud of dust, lit by candles within the

outhouse, whose beams upon the haze carried forward the outline of

the doorway into the wide night of the garden.

When she came close and looked in she beheld indistinct forms

racing up and down to the figure of the dance, the silence of their

footfalls arising from their being overshoe in "scroff"--that is

to say, the powdery residuum from the storage of peat and other

products, the stirring of which by their turbulent feet created the

nebulosity that involved the scene. Through this floating, fusty

_debris_ of peat and hay, mixed with the perspirations and warmth of

the dancers, and forming together a sort of vegeto-human pollen, the

muted fiddles feebly pushed their notes, in marked contrast to the

spirit with which the measure was trodden out. They coughed as

they danced, and laughed as they coughed. Of the rushing couples

there could barely be discerned more than the high lights--the

indistinctness shaping them to satyrs clasping nymphs--a multiplicity

of Pans whirling a multiplicity of Syrinxes; Lotis attempting to

elude Priapus, and always failing.

At intervals a couple would approach the doorway for air, and

the haze no longer veiling their features, the demigods resolved

themselves into the homely personalities of her own next-door

neighbours. Could Trantridge in two or three short hours have

metamorphosed itself thus madly!

Some Sileni of the throng sat on benches and hay-trusses by the wall;

and one of them recognized her.

"The maids don't think it respectable to dance at The Flower-de-Luce,"

he explained. "They don't like to let everybody see which be their

fancy-men. Besides, the house sometimes shuts up just when their

jints begin to get greased. So we come here and send out for

liquor."

"But when be any of you going home?" asked Tess with some anxiety.

"Now--a'most directly. This is all but the last jig."

She waited. The reel drew to a close, and some of the party were in

the mind of starting. But others would not, and another dance was

formed. This surely would end it, thought Tess. But it merged in

yet another. She became restless and uneasy; yet, having waited so

long, it was necessary to wait longer; on account of the fair the

roads were dotted with roving characters of possibly ill intent; and,

though not fearful of measurable dangers, she feared the unknown.

Had she been near Marlott she would have had less dread.

"Don't ye be nervous, my dear good soul," expostulated, between his

coughs, a young man with a wet face and his straw hat so far back

upon his head that the brim encircled it like the nimbus of a saint.

"What's yer hurry? To-morrow is Sunday, thank God, and we can sleep

it off in church-time. Now, have a turn with me?"

She did not abhor dancing, but she was not going to dance here. The

movement grew more passionate: the fiddlers behind the luminous

pillar of cloud now and then varied the air by playing on the wrong

side of the bridge or with the back of the bow. But it did not

matter; the panting shapes spun onwards.

They did not vary their partners if their inclination were to stick

to previous ones. Changing partners simply meant that a satisfactory

choice had not as yet been arrived at by one or other of the pair,

and by this time every couple had been suitably matched. It was then

that the ecstasy and the dream began, in which emotion was the matter

of the universe, and matter but an adventitious intrusion likely to

hinder you from spinning where you wanted to spin.

Suddenly there was a dull thump on the ground: a couple had fallen,

and lay in a mixed heap. The next couple, unable to check its

progress, came toppling over the obstacle. An inner cloud of dust

rose around the prostrate figures amid the general one of the room,

in which a twitching entanglement of arms and legs was discernible.

"You shall catch it for this, my gentleman, when you get home!" burst

in female accents from the human heap--those of the unhappy partner

of the man whose clumsiness had caused the mishap; she happened

also to be his recently married wife, in which assortment there was

nothing unusual at Trantridge as long as any affection remained

between wedded couples; and, indeed, it was not uncustomary in their

later lives, to avoid making odd lots of the single people between

whom there might be a warm understanding.

A loud laugh from behind Tess's back, in the shade of the garden,

united with the titter within the room. She looked round, and saw

the red coal of a cigar: Alec d'Urberville was standing there alone.

He beckoned to her, and she reluctantly retreated towards him.

"Well, my Beauty, what are you doing here?"

She was so tired after her long day and her walk that she confided

her trouble to him--that she had been waiting ever since he saw her

to have their company home, because the road at night was strange to

her. "But it seems they will never leave off, and I really think I

will wait no longer."

"Certainly do not. I have only a saddle-horse here to-day; but come

to The Flower-de-Luce, and I'll hire a trap, and drive you home with

me."

Tess, though flattered, had never quite got over her original

mistrust of him, and, despite their tardiness, she preferred to walk

home with the work-folk. So she answered that she was much obliged

to him, but would not trouble him. "I have said that I will wait for

'em, and they will expect me to now."

"Very well, Miss Independence. Please yourself... Then I shall not

hurry... My good Lord, what a kick-up they are having there!"

He had not put himself forward into the light, but some of them

had perceived him, and his presence led to a slight pause and a

consideration of how the time was flying. As soon as he had re-lit

a cigar and walked away the Trantridge people began to collect

themselves from amid those who had come in from other farms, and

prepared to leave in a body. Their bundles and baskets were gathered

up, and half an hour later, when the clock-chime sounded a quarter

past eleven, they were straggling along the lane which led up the

hill towards their homes.

It was a three-mile walk, along a dry white road, made whiter

to-night by the light of the moon.

Tess soon perceived as she walked in the flock, sometimes with this

one, sometimes with that, that the fresh night air was producing

staggerings and serpentine courses among the men who had partaken too

freely; some of the more careless women also were wandering in their

gait--to wit, a dark virago, Car Darch, dubbed Queen of Spades, till

lately a favourite of d'Urberville's; Nancy, her sister, nicknamed

the Queen of Diamonds; and the young married woman who had already

tumbled down. Yet however terrestrial and lumpy their appearance

just now to the mean unglamoured eye, to themselves the case was

different. They followed the road with a sensation that they were

soaring along in a supporting medium, possessed of original and

profound thoughts, themselves and surrounding nature forming

an organism of which all the parts harmoniously and joyously

interpenetrated each other. They were as sublime as the moon and

stars above them, and the moon and stars were as ardent as they.

Tess, however, had undergone such painful experiences of this kind in

her father's house that the discovery of their condition spoilt the

pleasure she was beginning to feel in the moonlight journey. Yet she

stuck to the party, for reasons above given.

In the open highway they had progressed in scattered order; but now

their route was through a field-gate, and the foremost finding a

difficulty in opening it, they closed up together.

This leading pedestrian was Car the Queen of Spades, who carried a

wicker-basket containing her mother's groceries, her own draperies,

and other purchases for the week. The basket being large and heavy,

Car had placed it for convenience of porterage on the top of her

head, where it rode on in jeopardized balance as she walked with

arms akimbo.

"Well--whatever is that a-creeping down thy back, Car Darch?" said

one of the group suddenly.

All looked at Car. Her gown was a light cotton print, and from the

back of her head a kind of rope could be seen descending to some

distance below her waist, like a Chinaman's queue.

"'Tis her hair falling down," said another.

No; it was not her hair: it was a black stream of something oozing

from her basket, and it glistened like a slimy snake in the cold

still rays of the moon.

"'Tis treacle," said an observant matron.

Treacle it was. Car's poor old grandmother had a weakness for the

sweet stuff. Honey she had in plenty out of her own hives, but

treacle was what her soul desired, and Car had been about to give her

a treat of surprise. Hastily lowering the basket the dark girl found

that the vessel containing the syrup had been smashed within.

By this time there had arisen a shout of laughter at the

extraordinary appearance of Car's back, which irritated the dark

queen into getting rid of the disfigurement by the first sudden means

available, and independently of the help of the scoffers. She rushed

excitedly into the field they were about to cross, and flinging

herself flat on her back upon the grass, began to wipe her gown

as well as she could by spinning horizontally on the herbage and

dragging herself over it upon her elbows.

The laughter rang louder; they clung to the gate, to the posts,

rested on their staves, in the weakness engendered by their

convulsions at the spectacle of Car. Our heroine, who had hitherto

held her peace, at this wild moment could not help joining in with

the rest.

It was a misfortune--in more ways than one. No sooner did the dark

queen hear the soberer richer note of Tess among those of the other

work-people than a long-smouldering sense of rivalry inflamed her to

madness. She sprang to her feet and closely faced the object of her

dislike.

"How darest th' laugh at me, hussy!" she cried.

"I couldn't really help it when t'others did," apologized Tess,

still tittering.

"Ah, th'st think th' beest everybody, dostn't, because th' beest

first favourite with He just now! But stop a bit, my lady, stop a

bit! I'm as good as two of such! Look here--here's at 'ee!"

To Tess's horror the dark queen began stripping off the bodice of

her gown--which for the added reason of its ridiculed condition she

was only too glad to be free of--till she had bared her plump neck,

shoulders, and arms to the moonshine, under which they looked as

luminous and beautiful as some Praxitelean creation, in their

possession of the faultless rotundities of a lusty country-girl.

She closed her fists and squared up at Tess.

"Indeed, then, I shall not fight!" said the latter majestically; "and

if I had know you was of that sort, I wouldn't have so let myself

down as to come with such a whorage as this is!"

The rather too inclusive speech brought down a torrent of

vituperation from other quarters upon fair Tess's unlucky head,

particularly from the Queen of Diamonds, who having stood in the

relations to d'Urberville that Car had also been suspected of, united

with the latter against the common enemy. Several other women also

chimed in, with an animus which none of them would have been so

fatuous as to show but for the rollicking evening they had passed.

Thereupon, finding Tess unfairly browbeaten, the husbands and lovers

tried to make peace by defending her; but the result of that attempt

was directly to increase the war.

Tess was indignant and ashamed. She no longer minded the loneliness

of the way and the lateness of the hour; her one object was to get

away from the whole crew as soon as possible. She knew well enough

that the better among them would repent of their passion next day.

They were all now inside the field, and she was edging back to rush

off alone when a horseman emerged almost silently from the corner of

the hedge that screened the road, and Alec d'Urberville looked round

upon them.

"What the devil is all this row about, work-folk?" he asked.

The explanation was not readily forthcoming; and, in truth, he did

not require any. Having heard their voices while yet some way off he

had ridden creepingly forward, and learnt enough to satisfy himself.

Tess was standing apart from the rest, near the gate. He bent over

towards her. "Jump up behind me," he whispered, "and we'll get shot

of the screaming cats in a jiffy!"

She felt almost ready to faint, so vivid was her sense of the crisis.

At almost any other moment of her life she would have refused such

proffered aid and company, as she had refused them several times

before; and now the loneliness would not of itself have forced her

to do otherwise. But coming as the invitation did at the particular

juncture when fear and indignation at these adversaries could be

transformed by a spring of the foot into a triumph over them, she

abandoned herself to her impulse, climbed the gate, put her toe upon

his instep, and scrambled into the saddle behind him. The pair were

speeding away into the distant gray by the time that the contentious

revellers became aware of what had happened.

The Queen of Spades forgot the stain on her bodice, and stood

beside the Queen of Diamonds and the new-married, staggering young

woman--all with a gaze of fixity in the direction in which the

horse's tramp was diminishing into silence on the road.

"What be ye looking at?" asked a man who had not observed the

incident.

"Ho-ho-ho!" laughed dark Car.

"Hee-hee-hee!" laughed the tippling bride, as she steadied herself on

the arm of her fond husband.

"Heu-heu-heu!" laughed dark Car's mother, stroking her moustache as

she explained laconically: "Out of the frying-pan into the fire!"

Then these children of the open air, whom even excess of alcohol

could scarce injure permanently, betook themselves to the field-path;

and as they went there moved onward with them, around the shadow of

each one's head, a circle of opalized light, formed by the moon's

rays upon the glistening sheet of dew. Each pedestrian could see

no halo but his or her own, which never deserted the head-shadow,

whatever its vulgar unsteadiness might be; but adhered to it, and

persistently beautified it; till the erratic motions seemed an

inherent part of the irradiation, and the fumes of their breathing

a component of the night's mist; and the spirit of the scene, and

of the moonlight, and of Nature, seemed harmoniously to mingle with

the spirit of wine.

XI

The twain cantered along for some time without speech, Tess as she

clung to him still panting in her triumph, yet in other respects

dubious. She had perceived that the horse was not the spirited one

he sometimes rose, and felt no alarm on that score, though her seat

was precarious enough despite her tight hold of him. She begged him

to slow the animal to a walk, which Alec accordingly did.

"Neatly done, was it not, dear Tess?" he said by and by.

"Yes!" said she. "I am sure I ought to be much obliged to you."

"And are you?"

She did not reply.

"Tess, why do you always dislike my kissing you?"

"I suppose--because I don't love you."

"You are quite sure?"

"I am angry with you sometimes!"

"Ah, I half feared as much." Nevertheless, Alec did not object to

that confession. He knew that anything was better then frigidity.

"Why haven't you told me when I have made you angry?"

"You know very well why. Because I cannot help myself here."

"I haven't offended you often by love-making?"

"You have sometimes."

"How many times?"

"You know as well as I--too many times."

"Every time I have tried?"

She was silent, and the horse ambled along for a considerable

distance, till a faint luminous fog, which had hung in the hollows

all the evening, became general and enveloped them. It seemed to

hold the moonlight in suspension, rendering it more pervasive than in

clear air. Whether on this account, or from absent-mindedness, or

from sleepiness, she did not perceive that they had long ago passed

the point at which the lane to Trantridge branched from the highway,

and that her conductor had not taken the Trantridge track.

She was inexpressibly weary. She had risen at five o'clock every

morning of that week, had been on foot the whole of each day, and on

this evening had in addition walked the three miles to Chaseborough,

waited three hours for her neighbours without eating or drinking,

her impatience to start them preventing either; she had then walked

a mile of the way home, and had undergone the excitement of the

quarrel, till, with the slow progress of their steed, it was now

nearly one o'clock. Only once, however, was she overcome by actual

drowsiness. In that moment of oblivion her head sank gently against

him.

D'Urberville stopped the horse, withdrew his feet from the stirrups,

turned sideways on the saddle, and enclosed her waist with his arm to

support her.

This immediately put her on the defensive, and with one of those

sudden impulses of reprisal to which she was liable she gave him a

little push from her. In his ticklish position he nearly lost his

balance and only just avoided rolling over into the road, the horse,

though a powerful one, being fortunately the quietest he rode.

"That is devilish unkind!" he said. "I mean no harm--only to keep

you from falling."

She pondered suspiciously, till, thinking that this might after all

be true, she relented, and said quite humbly, "I beg your pardon,

sir."

"I won't pardon you unless you show some confidence in me. Good

God!" he burst out, "what am I, to be repulsed so by a mere chit like

you? For near three mortal months have you trifled with my feelings,

eluded me, and snubbed me; and I won't stand it!"

"I'll leave you to-morrow, sir."

"No, you will not leave me to-morrow! Will you, I ask once more,

show your belief in me by letting me clasp you with my arm? Come,

between us two and nobody else, now. We know each other well; and

you know that I love you, and think you the prettiest girl in the

world, which you are. Mayn't I treat you as a lover?"

She drew a quick pettish breath of objection, writhing uneasily on

her seat, looked far ahead, and murmured, "I don't know--I wish--how

can I say yes or no when--"

He settled the matter by clasping his arm round her as he desired,

and Tess expressed no further negative. Thus they sidled

slowly onward till it struck her they had been advancing for an

unconscionable time--far longer than was usually occupied by the

short journey from Chaseborough, even at this walking pace, and

that they were no longer on hard road, but in a mere trackway.

"Why, where be we?" she exclaimed.

"Passing by a wood."

"A wood--what wood? Surely we are quite out of the road?"

"A bit of The Chase--the oldest wood in England. It is a lovely

night, and why should we not prolong our ride a little?"

"How could you be so treacherous!" said Tess, between archness and

real dismay, and getting rid of his arm by pulling open his fingers

one by one, though at the risk of slipping off herself. "Just when

I've been putting such trust in you, and obliging you to please you,

because I thought I had wronged you by that push! Please set me

down, and let me walk home."

"You cannot walk home, darling, even if the air were clear. We are

miles away from Trantridge, if I must tell you, and in this growing

fog you might wander for hours among these trees."

"Never mind that," she coaxed. "Put me down, I beg you. I don't

mind where it is; only let me get down, sir, please!"

"Very well, then, I will--on one condition. Having brought you

here to this out-of-the-way place, I feel myself responsible for

your safe-conduct home, whatever you may yourself feel about it.

As to your getting to Trantridge without assistance, it is quite

impossible; for, to tell the truth, dear, owing to this fog, which so

disguises everything, I don't quite know where we are myself. Now,

if you will promise to wait beside the horse while I walk through the

bushes till I come to some road or house, and ascertain exactly our

whereabouts, I'll deposit you here willingly. When I come back I'll

give you full directions, and if you insist upon walking you may; or

you may ride--at your pleasure."

She accepted these terms, and slid off on the near side, though not

till he had stolen a cursory kiss. He sprang down on the other side.

"I suppose I must hold the horse?" said she.

"Oh no; it's not necessary," replied Alec, patting the panting

creature. "He's had enough of it for to-night."

He turned the horse's head into the bushes, hitched him on to a

bough, and made a sort of couch or nest for her in the deep mass of

dead leaves.

"Now, you sit there," he said. "The leaves have not got damp as yet.

Just give an eye to the horse--it will be quite sufficient."

He took a few steps away from her, but, returning, said, "By the bye,

Tess, your father has a new cob to-day. Somebody gave it to him."

"Somebody? You!"

D'Urberville nodded.

"O how very good of you that is!" she exclaimed, with a painful sense

of the awkwardness of having to thank him just then.

"And the children have some toys."

"I didn't know--you ever sent them anything!" she murmured, much

moved. "I almost wish you had not--yes, I almost wish it!"

"Why, dear?"

"It--hampers me so."

"Tessy--don't you love me ever so little now?"

"I'm grateful," she reluctantly admitted. "But I fear I do not--"

The sudden vision of his passion for herself as a factor in this

result so distressed her that, beginning with one slow tear, and

then following with another, she wept outright.

"Don't cry, dear, dear one! Now sit down here, and wait till I

come." She passively sat down amid the leaves he had heaped, and

shivered slightly. "Are you cold?" he asked.

"Not very--a little."

He touched her with his fingers, which sank into her as into down.

"You have only that puffy muslin dress on--how's that?"

"It's my best summer one. 'Twas very warm when I started, and I

didn't know I was going to ride, and that it would be night."

"Nights grow chilly in September. Let me see." He pulled off a

light overcoat that he had worn, and put it round her tenderly.

"That's it--now you'll feel warmer," he continued. "Now, my pretty,

rest there; I shall soon be back again."

Having buttoned the overcoat round her shoulders he plunged into the

webs of vapour which by this time formed veils between the trees.

She could hear the rustling of the branches as he ascended the

adjoining slope, till his movements were no louder than the hopping

of a bird, and finally died away. With the setting of the moon the

pale light lessened, and Tess became invisible as she fell into

reverie upon the leaves where he had left her.

In the meantime Alec d'Urberville had pushed on up the slope to clear

his genuine doubt as to the quarter of The Chase they were in. He

had, in fact, ridden quite at random for over an hour, taking any

turning that came to hand in order to prolong companionship with her,

and giving far more attention to Tess's moonlit person than to any

wayside object. A little rest for the jaded animal being desirable,

he did not hasten his search for landmarks. A clamber over the

hill into the adjoining vale brought him to the fence of a highway

whose contours he recognized, which settled the question of their

whereabouts. D'Urberville thereupon turned back; but by this time

the moon had quite gone down, and partly on account of the fog The

Chase was wrapped in thick darkness, although morning was not far

off. He was obliged to advance with outstretched hands to avoid

contact with the boughs, and discovered that to hit the exact spot

from which he had started was at first entirely beyond him. Roaming

up and down, round and round, he at length heard a slight movement of

the horse close at hand; and the sleeve of his overcoat unexpectedly

caught his foot.

"Tess!" said d'Urberville.

There was no answer. The obscurity was now so great that he could

see absolutely nothing but a pale nebulousness at his feet, which

represented the white muslin figure he had left upon the dead leaves.

Everything else was blackness alike. D'Urberville stooped; and heard

a gentle regular breathing. He knelt and bent lower, till her breath

warmed his face, and in a moment his cheek was in contact with hers.

She was sleeping soundly, and upon her eyelashes there lingered

tears.

Darkness and silence ruled everywhere around. Above them rose the

primeval yews and oaks of The Chase, in which there poised gentle

roosting birds in their last nap; and about them stole the hopping

rabbits and hares. But, might some say, where was Tess's guardian

angel? where was the providence of her simple faith? Perhaps, like

that other god of whom the ironical Tishbite spoke, he was talking,

or he was pursuing, or he was in a journey, or he was sleeping and

not to be awaked.

Why it was that upon this beautiful feminine tissue, sensitive as

gossamer, and practically blank as snow as yet, there should have

been traced such a coarse pattern as it was doomed to receive; why

so often the coarse appropriates the finer thus, the wrong man the

woman, the wrong woman the man, many thousand years of analytical

philosophy have failed to explain to our sense of order. One may,

indeed, admit the possibility of a retribution lurking in the present

catastrophe. Doubtless some of Tess d'Urberville's mailed ancestors

rollicking home from a fray had dealt the same measure even more

ruthlessly towards peasant girls of their time. But though to visit

the sins of the fathers upon the children may be a morality good

enough for divinities, it is scorned by average human nature; and it

therefore does not mend the matter.

As Tess's own people down in those retreats are never tired of saying

among each other in their fatalistic way: "It was to be." There

lay the pity of it. An immeasurable social chasm was to divide our

heroine's personality thereafter from that previous self of hers

who stepped from her mother's door to try her fortune at Trantridge

poultry-farm.

END OF PHASE THE FIRST

Phase the Second: Maiden No More

XII

The basket was heavy and the bundle was large, but she lugged them

along like a person who did not find her especial burden in material

things. Occasionally she stopped to rest in a mechanical way by some

gate or post; and then, giving the baggage another hitch upon her

full round arm, went steadily on again.

It was a Sunday morning in late October, about four months after Tess

Durbeyfield's arrival at Trantridge, and some few weeks subsequent to

the night ride in The Chase. The time was not long past daybreak,

and the yellow luminosity upon the horizon behind her back lighted

the ridge towards which her face was set--the barrier of the vale

wherein she had of late been a stranger--which she would have to

climb over to reach her birthplace. The ascent was gradual on this

side, and the soil and scenery differed much from those within

Blakemore Vale. Even the character and accent of the two peoples

had shades of difference, despite the amalgamating effects of a

roundabout railway; so that, though less than twenty miles from the

place of her sojourn at Trantridge, her native village had seemed a

far-away spot. The field-folk shut in there traded northward and

westward, travelled, courted, and married northward and westward,

thought northward and westward; those on this side mainly directed

their energies and attention to the east and south.

The incline was the same down which d'Urberville had driven her so

wildly on that day in June. Tess went up the remainder of its length

without stopping, and on reaching the edge of the escarpment gazed

over the familiar green world beyond, now half-veiled in mist. It

was always beautiful from here; it was terribly beautiful to Tess

to-day, for since her eyes last fell upon it she had learnt that the

serpent hisses where the sweet birds sing, and her views of life had

been totally changed for her by the lesson. Verily another girl than

the simple one she had been at home was she who, bowed by thought,

stood still here, and turned to look behind her. She could not bear

to look forward into the Vale.

Ascending by the long white road that Tess herself had just laboured

up, she saw a two-wheeled vehicle, beside which walked a man, who

held up his hand to attract her attention.

She obeyed the signal to wait for him with unspeculative repose, and

in a few minutes man and horse stopped beside her.

"Why did you slip away by stealth like this?" said d'Urberville, with

upbraiding breathlessness; "on a Sunday morning, too, when people

were all in bed! I only discovered it by accident, and I have been

driving like the deuce to overtake you. Just look at the mare. Why

go off like this? You know that nobody wished to hinder your going.

And how unnecessary it has been for you to toil along on foot, and

encumber yourself with this heavy load! I have followed like a

madman, simply to drive you the rest of the distance, if you won't

come back."

"I shan't come back," said she.

"I thought you wouldn't--I said so! Well, then, put up your basket,

and let me help you on."

She listlessly placed her basket and bundle within the dog-cart, and

stepped up, and they sat side by side. She had no fear of him now,

and in the cause of her confidence her sorrow lay.

D'Urberville mechanically lit a cigar, and the journey was continued

with broken unemotional conversation on the commonplace objects by

the wayside. He had quite forgotten his struggle to kiss her when,

in the early summer, they had driven in the opposite direction along

the same road. But she had not, and she sat now, like a puppet,

replying to his remarks in monosyllables. After some miles they came

in view of the clump of trees beyond which the village of Marlott

stood. It was only then that her still face showed the least

emotion, a tear or two beginning to trickle down.

"What are you crying for?" he coldly asked.

"I was only thinking that I was born over there," murmured Tess.

"Well--we must all be born somewhere."

"I wish I had never been born--there or anywhere else!"

"Pooh! Well, if you didn't wish to come to Trantridge why did you

come?"

She did not reply.

"You didn't come for love of me, that I'll swear."

"'Tis quite true. If I had gone for love o' you, if I had ever

sincerely loved you, if I loved you still, I should not so loathe and

hate myself for my weakness as I do now! ... My eyes were dazed by

you for a little, and that was all."

He shrugged his shoulders. She resumed--

"I didn't understand your meaning till it was too late."

"That's what every woman says."

"How can you dare to use such words!" she cried, turning impetuously

upon him, her eyes flashing as the latent spirit (of which he was to

see more some day) awoke in her. "My God! I could knock you out of

the gig! Did it never strike your mind that what every woman says

some women may feel?"

"Very well," he said, laughing; "I am sorry to wound you. I did

wrong--I admit it." He dropped into some little bitterness as he

continued: "Only you needn't be so everlastingly flinging it in my

face. I am ready to pay to the uttermost farthing. You know you

need not work in the fields or the dairies again. You know you may

clothe yourself with the best, instead of in the bald plain way you

have lately affected, as if you couldn't get a ribbon more than you

earn."

Her lip lifted slightly, though there was little scorn, as a rule,

in her large and impulsive nature.

"I have said I will not take anything more from you, and I will

not--I cannot! I SHOULD be your creature to go on doing that, and

I won't!"

"One would think you were a princess from your manner, in addition

to a true and original d'Urberville--ha! ha! Well, Tess, dear, I

can say no more. I suppose I am a bad fellow--a damn bad fellow.

I was born bad, and I have lived bad, and I shall die bad in all

probability. But, upon my lost soul, I won't be bad towards you

again, Tess. And if certain circumstances should arise--you

understand--in which you are in the least need, the least difficulty,

send me one line, and you shall have by return whatever you require.

I may not be at Trantridge--I am going to London for a time--I can't

stand the old woman. But all letters will be forwarded."

She said that she did not wish him to drive her further, and they

stopped just under the clump of trees. D'Urberville alighted, and

lifted her down bodily in his arms, afterwards placing her articles

on the ground beside her. She bowed to him slightly, her eye just

lingering in his; and then she turned to take the parcels for

departure.

Alec d'Urberville removed his cigar, bent towards her, and said--

"You are not going to turn away like that, dear! Come!"

"If you wish," she answered indifferently. "See how you've mastered

me!"

She thereupon turned round and lifted her face to his, and remained

like a marble term while he imprinted a kiss upon her cheek--half

perfunctorily, half as if zest had not yet quite died out. Her eyes

vaguely rested upon the remotest trees in the lane while the kiss was

given, as though she were nearly unconscious of what he did.

"Now the other side, for old acquaintance' sake."

She turned her head in the same passive way, as one might turn at the

request of a sketcher or hairdresser, and he kissed the other side,

his lips touching cheeks that were damp and smoothly chill as the

skin of the mushrooms in the fields around.

"You don't give me your mouth and kiss me back. You never willingly

do that--you'll never love me, I fear."

"I have said so, often. It is true. I have never really and truly

loved you, and I think I never can." She added mournfully, "Perhaps,

of all things, a lie on this thing would do the most good to me now;

but I have honour enough left, little as 'tis, not to tell that lie.

If I did love you, I may have the best o' causes for letting you know

it. But I don't."

He emitted a laboured breath, as if the scene were getting rather

oppressive to his heart, or to his conscience, or to his gentility.

"Well, you are absurdly melancholy, Tess. I have no

reason for flattering you now, and I can say plainly

that you need not be so sad. You can hold your own for

beauty against any woman of these parts, gentle or

simple; I say it to you as a practical man and

well-wisher. If you are wise you will show it to the

world more than you do before it fades... And yet,

Tess, will you come back to me! Upon my soul, I don't

like to let you go like this!"

"Never, never! I made up my mind as soon as I saw--what I ought to

have seen sooner; and I won't come."

"Then good morning, my four months' cousin--good-bye!"

He leapt up lightly, arranged the reins, and was gone between the

tall red-berried hedges.

Tess did not look after him, but slowly wound along the crooked lane.

It was still early, and though the sun's lower limb was just free of

the hill, his rays, ungenial and peering, addressed the eye rather

than the touch as yet. There was not a human soul near. Sad October

and her sadder self seemed the only two existences haunting that

lane.

As she walked, however, some footsteps approached behind her, the

footsteps of a man; and owing to the briskness of his advance he was

close at her heels and had said "Good morning" before she had been

long aware of his propinquity. He appeared to be an artisan of some

sort, and carried a tin pot of red paint in his hand. He asked

in a business-like manner if he should take her basket, which she

permitted him to do, walking beside him.

"It is early to be astir this Sabbath morn!" he said cheerfully.

"Yes," said Tess.

"When most people are at rest from their week's work."

She also assented to this.

"Though I do more real work to-day than all the week besides."

"Do you?"

"All the week I work for the glory of man, and on Sunday for the

glory of God. That's more real than the other--hey? I have a little

to do here at this stile." The man turned, as he spoke, to an

opening at the roadside leading into a pasture. "If you'll wait a

moment," he added, "I shall not be long."

As he had her basket she could not well do otherwise; and she waited,

observing him. He set down her basket and the tin pot, and stirring

the paint with the brush that was in it began painting large square

letters on the middle board of the three composing the stile, placing

a comma after each word, as if to give pause while that word was

driven well home to the reader's heart--

THY, DAMNATION, SLUMBERETH, NOT.

2 Pet. ii. 3.

Against the peaceful landscape, the pale, decaying tints of the

copses, the blue air of the horizon, and the lichened stile-boards,

these staring vermilion words shone forth. They seemed to shout

themselves out and make the atmosphere ring. Some people might have

cried "Alas, poor Theology!" at the hideous defacement--the last

grotesque phase of a creed which had served mankind well in its time.

But the words entered Tess with accusatory horror. It was as if this

man had known her recent history; yet he was a total stranger.

Having finished his text he picked up her basket, and she

mechanically resumed her walk beside him.

"Do you believe what you paint?" she asked in low tones.

"Believe that tex? Do I believe in my own existence!"

"But," said she tremulously, "suppose your sin was not of your own

seeking?"

He shook his head.

"I cannot split hairs on that burning query," he said. "I have

walked hundreds of miles this past summer, painting these texes on

every wall, gate, and stile the length and breadth of this district.

I leave their application to the hearts of the people who read 'em."

"I think they are horrible," said Tess. "Crushing! Killing!"

"That's what they are meant to be!" he replied in a trade voice.

"But you should read my hottest ones--them I kips for slums and

seaports. They'd make ye wriggle! Not but what this is a very good

tex for rural districts. ... Ah--there's a nice bit of blank wall up

by that barn standing to waste. I must put one there--one that it

will be good for dangerous young females like yerself to heed. Will

ye wait, missy?"

"No," said she; and taking her basket Tess trudged on. A little way

forward she turned her head. The old gray wall began to advertise

a similar fiery lettering to the first, with a strange and unwonted

mien, as if distressed at duties it had never before been called upon

to perform. It was with a sudden flush that she read and realized

what was to be the inscription he was now halfway through--

THOU, SHALT, NOT, COMMIT--

Her cheerful friend saw her looking, stopped his brush, and shouted--

"If you want to ask for edification on these things of moment,

there's a very earnest good man going to preach a charity-sermon

to-day in the parish you are going to--Mr Clare of Emminster. I'm

not of his persuasion now, but he's a good man, and he'll expound as

well as any parson I know. 'Twas he began the work in me."

But Tess did not answer; she throbbingly resumed her walk, her eyes

fixed on the ground. "Pooh--I don't believe God said such things!"

she murmured contemptuously when her flush had died away.

A plume of smoke soared up suddenly from her father's chimney, the

sight of which made her heart ache. The aspect of the interior, when

she reached it, made her heart ache more. Her mother, who had just

come down stairs, turned to greet her from the fireplace, where she

was kindling barked-oak twigs under the breakfast kettle. The young

children were still above, as was also her father, it being Sunday

morning, when he felt justified in lying an additional half-hour.

"Well!--my dear Tess!" exclaimed her surprised mother, jumping up and

kissing the girl. "How be ye? I didn't see you till you was in upon

me! Have you come home to be married?"

"No, I have not come for that, mother."

"Then for a holiday?"

"Yes--for a holiday; for a long holiday," said Tess.

"What, isn't your cousin going to do the handsome thing?"

"He's not my cousin, and he's not going to marry me."

Her mother eyed her narrowly.

"Come, you have not told me all," she said.

Then Tess went up to her mother, put her face upon Joan's neck, and

told.

"And yet th'st not got him to marry 'ee!" reiterated her mother. "Any

woman would have done it but you, after that!"

"Perhaps any woman would except me."

"It would have been something like a story to come back with, if

you had!" continued Mrs Durbeyfield, ready to burst into tears of

vexation. "After all the talk about you and him which has reached

us here, who would have expected it to end like this! Why didn't ye

think of doing some good for your family instead o' thinking only of

yourself? See how I've got to teave and slave, and your poor weak

father with his heart clogged like a dripping-pan. I did hope for

something to come out o' this! To see what a pretty pair you and he

made that day when you drove away together four months ago! See what

he has given us--all, as we thought, because we were his kin. But if

he's not, it must have been done because of his love for 'ee. And

yet you've not got him to marry!"

Get Alec d'Urberville in the mind to marry her! He marry HER! On

matrimony he had never once said a word. And what if he had? How a

convulsive snatching at social salvation might have impelled her to

answer him she could not say. But her poor foolish mother little

knew her present feeling towards this man. Perhaps it was unusual

in the circumstances, unlucky, unaccountable; but there it was; and

this, as she had said, was what made her detest herself. She had

never wholly cared for him; she did not at all care for him now. She

had dreaded him, winced before him, succumbed to adroit advantages

he took of her helplessness; then, temporarily blinded by his ardent

manners, had been stirred to confused surrender awhile: had suddenly

despised and disliked him, and had run away. That was all. Hate him

she did not quite; but he was dust and ashes to her, and even for her

name's sake she scarcely wished to marry him.

"You ought to have been more careful if you didn't mean to get him to

make you his wife!"

"O mother, my mother!" cried the agonized girl, turning passionately

upon her parent as if her poor heart would break. "How could I be

expected to know? I was a child when I left this house four months

ago. Why didn't you tell me there was danger in men-folk? Why

didn't you warn me? Ladies know what to fend hands against, because

they read novels that tell them of these tricks; but I never had the

chance o' learning in that way, and you did not help me!"

Her mother was subdued.

"I thought if I spoke of his fond feelings and what they might lead

to, you would be hontish wi' him and lose your chance," she murmured,

wiping her eyes with her apron. "Well, we must make the best of it,

I suppose. 'Tis nater, after all, and what do please God!"

XIII

The event of Tess Durbeyfield's return from the manor of her bogus

kinsfolk was rumoured abroad, if rumour be not too large a word for

a space of a square mile. In the afternoon several young girls of

Marlott, former schoolfellows and acquaintances of Tess, called to

see her, arriving dressed in their best starched and ironed, as

became visitors to a person who had made a transcendent conquest (as

they supposed), and sat round the room looking at her with great

curiosity. For the fact that it was this said thirty-first cousin,

Mr d'Urberville, who had fallen in love with her, a gentleman

not altogether local, whose reputation as a reckless gallant and

heartbreaker was beginning to spread beyond the immediate boundaries

of Trantridge, lent Tess's supposed position, by its fearsomeness, a

far higher fascination that it would have exercised if unhazardous.

Their interest was so deep that the younger ones whispered when her

back was turned--

"How pretty she is; and how that best frock do set her off! I

believe it cost an immense deal, and that it was a gift from him."

Tess, who was reaching up to get the tea-things from the

corner-cupboard, did not hear these commentaries. If she had heard

them, she might soon have set her friends right on the matter. But

her mother heard, and Joan's simple vanity, having been denied the

hope of a dashing marriage, fed itself as well as it could upon

the sensation of a dashing flirtation. Upon the whole she felt

gratified, even though such a limited and evanescent triumph should

involve her daughter's reputation; it might end in marriage yet, and

in the warmth of her responsiveness to their admiration she invited

her visitors to stay to tea.

Their chatter, their laughter, their good-humoured innuendoes, above

all, their flashes and flickerings of envy, revived Tess's spirits

also; and, as the evening wore on, she caught the infection of their

excitement, and grew almost gay. The marble hardness left her face,

she moved with something of her old bounding step, and flushed in all

her young beauty.

At moments, in spite of thought, she would reply to their inquiries

with a manner of superiority, as if recognizing that her experiences

in the field of courtship had, indeed, been slightly enviable. But

so far was she from being, in the words of Robert South, "in love

with her own ruin," that the illusion was transient as lightning;

cold reason came back to mock her spasmodic weakness; the ghastliness

of her momentary pride would convict her, and recall her to reserved

listlessness again.

And the despondency of the next morning's dawn, when it was no longer

Sunday, but Monday; and no best clothes; and the laughing visitors

were gone, and she awoke alone in her old bed, the innocent younger

children breathing softly around her. In place of the excitement of

her return, and the interest it had inspired, she saw before her a

long and stony highway which she had to tread, without aid, and with

little sympathy. Her depression was then terrible, and she could

have hidden herself in a tomb.

In the course of a few weeks Tess revived sufficiently to show

herself so far as was necessary to get to church one Sunday morning.

She liked to hear the chanting--such as it was--and the old Psalms,

and to join in the Morning Hymn. That innate love of melody, which

she had inherited from her ballad-singing mother, gave the simplest

music a power over her which could well-nigh drag her heart out of

her bosom at times.

To be as much out of observation as possible for reasons of her own,

and to escape the gallantries of the young men, she set out before

the chiming began, and took a back seat under the gallery, close to

the lumber, where only old men and women came, and where the bier

stood on end among the churchyard tools.

Parishioners dropped in by twos and threes, deposited themselves

in rows before her, rested three-quarters of a minute on their

foreheads as if they were praying, though they were not; then sat up,

and looked around. When the chants came on, one of her favourites

happened to be chosen among the rest--the old double chant

"Langdon"--but she did not know what it was called, though she would

much have liked to know. She thought, without exactly wording the

thought, how strange and god-like was a composer's power, who from

the grave could lead through sequences of emotion, which he alone had

felt at first, a girl like her who had never heard of his name, and

never would have a clue to his personality.

The people who had turned their heads turned them again as the

service proceeded; and at last observing her, they whispered to each

other. She knew what their whispers were about, grew sick at heart,

and felt that she could come to church no more.

The bedroom which she shared with some of the children formed her

retreat more continually than ever. Here, under her few square yards

of thatch, she watched winds, and snows, and rains, gorgeous sunsets,

and successive moons at their full. So close kept she that at length

almost everybody thought she had gone away.

The only exercise that Tess took at this time was after dark; and it

was then, when out in the woods, that she seemed least solitary. She

knew how to hit to a hair's-breadth that moment of evening when the

light and the darkness are so evenly balanced that the constraint of

day and the suspense of night neutralize each other, leaving absolute

mental liberty. It is then that the plight of being alive becomes

attenuated to its least possible dimensions. She had no fear of the

shadows; her sole idea seemed to be to shun mankind--or rather that

cold accretion called the world, which, so terrible in the mass, is

so unformidable, even pitiable, in its units.

On these lonely hills and dales her quiescent glide was of a piece

with the element she moved in. Her flexuous and stealthy figure

became an integral part of the scene. At times her whimsical fancy

would intensify natural processes around her till they seemed a part

of her own story. Rather they became a part of it; for the world is

only a psychological phenomenon, and what they seemed they were. The

midnight airs and gusts, moaning amongst the tightly-wrapped buds and

bark of the winter twigs, were formulae of bitter reproach. A wet

day was the expression of irremediable grief at her weakness in the

mind of some vague ethical being whom she could not class definitely

as the God of her childhood, and could not comprehend as any other.

But this encompassment of her own characterization, based on shreds

of convention, peopled by phantoms and voices antipathetic to her,

was a sorry and mistaken creation of Tess's fancy--a cloud of moral

hobgoblins by which she was terrified without reason. It was they

that were out of harmony with the actual world, not she. Walking

among the sleeping birds in the hedges, watching the skipping rabbits

on a moonlit warren, or standing under a pheasant-laden bough, she

looked upon herself as a figure of Guilt intruding into the haunts

of Innocence. But all the while she was making a distinction where

there was no difference. Feeling herself in antagonism, she was

quite in accord. She had been made to break an accepted social law,

but no law known to the environment in which she fancied herself such

an anomaly.

XIV

It was a hazy sunrise in August. The denser nocturnal vapours,

attacked by the warm beams, were dividing and shrinking into isolated

fleeces within hollows and coverts, where they waited till they

should be dried away to nothing.

The sun, on account of the mist, had a curious sentient, personal

look, demanding the masculine pronoun for its adequate expression.

His present aspect, coupled with the lack of all human forms in the

scene, explained the old-time heliolatries in a moment. One could

feel that a saner religion had never prevailed under the sky. The

luminary was a golden-haired, beaming, mild-eyed, God-like creature,

gazing down in the vigour and intentness of youth upon an earth that

was brimming with interest for him.

His light, a little later, broke though chinks of cottage shutters,

throwing stripes like red-hot pokers upon cupboards, chests of

drawers, and other furniture within; and awakening harvesters who

were not already astir.

But of all ruddy things that morning the brightest were two broad

arms of painted wood, which rose from the margin of yellow cornfield

hard by Marlott village. They, with two others below, formed the

revolving Maltese cross of the reaping-machine, which had been

brought to the field on the previous evening to be ready for

operations this day. The paint with which they were smeared,

intensified in hue by the sunlight, imparted to them a look of

having been dipped in liquid fire.

The field had already been "opened"; that is to say, a lane a few

feet wide had been hand-cut through the wheat along the whole

circumference of the field for the first passage of the horses and

machine.

Two groups, one of men and lads, the other of women, had come down

the lane just at the hour when the shadows of the eastern hedge-top

struck the west hedge midway, so that the heads of the groups were

enjoying sunrise while their feet were still in the dawn. They

disappeared from the lane between the two stone posts which flanked

the nearest field-gate.

Presently there arose from within a ticking like the love-making of

the grasshopper. The machine had begun, and a moving concatenation

of three horses and the aforesaid long rickety machine was visible

over the gate, a driver sitting upon one of the hauling horses,

and an attendant on the seat of the implement. Along one side of

the field the whole wain went, the arms of the mechanical reaper

revolving slowly, till it passed down the hill quite out of sight.

In a minute it came up on the other side of the field at the same

equable pace; the glistening brass star in the forehead of the fore

horse first catching the eye as it rose into view over the stubble,

then the bright arms, and then the whole machine.

The narrow lane of stubble encompassing the field grew wider with

each circuit, and the standing corn was reduced to a smaller area as

the morning wore on. Rabbits, hares, snakes, rats, mice, retreated

inwards as into a fastness, unaware of the ephemeral nature of their

refuge, and of the doom that awaited them later in the day when,

their covert shrinking to a more and more horrible narrowness, they

were huddled together, friends and foes, till the last few yards of

upright wheat fell also under the teeth of the unerring reaper, and

they were every one put to death by the sticks and stones of the

harvesters.

The reaping-machine left the fallen corn behind it in little heaps,

each heap being of the quantity for a sheaf; and upon these the

active binders in the rear laid their hands--mainly women, but some

of them men in print shirts, and trousers supported round their

waists by leather straps, rendering useless the two buttons behind,

which twinkled and bristled with sunbeams at every movement of each

wearer, as if they were a pair of eyes in the small of his back.

But those of the other sex were the most interesting of this company

of binders, by reason of the charm which is acquired by woman when

she becomes part and parcel of outdoor nature, and is not merely

an object set down therein as at ordinary times. A field-man is a

personality afield; a field-woman is a portion of the field; she had

somehow lost her own margin, imbibed the essence of her surrounding,

and assimilated herself with it.

The women--or rather girls, for they were mostly young--wore drawn

cotton bonnets with great flapping curtains to keep off the sun, and

gloves to prevent their hands being wounded by the stubble. There

was one wearing a pale pink jacket, another in a cream-coloured

tight-sleeved gown, another in a petticoat as red as the arms of the

reaping-machine; and others, older, in the brown-rough "wropper"

or over-all--the old-established and most appropriate dress of the

field-woman, which the young ones were abandoning. This morning the

eye returns involuntarily to the girl in the pink cotton jacket, she

being the most flexuous and finely-drawn figure of them all. But

her bonnet is pulled so far over her brow that none of her face is

disclosed while she binds, though her complexion may be guessed from

a stray twine or two of dark brown hair which extends below the

curtain of her bonnet. Perhaps one reason why she seduces casual

attention is that she never courts it, though the other women often

gaze around them.

Her binding proceeds with clock-like monotony. From the sheaf last

finished she draws a handful of ears, patting their tips with her

left palm to bring them even. Then, stooping low, she moves forward,

gathering the corn with both hands against her knees, and pushing

her left gloved hand under the bundle to meet the right on the other

side, holding the corn in an embrace like that of a lover. She

brings the ends of the bond together, and kneels on the sheaf while

she ties it, beating back her skirts now and then when lifted by the

breeze. A bit of her naked arm is visible between the buff leather

of the gauntlet and the sleeve of her gown; and as the day wears on

its feminine smoothness becomes scarified by the stubble and bleeds.

At intervals she stands up to rest, and to retie her disarranged

apron, or to pull her bonnet straight. Then one can see the oval

face of a handsome young woman with deep dark eyes and long heavy

clinging tresses, which seem to clasp in a beseeching way anything

they fall against. The cheeks are paler, the teeth more regular,

the red lips thinner than is usual in a country-bred girl.

It is Tess Durbeyfield, otherwise d'Urberville, somewhat changed--the

same, but not the same; at the present stage of her existence living

as a stranger and an alien here, though it was no strange land that

she was in. After a long seclusion she had come to a resolve to

undertake outdoor work in her native village, the busiest season of

the year in the agricultural world having arrived, and nothing that

she could do within the house being so remunerative for the time as

harvesting in the fields.

The movements of the other women were more or less similar to Tess's,

the whole bevy of them drawing together like dancers in a quadrille

at the completion of a sheaf by each, every one placing her sheaf on

end against those of the rest, till a shock, or "stitch" as it was

here called, of ten or a dozen was formed.

They went to breakfast, and came again, and the work proceeded as

before. As the hour of eleven drew near a person watching her might

have noticed that every now and then Tess's glance flitted wistfully

to the brow of the hill, though she did not pause in her sheafing.

On the verge of the hour the heads of a group of children, of ages

ranging from six to fourteen, rose over the stubbly convexity of the

hill.

The face of Tess flushed slightly, but still she did not pause.

The eldest of the comers, a girl who wore a triangular shawl, its

corner draggling on the stubble, carried in her arms what at first

sight seemed to be a doll, but proved to be an infant in long

clothes. Another brought some lunch. The harvesters ceased working,

took their provisions, and sat down against one of the shocks. Here

they fell to, the men plying a stone jar freely, and passing round a

cup.

Tess Durbeyfield had been one of the last to suspend her labours.

She sat down at the end of the shock, her face turned somewhat away

from her companions. When she had deposited herself a man in a

rabbit-skin cap, and with a red handkerchief tucked into his belt,

held the cup of ale over the top of the shock for her to drink. But

she did not accept his offer. As soon as her lunch was spread she

called up the big girl, her sister, and took the baby of her, who,

glad to be relieved of the burden, went away to the next shock and

joined the other children playing there. Tess, with a curiously

stealthy yet courageous movement, and with a still rising colour,

unfastened her frock and began suckling the child.

The men who sat nearest considerately turned their faces towards the

other end of the field, some of them beginning to smoke; one, with

absent-minded fondness, regretfully stroking the jar that would no

longer yield a stream. All the women but Tess fell into animated

talk, and adjusted the disarranged knots of their hair.

When the infant had taken its fill, the young mother sat it upright

in her lap, and looking into the far distance, dandled it with a

gloomy indifference that was almost dislike; then all of a sudden she

fell to violently kissing it some dozens of times, as if she could

never leave off, the child crying at the vehemence of an onset which

strangely combined passionateness with contempt.

"She's fond of that there child, though she mid pretend to hate en,

and say she wishes the baby and her too were in the churchyard,"

observed the woman in the red petticoat.

"She'll soon leave off saying that," replied the one in buff. "Lord,

'tis wonderful what a body can get used to o' that sort in time!"

"A little more than persuading had to do wi' the coming o't, I

reckon. There were they that heard a sobbing one night last year in

The Chase; and it mid ha' gone hard wi' a certain party if folks had

come along."

"Well, a little more, or a little less, 'twas a thousand pities that

it should have happened to she, of all others. But 'tis always the

comeliest! The plain ones be as safe as churches--hey, Jenny?" The

speaker turned to one of the group who certainly was not ill-defined

as plain.

It was a thousand pities, indeed; it was impossible for even an enemy

to feel otherwise on looking at Tess as she sat there, with her

flower-like mouth and large tender eyes, neither black nor blue nor

grey nor violet; rather all those shades together, and a hundred

others, which could be seen if one looked into their irises--shade

behind shade--tint beyond tint--around pupils that had no bottom; an

almost standard woman, but for the slight incautiousness of character

inherited from her race.

A resolution which had surprised herself had brought her into the

fields this week for the first time during many months. After

wearing and wasting her palpitating heart with every engine of regret

that lonely inexperience could devise, common sense had illuminated

her. She felt that she would do well to be useful again--to taste

anew sweet independence at any price. The past was past; whatever

it had been, it was no more at hand. Whatever its consequences,

time would close over them; they would all in a few years be as if

they had never been, and she herself grassed down and forgotten.

Meanwhile the trees were just as green as before; the birds sang and

the sun shone as clearly now as ever. The familiar surroundings had

not darkened because of her grief, nor sickened because of her pain.

She might have seen that what had bowed her head so profoundly--the

thought of the world's concern at her situation--was founded on an

illusion. She was not an existence, an experience, a passion, a

structure of sensations, to anybody but herself. To all humankind

besides, Tess was only a passing thought. Even to friends she was

no more than a frequently passing thought. If she made herself

miserable the livelong night and day it was only this much to

them--"Ah, she makes herself unhappy." If she tried to be cheerful,

to dismiss all care, to take pleasure in the daylight, the flowers,

the baby, she could only be this idea to them--"Ah, she bears it

very well." Moreover, alone in a desert island would she have been

wretched at what had happened to her? Not greatly. If she could

have been but just created, to discover herself as a spouseless

mother, with no experience of life except as the parent of a nameless

child, would the position have caused her to despair? No, she would

have taken it calmly, and found pleasure therein. Most of the misery

had been generated by her conventional aspect, and not by her innate

sensations.

Whatever Tess's reasoning, some spirit had induced her to dress

herself up neatly as she had formerly done, and come out into the

fields, harvest-hands being greatly in demand just then. This was

why she had borne herself with dignity, and had looked people calmly

in the face at times, even when holding the baby in her arms.

The harvest-men rose from the shock of corn, and stretched their

limbs, and extinguished their pipes. The horses, which had been

unharnessed and fed, were again attached to the scarlet machine.

Tess, having quickly eaten her own meal, beckoned to her eldest

sister to come and take away the baby, fastened her dress, put on

the buff gloves again, and stooped anew to draw a bond from the last

completed sheaf for the tying of the next.

In the afternoon and evening the proceedings of the morning were

continued, Tess staying on till dusk with the body of harvesters.

Then they all rode home in one of the largest wagons, in the company

of a broad tarnished moon that had risen from the ground to the

eastwards, its face resembling the outworn gold-leaf halo of some

worm-eaten Tuscan saint. Tess's female companions sang songs, and

showed themselves very sympathetic and glad at her reappearance out

of doors, though they could not refrain from mischievously throwing

in a few verses of the ballad about the maid who went to the merry

green wood and came back a changed state. There are counterpoises

and compensations in life; and the event which had made of her a

social warning had also for the moment made her the most interesting

personage in the village to many. Their friendliness won her still

farther away from herself, their lively spirits were contagious, and

she became almost gay.

But now that her moral sorrows were passing away a fresh one arose on

the natural side of her which knew no social law. When she reached

home it was to learn to her grief that the baby had been suddenly

taken ill since the afternoon. Some such collapse had been probable,

so tender and puny was its frame; but the event came as a shock

nevertheless.

The baby's offence against society in coming into the world was

forgotten by the girl-mother; her soul's desire was to continue that

offence by preserving the life of the child. However, it soon grew

clear that the hour of emancipation for that little prisoner of the

flesh was to arrive earlier than her worst misgiving had conjectured.

And when she had discovered this she was plunged into a misery which

transcended that of the child's simple loss. Her baby had not been

baptized.

Tess had drifted into a frame of mind which accepted passively the

consideration that if she should have to burn for what she had done,

burn she must, and there was an end of it. Like all village girls,

she was well grounded in the Holy Scriptures, and had dutifully

studied the histories of Aholah and Aholibah, and knew the inferences

to be drawn therefrom. But when the same question arose with regard

to the baby, it had a very different colour. Her darling was about

to die, and no salvation.

It was nearly bedtime, but she rushed downstairs and asked if she

might send for the parson. The moment happened to be one at which

her father's sense of the antique nobility of his family was highest,

and his sensitiveness to the smudge which Tess had set upon that

nobility most pronounced, for he had just returned from his weekly

booze at Rolliver's Inn. No parson should come inside his door, he

declared, prying into his affairs, just then, when, by her shame, it

had become more necessary than ever to hide them. He locked the door

and put the key in his pocket.

The household went to bed, and, distressed beyond measure, Tess

retired also. She was continually waking as she lay, and in the

middle of the night found that the baby was still worse. It was

obviously dying--quietly and painlessly, but none the less surely.

In her misery she rocked herself upon the bed. The clock struck the

solemn hour of one, that hour when fancy stalks outside reason, and

malignant possibilities stand rock-firm as facts. She thought of

the child consigned to the nethermost corner of hell, as its double

doom for lack of baptism and lack of legitimacy; saw the arch-fiend

tossing it with his three-pronged fork, like the one they used for

heating the oven on baking days; to which picture she added many

other quaint and curious details of torment sometimes taught the

young in this Christian country. The lurid presentment so powerfully

affected her imagination in the silence of the sleeping house that

her nightgown became damp with perspiration, and the bedstead shook

with each throb of her heart.

The infant's breathing grew more difficult, and the mother's mental

tension increased. It was useless to devour the little thing with

kisses; she could stay in bed no longer, and walked feverishly about

the room.

"O merciful God, have pity; have pity upon my poor baby!" she cried.

"Heap as much anger as you want to upon me, and welcome; but pity the

child!"

She leant against the chest of drawers, and murmured incoherent

supplications for a long while, till she suddenly started up.

"Ah! perhaps baby can be saved! Perhaps it will be just the same!"

She spoke so brightly that it seemed as though her face might have

shone in the gloom surrounding her. She lit a candle, and went to

a second and a third bed under the wall, where she awoke her young

sisters and brothers, all of whom occupied the same room. Pulling

out the washing-stand so that she could get behind it, she poured

some water from a jug, and made them kneel around, putting their

hands together with fingers exactly vertical. While the children,

scarcely awake, awe-stricken at her manner, their eyes growing larger

and larger, remained in this position, she took the baby from her

bed--a child's child--so immature as scarce to seem a sufficient

personality to endow its producer with the maternal title. Tess then

stood erect with the infant on her arm beside the basin; the next

sister held the Prayer-Book open before her, as the clerk at church

held it before the parson; and thus the girl set about baptizing her

child.

Her figure looked singularly tall and imposing as she stood in her

long white nightgown, a thick cable of twisted dark hair hanging

straight down her back to her waist. The kindly dimness of the weak

candle abstracted from her form and features the little blemishes

which sunlight might have revealed--the stubble scratches upon her

wrists, and the weariness of her eyes--her high enthusiasm having

a transfiguring effect upon the face which had been her undoing,

showing it as a thing of immaculate beauty, with a touch of dignity

which was almost regal. The little ones kneeling round, their sleepy

eyes blinking and red, awaited her preparations full of a suspended

wonder which their physical heaviness at that hour would not allow to

become active.

The most impressed of them said:

"Be you really going to christen him, Tess?"

The girl-mother replied in a grave affirmative.

"What's his name going to be?"

She had not thought of that, but a name suggested by a phrase in

the book of Genesis came into her head as she proceeded with the

baptismal service, and now she pronounced it:

"SORROW, I baptize thee in the name of the Father, and of the Son,

and of the Holy Ghost."

She sprinkled the water, and there was silence.

"Say 'Amen,' children."

The tiny voices piped in obedient response, "Amen!"

Tess went on:

"We receive this child"--and so forth--"and do sign him with the sign

of the Cross."

Here she dipped her hand into the basin, and fervently drew an

immense cross upon the baby with her forefinger, continuing with

the customary sentences as to his manfully fighting against sin,

the world, and the devil, and being a faithful soldier and servant

unto his life's end. She duly went on with the Lord's Prayer, the

children lisping it after her in a thin gnat-like wail, till, at the

conclusion, raising their voices to clerk's pitch, they again piped

into silence, "Amen!"

Then their sister, with much augmented confidence in the efficacy

of the sacrament, poured forth from the bottom of her heart the

thanksgiving that follows, uttering it boldly and triumphantly in the

stopt-diapason note which her voice acquired when her heart was in

her speech, and which will never be forgotten by those who knew her.

The ecstasy of faith almost apotheosized her; it set upon her face a

glowing irradiation, and brought a red spot into the middle of each

cheek; while the miniature candle-flame inverted in her eye-pupils

shone like a diamond. The children gazed up at her with more and

more reverence, and no longer had a will for questioning. She did

not look like Sissy to them now, but as a being large, towering, and

awful--a divine personage with whom they had nothing in common.

Poor Sorrow's campaign against sin, the world, and the devil was

doomed to be of limited brilliancy--luckily perhaps for himself,

considering his beginnings. In the blue of the morning that fragile

soldier and servant breathed his last, and when the other children

awoke they cried bitterly, and begged Sissy to have another pretty

baby.

The calmness which had possessed Tess since the christening remained

with her in the infant's loss. In the daylight, indeed, she felt her

terrors about his soul to have been somewhat exaggerated; whether

well founded or not, she had no uneasiness now, reasoning that

if Providence would not ratify such an act of approximation

she, for one, did not value the kind of heaven lost by the

irregularity--either for herself or for her child.

So passed away Sorrow the Undesired--that intrusive creature, that

bastard gift of shameless Nature, who respects not the social law;

a waif to whom eternal Time had been a matter of days merely, who

knew not that such things as years and centuries ever were; to whom

the cottage interior was the universe, the week's weather climate,

new-born babyhood human existence, and the instinct to suck human

knowledge.

Tess, who mused on the christening a good deal, wondered if it were

doctrinally sufficient to secure a Christian burial for the child.

Nobody could tell this but the parson of the parish, and he was a

new-comer, and did not know her. She went to his house after dusk,

and stood by the gate, but could not summon courage to go in. The

enterprise would have been abandoned if she had not by accident met

him coming homeward as she turned away. In the gloom she did not

mind speaking freely.

"I should like to ask you something, sir."

He expressed his willingness to listen, and she told the story of the

baby's illness and the extemporized ordinance. "And now, sir," she

added earnestly, "can you tell me this--will it be just the same for

him as if you had baptized him?"

Having the natural feelings of a tradesman at finding that a job he

should have been called in for had been unskilfully botched by his

customers among themselves, he was disposed to say no. Yet the

dignity of the girl, the strange tenderness in her voice, combined

to affect his nobler impulses--or rather those that he had left in

him after ten years of endeavour to graft technical belief on actual

scepticism. The man and the ecclesiastic fought within him, and the

victory fell to the man.

"My dear girl," he said, "it will be just the same."

"Then will you give him a Christian burial?" she asked quickly.

The Vicar felt himself cornered. Hearing of the baby's illness, he

had conscientiously gone to the house after nightfall to perform the

rite, and, unaware that the refusal to admit him had come from Tess's

father and not from Tess, he could not allow the plea of necessity

for its irregular administration.

"Ah--that's another matter," he said.

"Another matter--why?" asked Tess, rather warmly.

"Well--I would willingly do so if only we two were concerned. But I

must not--for certain reasons."

"Just for once, sir!"

"Really I must not."

"O sir!" She seized his hand as she spoke.

He withdrew it, shaking his head.

"Then I don't like you!" she burst out, "and I'll never come to your

church no more!"

"Don't talk so rashly."

"Perhaps it will be just the same to him if you don't? ... Will it

be just the same? Don't for God's sake speak as saint to sinner, but

as you yourself to me myself--poor me!"

How the Vicar reconciled his answer with the strict notions he

supposed himself to hold on these subjects it is beyond a layman's

power to tell, though not to excuse. Somewhat moved, he said in

this case also--

"It will be just the same."

So the baby was carried in a small deal box, under an ancient woman's

shawl, to the churchyard that night, and buried by lantern-light,

at the cost of a shilling and a pint of beer to the sexton, in that

shabby corner of God's allotment where He lets the nettles grow,

and where all unbaptized infants, notorious drunkards, suicides,

and others of the conjecturally damned are laid. In spite of the

untoward surroundings, however, Tess bravely made a little cross of

two laths and a piece of string, and having bound it with flowers,

she stuck it up at the head of the grave one evening when she could

enter the churchyard without being seen, putting at the foot also

a bunch of the same flowers in a little jar of water to keep them

alive. What matter was it that on the outside of the jar the eye of

mere observation noted the words "Keelwell's Marmalade"? The eye of

maternal affection did not see them in its vision of higher things.

XV

"By experience," says Roger Ascham, "we find out a short way by

a long wandering." Not seldom that long wandering unfits us for

further travel, and of what use is our experience to us then? Tess

Durbeyfield's experience was of this incapacitating kind. At last

she had learned what to do; but who would now accept her doing?

If before going to the d'Urbervilles' she had vigorously moved under

the guidance of sundry gnomic texts and phrases known to her and to

the world in general, no doubt she would never have been imposed on.

But it had not been in Tess's power--nor is it in anybody's power--to

feel the whole truth of golden opinions while it is possible to

profit by them. She--and how many more--might have ironically said

to God with Saint Augustine: "Thou hast counselled a better course

than Thou hast permitted."

She remained at her father's house during the winter months, plucking

fowls, or cramming turkeys and geese, or making clothes for her

sisters and brothers out of some finery which d'Urberville had given

her, and she had put by with contempt. Apply to him she would not.

But she would often clasp her hands behind her head and muse when she

was supposed to be working hard.

She philosophically noted dates as they came past in the revolution

of the year; the disastrous night of her undoing at Trantridge with

its dark background of The Chase; also the dates of the baby's birth

and death; also her own birthday; and every other day individualized

by incidents in which she had taken some share. She suddenly thought

one afternoon, when looking in the glass at her fairness, that there

was yet another date, of greater importance to her than those; that

of her own death, when all these charms would have disappeared; a day

which lay sly and unseen among all the other days of the year, giving

no sign or sound when she annually passed over it; but not the less

surely there. When was it? Why did she not feel the chill of each

yearly encounter with such a cold relation? She had Jeremy Taylor's

thought that some time in the future those who had known her would

say: "It is the ----th, the day that poor Tess Durbeyfield died"; and

there would be nothing singular to their minds in the statement. Of

that day, doomed to be her terminus in time through all the ages, she

did not know the place in month, week, season or year.

Almost at a leap Tess thus changed from simple girl to complex woman.

Symbols of reflectiveness passed into her face, and a note of tragedy

at times into her voice. Her eyes grew larger and more eloquent.

She became what would have been called a fine creature; her aspect

was fair and arresting; her soul that of a woman whom the turbulent

experiences of the last year or two had quite failed to demoralize.

But for the world's opinion those experiences would have been simply

a liberal education.

She had held so aloof of late that her trouble, never generally

known, was nearly forgotten in Marlott. But it became evident to her

that she could never be really comfortable again in a place which

had seen the collapse of her family's attempt to "claim kin"--and,

through her, even closer union--with the rich d'Urbervilles. At

least she could not be comfortable there till long years should have

obliterated her keen consciousness of it. Yet even now Tess felt the

pulse of hopeful life still warm within her; she might be happy in

some nook which had no memories. To escape the past and all that

appertained thereto was to annihilate it, and to do that she would

have to get away.

Was once lost always lost really true of chastity? she would ask

herself. She might prove it false if she could veil bygones. The

recuperative power which pervaded organic nature was surely not

denied to maidenhood alone.

She waited a long time without finding opportunity for a new

departure. A particularly fine spring came round, and the stir of

germination was almost audible in the buds; it moved her, as it moved

the wild animals, and made her passionate to go. At last, one day in

early May, a letter reached her from a former friend of her mother's,

to whom she had addressed inquiries long before--a person whom she

had never seen--that a skilful milkmaid was required at a dairy-house

many miles to the southward, and that the dairyman would be glad to

have her for the summer months.

It was not quite so far off as could have been wished; but it was

probably far enough, her radius of movement and repute having been

so small. To persons of limited spheres, miles are as geographical

degrees, parishes as counties, counties as provinces and kingdoms.

On one point she was resolved: there should be no more d'Urberville

air-castles in the dreams and deeds of her new life. She would be

the dairymaid Tess, and nothing more. Her mother knew Tess's feeling

on this point so well, though no words had passed between them on the

subject, that she never alluded to the knightly ancestry now.

Yet such is human inconsistency that one of the interests of the

new place to her was the accidental virtues of its lying near her

forefathers' country (for they were not Blakemore men, though her

mother was Blakemore to the bone). The dairy called Talbothays,

for which she was bound, stood not remotely from some of the former

estates of the d'Urbervilles, near the great family vaults of her

granddames and their powerful husbands. She would be able to look at

them, and think not only that d'Urberville, like Babylon, had fallen,

but that the individual innocence of a humble descendant could lapse

as silently. All the while she wondered if any strange good thing

might come of her being in her ancestral land; and some spirit within

her rose automatically as the sap in the twigs. It was unexpected

youth, surging up anew after its temporary check, and bringing with

it hope, and the invincible instinct towards self-delight.

END OF PHASE THE SECOND

Phase the Third: The Rally

XVI

On a thyme-scented, bird-hatching morning in May, between two and

three years after the return from Trantridge--silent, reconstructive

years for Tess Durbeyfield--she left her home for the second time.

Having packed up her luggage so that it could be sent to her later,

she started in a hired trap for the little town of Stourcastle,

through which it was necessary to pass on her journey, now in a

direction almost opposite to that of her first adventuring. On the

curve of the nearest hill she looked back regretfully at Marlott and

her father's house, although she had been so anxious to get away.

Her kindred dwelling there would probably continue their daily

lives as heretofore, with no great diminution of pleasure in their

consciousness, although she would be far off, and they deprived of

her smile. In a few days the children would engage in their games as

merrily as ever, without the sense of any gap left by her departure.

This leaving of the younger children she had decided to be for the

best; were she to remain they would probably gain less good by her

precepts than harm by her example.

She went through Stourcastle without pausing and onward to a junction

of highways, where she could await a carrier's van that ran to the

south-west; for the railways which engirdled this interior tract of

country had never yet struck across it. While waiting, however,

there came along a farmer in his spring cart, driving approximately

in the direction that she wished to pursue. Though he was a stranger

to her she accepted his offer of a seat beside him, ignoring that

its motive was a mere tribute to her countenance. He was going to

Weatherbury, and by accompanying him thither she could walk the

remainder of the distance instead of travelling in the van by way of

Casterbridge.

Tess did not stop at Weatherbury, after this long drive, further than

to make a slight nondescript meal at noon at a cottage to which the

farmer recommended her. Thence she started on foot, basket in hand,

to reach the wide upland of heath dividing this district from the

low-lying meads of a further valley in which the dairy stood that was

the aim and end of her day's pilgrimage.

Tess had never before visited this part of the country, and yet she

felt akin to the landscape. Not so very far to the left of her she

could discern a dark patch in the scenery, which inquiry confirmed

her in supposing to be trees marking the environs of Kingsbere--in

the church of which parish the bones of her ancestors--her useless

ancestors--lay entombed.

She had no admiration for them now; she almost hated them for the

dance they had led her; not a thing of all that had been theirs did

she retain but the old seal and spoon. "Pooh--I have as much of

mother as father in me!" she said. "All my prettiness comes from

her, and she was only a dairymaid."

The journey over the intervening uplands and lowlands of Egdon,

when she reached them, was a more troublesome walk than she had

anticipated, the distance being actually but a few miles. It was

two hours, owing to sundry wrong turnings, ere she found herself

on a summit commanding the long-sought-for vale, the Valley of the

Great Dairies, the valley in which milk and butter grew to rankness,

and were produced more profusely, if less delicately, than at her

home--the verdant plain so well watered by the river Var or Froom.

It was intrinsically different from the Vale of Little Dairies,

Blackmoor Vale, which, save during her disastrous sojourn at

Trantridge, she had exclusively known till now. The world was drawn

to a larger pattern here. The enclosures numbered fifty acres

instead of ten, the farmsteads were more extended, the groups of

cattle formed tribes hereabout; there only families. These myriads

of cows stretching under her eyes from the far east to the far west

outnumbered any she had ever seen at one glance before. The green

lea was speckled as thickly with them as a canvas by Van Alsloot

or Sallaert with burghers. The ripe hue of the red and dun kine

absorbed the evening sunlight, which the white-coated animals

returned to the eye in rays almost dazzling, even at the distant

elevation on which she stood.

The bird's-eye perspective before her was not so luxuriantly

beautiful, perhaps, as that other one which she knew so well; yet it

was more cheering. It lacked the intensely blue atmosphere of the

rival vale, and its heavy soils and scents; the new air was clear,

bracing, ethereal. The river itself, which nourished the grass

and cows of these renowned dairies, flowed not like the streams in

Blackmoor. Those were slow, silent, often turbid; flowing over

beds of mud into which the incautious wader might sink and vanish

unawares. The Froom waters were clear as the pure River of Life

shown to the Evangelist, rapid as the shadow of a cloud, with

pebbly shallows that prattled to the sky all day long. There the

water-flower was the lily; the crow-foot here.

Either the change in the quality of the air from heavy to light, or

the sense of being amid new scenes where there were no invidious eyes

upon her, sent up her spirits wonderfully. Her hopes mingled with

the sunshine in an ideal photosphere which surrounded her as she

bounded along against the soft south wind. She heard a pleasant

voice in every breeze, and in every bird's note seemed to lurk a

joy.

Her face had latterly changed with changing states of mind,

continually fluctuating between beauty and ordinariness, according as

the thoughts were gay or grave. One day she was pink and flawless;

another pale and tragical. When she was pink she was feeling less

than when pale; her more perfect beauty accorded with her less

elevated mood; her more intense mood with her less perfect beauty.

It was her best face physically that was now set against the south

wind.

The irresistible, universal, automatic tendency to find sweet

pleasure somewhere, which pervades all life, from the meanest to the

highest, had at length mastered Tess. Being even now only a young

woman of twenty, one who mentally and sentimentally had not finished

growing, it was impossible that any event should have left upon her

an impression that was not in time capable of transmutation.

And thus her spirits, and her thankfulness, and her hopes, rose

higher and higher. She tried several ballads, but found them

inadequate; till, recollecting the psalter that her eyes had so often

wandered over of a Sunday morning before she had eaten of the tree

of knowledge, she chanted: "O ye Sun and Moon ... O ye Stars ... ye

Green Things upon the Earth ... ye Fowls of the Air ... Beasts and

Cattle ... Children of Men ... bless ye the Lord, praise Him and

magnify Him for ever!"

She suddenly stopped and murmured: "But perhaps I don't quite know

the Lord as yet."

And probably the half-unconscious rhapsody was a Fetishistic

utterance in a Monotheistic setting; women whose chief companions

are the forms and forces of outdoor Nature retain in their souls far

more of the Pagan fantasy of their remote forefathers than of the

systematized religion taught their race at later date. However, Tess

found at least approximate expression for her feelings in the old

_Benedicite_ that she had lisped from infancy; and it was enough.

Such high contentment with such a slight initial performance as that

of having started towards a means of independent living was a part of

the Durbeyfield temperament. Tess really wished to walk uprightly,

while her father did nothing of the kind; but she resembled him in

being content with immediate and small achievements, and in having no

mind for laborious effort towards such petty social advancement as

could alone be effected by a family so heavily handicapped as the

once powerful d'Urbervilles were now.

There was, it might be said, the energy of her mother's unexpended

family, as well as the natural energy of Tess's years, rekindled

after the experience which had so overwhelmed her for the time. Let

the truth be told--women do as a rule live through such humiliations,

and regain their spirits, and again look about them with an

interested eye. While there's life there's hope is a conviction not

so entirely unknown to the "betrayed" as some amiable theorists would

have us believe.

Tess Durbeyfield, then, in good heart, and full of zest for life,

descended the Egdon slopes lower and lower towards the dairy of her

pilgrimage.

The marked difference, in the final particular, between the rival

vales now showed itself. The secret of Blackmoor was best discovered

from the heights around; to read aright the valley before her it was

necessary to descend into its midst. When Tess had accomplished this

feat she found herself to be standing on a carpeted level, which

stretched to the east and west as far as the eye could reach.

The river had stolen from the higher tracts and brought in particles

to the vale all this horizontal land; and now, exhausted, aged, and

attenuated, lay serpentining along through the midst of its former

spoils.

Not quite sure of her direction, Tess stood still upon the hemmed

expanse of verdant flatness, like a fly on a billiard-table of

indefinite length, and of no more consequence to the surroundings

than that fly. The sole effect of her presence upon the placid

valley so far had been to excite the mind of a solitary heron, which,

after descending to the ground not far from her path, stood with neck

erect, looking at her.

Suddenly there arose from all parts of the lowland a prolonged and

repeated call--"Waow! waow! waow!"

From the furthest east to the furthest west the cries spread as if by

contagion, accompanied in some cases by the barking of a dog. It was

not the expression of the valley's consciousness that beautiful Tess

had arrived, but the ordinary announcement of milking-time--half-past

four o'clock, when the dairymen set about getting in the cows.

The red and white herd nearest at hand, which had been phlegmatically

waiting for the call, now trooped towards the steading in the

background, their great bags of milk swinging under them as they

walked. Tess followed slowly in their rear, and entered the barton

by the open gate through which they had entered before her. Long

thatched sheds stretched round the enclosure, their slopes encrusted

with vivid green moss, and their eaves supported by wooden posts

rubbed to a glossy smoothness by the flanks of infinite cows

and calves of bygone years, now passed to an oblivion almost

inconceivable in its profundity. Between the post were ranged

the milchers, each exhibiting herself at the present moment to a

whimsical eye in the rear as a circle on two stalks, down the centre

of which a switch moved pendulum-wise; while the sun, lowering itself

behind this patient row, threw their shadows accurately inwards upon

the wall. Thus it threw shadows of these obscure and homely figures

every evening with as much care over each contour as if it had been

the profile of a court beauty on a palace wall; copied them as

diligently as it had copied Olympian shapes on marble _faades_ long

ago, or the outline of Alexander, Caesar, and the Pharaohs.

They were the less restful cows that were stalled. Those that would

stand still of their own will were milked in the middle of the yard,

where many of such better behaved ones stood waiting now--all prime

milchers, such as were seldom seen out of this valley, and not always

within it; nourished by the succulent feed which the water-meads

supplied at this prime season of the year. Those of them that were

spotted with white reflected the sunshine in dazzling brilliancy,

and the polished brass knobs of their horns glittered with something

of military display. Their large-veined udders hung ponderous as

sandbags, the teats sticking out like the legs of a gipsy's crock;

and as each animal lingered for her turn to arrive the milk oozed

forth and fell in drops to the ground.

XVII

The dairymaids and men had flocked down from their cottages and out

of the dairy-house with the arrival of the cows from the meads; the

maids walking in pattens, not on account of the weather, but to keep

their shoes above the mulch of the barton. Each girl sat down on

her three-legged stool, her face sideways, her right cheek resting

against the cow, and looked musingly along the animal's flank at Tess

as she approached. The male milkers, with hat-brims turned down,

resting flat on their foreheads and gazing on the ground, did not

observe her.

One of these was a sturdy middle-aged man--whose long white "pinner"

was somewhat finer and cleaner than the wraps of the others, and

whose jacket underneath had a presentable marketing aspect--the

master-dairyman, of whom she was in quest, his double character as

a working milker and butter maker here during six days, and on the

seventh as a man in shining broad-cloth in his family pew at church,

being so marked as to have inspired a rhyme:

Dairyman Dick

All the week:--

On Sundays Mister Richard Crick.

Seeing Tess standing at gaze he went across to her.

The majority of dairymen have a cross manner at milking time, but it

happened that Mr Crick was glad to get a new hand--for the days were

busy ones now--and he received her warmly; inquiring for her mother

and the rest of the family--(though this as a matter of form merely,

for in reality he had not been aware of Mrs Durbeyfield's existence

till apprised of the fact by a brief business-letter about Tess).

"Oh--ay, as a lad I knowed your part o' the country very well," he

said terminatively. "Though I've never been there since. And a aged

woman of ninety that use to live nigh here, but is dead and gone long

ago, told me that a family of some such name as yours in Blackmoor

Vale came originally from these parts, and that 'twere a old ancient

race that had all but perished off the earth--though the new

generations didn't know it. But, Lord, I took no notice of the old

woman's ramblings, not I."

"Oh no--it is nothing," said Tess.

Then the talk was of business only.

"You can milk 'em clean, my maidy? I don't want my cows going azew at

this time o' year."

She reassured him on that point, and he surveyed her up and down.

She had been staying indoors a good deal, and her complexion had

grown delicate.

"Quite sure you can stand it? 'Tis comfortable enough here for rough

folk; but we don't live in a cowcumber frame."

She declared that she could stand it, and her zest and willingness

seemed to win him over.

"Well, I suppose you'll want a dish o' tay, or victuals of some sort,

hey? Not yet? Well, do as ye like about it. But faith, if 'twas I,

I should be as dry as a kex wi' travelling so far."

"I'll begin milking now, to get my hand in," said Tess.

She drank a little milk as temporary refreshment--to the

surprise--indeed, slight contempt--of Dairyman Crick, to whose mind

it had apparently never occurred that milk was good as a beverage.

"Oh, if ye can swaller that, be it so," he said indifferently, while

holding up the pail that she sipped from. "'Tis what I hain't

touched for years--not I. Rot the stuff; it would lie in my innerds

like lead. You can try your hand upon she," he pursued, nodding to

the nearest cow. "Not but what she do milk rather hard. We've hard

ones and we've easy ones, like other folks. However, you'll find out

that soon enough."

When Tess had changed her bonnet for a hood, and was really on her

stool under the cow, and the milk was squirting from her fists

into the pail, she appeared to feel that she really had laid a new

foundation for her future. The conviction bred serenity, her pulse

slowed, and she was able to look about her.

The milkers formed quite a little battalion of men and maids, the

men operating on the hard-teated animals, the maids on the kindlier

natures. It was a large dairy. There were nearly a hundred

milchers under Crick's management, all told; and of the herd the

master-dairyman milked six or eight with his own hands, unless away

from home. These were the cows that milked hardest of all; for his

journey-milkmen being more or less casually hired, he would not

entrust this half-dozen to their treatment, lest, from indifference,

they should not milk them fully; nor to the maids, lest they should

fail in the same way for lack of finger-grip; with the result that in

course of time the cows would "go azew"--that is, dry up. It was not

the loss for the moment that made slack milking so serious, but that

with the decline of demand there came decline, and ultimately

cessation, of supply.

After Tess had settled down to her cow there was for a time no talk

in the barton, and not a sound interfered with the purr of the

milk-jets into the numerous pails, except a momentary exclamation

to one or other of the beasts requesting her to turn round or stand

still. The only movements were those of the milkers' hands up and

down, and the swing of the cows' tails. Thus they all worked on,

encompassed by the vast flat mead which extended to either slope

of the valley--a level landscape compounded of old landscapes long

forgotten, and, no doubt, differing in character very greatly from

the landscape they composed now.

"To my thinking," said the dairyman, rising suddenly from a cow

he had just finished off, snatching up his three-legged stool in

one hand and the pail in the other, and moving on to the next

hard-yielder in his vicinity, "to my thinking, the cows don't gie

down their milk to-day as usual. Upon my life, if Winker do begin

keeping back like this, she'll not be worth going under by

midsummer."

"'Tis because there's a new hand come among us," said Jonathan Kail.

"I've noticed such things afore."

"To be sure. It may be so. I didn't think o't."

"I've been told that it goes up into their horns at such times," said

a dairymaid.

"Well, as to going up into their horns," replied Dairyman Crick

dubiously, as though even witchcraft might be limited by anatomical

possibilities, "I couldn't say; I certainly could not. But as nott

cows will keep it back as well as the horned ones, I don't quite

agree to it. Do ye know that riddle about the nott cows, Jonathan?

Why do nott cows give less milk in a year than horned?"

"I don't!" interposed the milkmaid, "Why do they?"

"Because there bain't so many of 'em," said the dairyman.

"Howsomever, these gam'sters do certainly keep back their milk

to-day. Folks, we must lift up a stave or two--that's the only cure

for't."

Songs were often resorted to in dairies hereabout as an enticement

to the cows when they showed signs of withholding their usual yield;

and the band of milkers at this request burst into melody--in purely

business-like tones, it is true, and with no great spontaneity; the

result, according to their own belief, being a decided improvement

during the song's continuance. When they had gone through fourteen

or fifteen verses of a cheerful ballad about a murderer who was

afraid to go to bed in the dark because he saw certain brimstone

flames around him, one of the male milkers said--

"I wish singing on the stoop didn't use up so much of a man's wind!

You should get your harp, sir; not but what a fiddle is best."

Tess, who had given ear to this, thought the words were addressed to

the dairyman, but she was wrong. A reply, in the shape of "Why?"

came as it were out of the belly of a dun cow in the stalls; it had

been spoken by a milker behind the animal, whom she had not hitherto

perceived.

"Oh yes; there's nothing like a fiddle," said the dairyman. "Though

I do think that bulls are more moved by a tune than cows--at least

that's my experience. Once there was an old aged man over at

Mellstock--William Dewy by name--one of the family that used to do

a good deal of business as tranters over there--Jonathan, do ye

mind?--I knowed the man by sight as well as I know my own brother, in

a manner of speaking. Well, this man was a coming home along from a

wedding, where he had been playing his fiddle, one fine moonlight

night, and for shortness' sake he took a cut across Forty-acres, a

field lying that way, where a bull was out to grass. The bull seed

William, and took after him, horns aground, begad; and though William

runned his best, and hadn't MUCH drink in him (considering 'twas a

wedding, and the folks well off), he found he'd never reach the fence

and get over in time to save himself. Well, as a last thought, he

pulled out his fiddle as he runned, and struck up a jig, turning to

the bull, and backing towards the corner. The bull softened down,

and stood still, looking hard at William Dewy, who fiddled on and on;

till a sort of a smile stole over the bull's face. But no sooner

did William stop his playing and turn to get over hedge than the

bull would stop his smiling and lower his horns towards the seat of

William's breeches. Well, William had to turn about and play on,

willy-nilly; and 'twas only three o'clock in the world, and 'a knowed

that nobody would come that way for hours, and he so leery and tired

that 'a didn't know what to do. When he had scraped till about four

o'clock he felt that he verily would have to give over soon, and he

said to himself, 'There's only this last tune between me and eternal

welfare! Heaven save me, or I'm a done man.' Well, then he called to

mind how he'd seen the cattle kneel o' Christmas Eves in the dead o'

night. It was not Christmas Eve then, but it came into his head to

play a trick upon the bull. So he broke into the 'Tivity Hymm, just

as at Christmas carol-singing; when, lo and behold, down went the

bull on his bended knees, in his ignorance, just as if 'twere the

true 'Tivity night and hour. As soon as his horned friend were down,

William turned, clinked off like a long-dog, and jumped safe over

hedge, before the praying bull had got on his feet again to take

after him. William used to say that he'd seen a man look a fool

a good many times, but never such a fool as that bull looked when

he found his pious feelings had been played upon, and 'twas not

Christmas Eve. ... Yes, William Dewy, that was the man's name; and

I can tell you to a foot where's he a-lying in Mellstock Churchyard

at this very moment--just between the second yew-tree and the north

aisle."

"It's a curious story; it carries us back to medieval times, when

faith was a living thing!"

The remark, singular for a dairy-yard, was murmured by the voice

behind the dun cow; but as nobody understood the reference, no notice

was taken, except that the narrator seemed to think it might imply

scepticism as to his tale.

"Well, 'tis quite true, sir, whether or no. I knowed the man well."

"Oh yes; I have no doubt of it," said the person behind the dun cow.

Tess's attention was thus attracted to the dairyman's interlocutor,

of whom she could see but the merest patch, owing to his burying his

head so persistently in the flank of the milcher. She could not

understand why he should be addressed as "sir" even by the dairyman

himself. But no explanation was discernible; he remained under the

cow long enough to have milked three, uttering a private ejaculation

now and then, as if he could not get on.

"Take it gentle, sir; take it gentle," said the dairyman. "'Tis

knack, not strength, that does it."

"So I find," said the other, standing up at last and stretching his

arms. "I think I have finished her, however, though she made my

fingers ache."

Tess could then see him at full length. He wore the ordinary white

pinner and leather leggings of a dairy-farmer when milking, and his

boots were clogged with the mulch of the yard; but this was all his

local livery. Beneath it was something educated, reserved, subtle,

sad, differing.

But the details of his aspect were temporarily thrust aside by

the discovery that he was one whom she had seen before. Such

vicissitudes had Tess passed through since that time that for a

moment she could not remember where she had met him; and then it

flashed upon her that he was the pedestrian who had joined in the

club-dance at Marlott--the passing stranger who had come she knew

not whence, had danced with others but not with her, and slightingly

left her, and gone on his way with his friends.

The flood of memories brought back by this revival of an incident

anterior to her troubles produced a momentary dismay lest,

recognizing her also, he should by some means discover her story.

But it passed away when she found no sign of remembrance in him. She

saw by degrees that since their first and only encounter his mobile

face had grown more thoughtful, and had acquired a young man's

shapely moustache and beard--the latter of the palest straw colour

where it began upon his cheeks, and deepening to a warm brown farther

from its root. Under his linen milking-pinner he wore a dark

velveteen jacket, cord breeches and gaiters, and a starched white

shirt. Without the milking-gear nobody could have guessed what

he was. He might with equal probability have been an eccentric

landowner or a gentlemanly ploughman. That he was but a novice at

dairy work she had realized in a moment, from the time he had spent

upon the milking of one cow.

Meanwhile many of the milkmaids had said to one another of the

newcomer, "How pretty she is!" with something of real generosity and

admiration, though with a half hope that the auditors would qualify

the assertion--which, strictly speaking, they might have done,

prettiness being an inexact definition of what struck the eye in

Tess. When the milking was finished for the evening they straggled

indoors, where Mrs Crick, the dairyman's wife--who was too

respectable to go out milking herself, and wore a hot stuff gown in

warm weather because the dairymaids wore prints--was giving an eye

to the leads and things.

Only two or three of the maids, Tess learnt, slept in the dairy-house

besides herself, most of the helpers going to their homes. She saw

nothing at supper-time of the superior milker who had commented on

the story, and asked no questions about him, the remainder of the

evening being occupied in arranging her place in the bed-chamber.

It was a large room over the milk-house, some thirty feet long; the

sleeping-cots of the other three indoor milkmaids being in the same

apartment. They were blooming young women, and, except one, rather

older than herself. By bedtime Tess was thoroughly tired, and fell

asleep immediately.

But one of the girls, who occupied an adjoining bed, was more wakeful

than Tess, and would insist upon relating to the latter various

particulars of the homestead into which she had just entered. The

girl's whispered words mingled with the shades, and, to Tess's drowsy

mind, they seemed to be generated by the darkness in which they

floated.

"Mr Angel Clare--he that is learning milking, and that plays

the harp--never says much to us. He is a pa'son's son, and is

too much taken up wi' his own thoughts to notice girls. He is

the dairyman's pupil--learning farming in all its branches. He

has learnt sheep-farming at another place, and he's now mastering

dairy-work.... Yes, he is quite the gentleman-born. His father is

the Reverent Mr Clare at Emminster--a good many miles from here."

"Oh--I have heard of him," said her companion, now awake. "A very

earnest clergyman, is he not?"

"Yes--that he is--the earnestest man in all Wessex, they say--the

last of the old Low Church sort, they tell me--for all about here be

what they call High. All his sons, except our Mr Clare, be made

pa'sons too."

Tess had not at this hour the curiosity to ask why the present Mr

Clare was not made a parson like his brethren, and gradually fell

asleep again, the words of her informant coming to her along with the

smell of the cheeses in the adjoining cheeseloft, and the measured

dripping of the whey from the wrings downstairs.

XVIII

Angel Clare rises out of the past not altogether as a distinct

figure, but as an appreciative voice, a long regard of fixed,

abstracted eyes, and a mobility of mouth somewhat too small and

delicately lined for a man's, though with an unexpectedly firm close

of the lower lip now and then; enough to do away with any inference

of indecision. Nevertheless, something nebulous, preoccupied, vague,

in his bearing and regard, marked him as one who probably had no very

definite aim or concern about his material future. Yet as a lad

people had said of him that he was one who might do anything if he

tried.

He was the youngest son of his father, a poor parson at the other end

of the county, and had arrived at Talbothays Dairy as a six months'

pupil, after going the round of some other farms, his object being

to acquire a practical skill in the various processes of farming,

with a view either to the Colonies or the tenure of a home-farm, as

circumstances might decide.

His entry into the ranks of the agriculturists and breeders was a

step in the young man's career which had been anticipated neither

by himself nor by others.

Mr Clare the elder, whose first wife had died and left him a

daughter, married a second late in life. This lady had somewhat

unexpectedly brought him three sons, so that between Angel, the

youngest, and his father the Vicar there seemed to be almost a

missing generation. Of these boys the aforesaid Angel, the child of

his old age, was the only son who had not taken a University degree,

though he was the single one of them whose early promise might have

done full justice to an academical training.

Some two or three years before Angel's appearance at the Marlott

dance, on a day when he had left school and was pursuing his studies

at home, a parcel came to the Vicarage from the local bookseller's,

directed to the Reverend James Clare. The Vicar having opened it and

found it to contain a book, read a few pages; whereupon he jumped up

from his seat and went straight to the shop with the book under his

arm.

"Why has this been sent to my house?" he asked peremptorily, holding

up the volume.

"It was ordered, sir."

"Not by me, or any one belonging to me, I am happy to say."

The shopkeeper looked into his order-book.

"Oh, it has been misdirected, sir," he said. "It was ordered by Mr

Angel Clare, and should have been sent to him."

Mr Clare winced as if he had been struck. He went home pale and

dejected, and called Angel into his study.

"Look into this book, my boy," he said. "What do you know about it?"

"I ordered it," said Angel simply.

"What for?"

"To read."

"How can you think of reading it?"

"How can I? Why--it is a system of philosophy. There is no more

moral, or even religious, work published."

"Yes--moral enough; I don't deny that. But religious!--and for YOU,

who intend to be a minister of the Gospel!"

"Since you have alluded to the matter, father," said the son, with

anxious thought upon his face, "I should like to say, once for

all, that I should prefer not to take Orders. I fear I could not

conscientiously do so. I love the Church as one loves a parent.

I shall always have the warmest affection for her. There is no

institution for whose history I have a deeper admiration; but I

cannot honestly be ordained her minister, as my brothers are, while

she refuses to liberate her mind from an untenable redemptive

theolatry."

It had never occurred to the straightforward and simple-minded Vicar

that one of his own flesh and blood could come to this! He was

stultified, shocked, paralysed. And if Angel were not going to

enter the Church, what was the use of sending him to Cambridge? The

University as a step to anything but ordination seemed, to this man

of fixed ideas, a preface without a volume. He was a man not merely

religious, but devout; a firm believer--not as the phrase is now

elusively construed by theological thimble-riggers in the Church and

out of it, but in the old and ardent sense of the Evangelical school:

one who could

Indeed opine

That the Eternal and Divine

Did, eighteen centuries ago

In very truth...

Angel's father tried argument, persuasion, entreaty.

"No, father; I cannot underwrite Article Four (leave alone the rest),

taking it 'in the literal and grammatical sense' as required by the

Declaration; and, therefore, I can't be a parson in the present state

of affairs," said Angel. "My whole instinct in matters of religion

is towards reconstruction; to quote your favorite Epistle to the

Hebrews, 'the removing of those things that are shaken, as of things

that are made, that those things which cannot be shaken may remain.'"

His father grieved so deeply that it made Angel quite ill to see him.

"What is the good of your mother and me economizing and stinting

ourselves to give you a University education, if it is not to be used

for the honour and glory of God?" his father repeated.

"Why, that it may be used for the honour and glory of man, father."

Perhaps if Angel had persevered he might have gone to Cambridge like

his brothers. But the Vicar's view of that seat of learning as a

stepping-stone to Orders alone was quite a family tradition; and so

rooted was the idea in his mind that perseverance began to appear to

the sensitive son akin to an intent to misappropriate a trust, and

wrong the pious heads of the household, who had been and were, as his

father had hinted, compelled to exercise much thrift to carry out

this uniform plan of education for the three young men.

"I will do without Cambridge," said Angel at last. "I feel that I

have no right to go there in the circumstances."

The effects of this decisive debate were not long in showing

themselves. He spent years and years in desultory studies,

undertakings, and meditations; he began to evince considerable

indifference to social forms and observances. The material

distinctions of rank and wealth he increasingly despised. Even the

"good old family" (to use a favourite phrase of a late local worthy)

had no aroma for him unless there were good new resolutions in its

representatives. As a balance to these austerities, when he went to

live in London to see what the world was like, and with a view to

practising a profession or business there, he was carried off his

head, and nearly entrapped by a woman much older than himself, though

luckily he escaped not greatly the worse for the experience.

Early association with country solitudes had bred in him an

unconquerable, and almost unreasonable, aversion to modern town life,

and shut him out from such success as he might have aspired to by

following a mundane calling in the impracticability of the spiritual

one. But something had to be done; he had wasted many valuable

years; and having an acquaintance who was starting on a thriving life

as a Colonial farmer, it occurred to Angel that this might be a lead

in the right direction. Farming, either in the Colonies, America, or

at home--farming, at any rate, after becoming well qualified for the

business by a careful apprenticeship--that was a vocation which would

probably afford an independence without the sacrifice of what he

valued even more than a competency--intellectual liberty.

So we find Angel Clare at six-and-twenty here at Talbothays as a

student of kine, and, as there were no houses near at hand in which

he could get a comfortable lodging, a boarder at the dairyman's.

His room was an immense attic which ran the whole length of the

dairy-house. It could only be reached by a ladder from the

cheese-loft, and had been closed up for a long time till he arrived

and selected it as his retreat. Here Clare had plenty of space, and

could often be heard by the dairy-folk pacing up and down when the

household had gone to rest. A portion was divided off at one end by

a curtain, behind which was his bed, the outer part being furnished

as a homely sitting-room.

At first he lived up above entirely, reading a good deal, and

strumming upon an old harp which he had bought at a sale, saying when

in a bitter humour that he might have to get his living by it in the

streets some day. But he soon preferred to read human nature by

taking his meals downstairs in the general dining-kitchen, with the

dairyman and his wife, and the maids and men, who all together formed

a lively assembly; for though but few milking hands slept in the

house, several joined the family at meals. The longer Clare resided

here the less objection had he to his company, and the more did he

like to share quarters with them in common.

Much to his surprise he took, indeed, a real delight in their

companionship. The conventional farm-folk of his imagination--

personified in the newspaper-press by the pitiable dummy known as

Hodge--were obliterated after a few days' residence. At close

quarters no Hodge was to be seen. At first, it is true, when Clare's

intelligence was fresh from a contrasting society, these friends with

whom he now hobnobbed seemed a little strange. Sitting down as a

level member of the dairyman's household seemed at the outset an

undignified proceeding. The ideas, the modes, the surroundings,

appeared retrogressive and unmeaning. But with living on there,

day after day, the acute sojourner became conscious of a new aspect

in the spectacle. Without any objective change whatever, variety

had taken the place of monotonousness. His host and his host's

household, his men and his maids, as they became intimately known to

Clare, began to differentiate themselves as in a chemical process.

The thought of Pascal's was brought home to him: "_A mesure qu'on a

plus d'esprit, on trouve qu'il y a plus d'hommes originaux. Les

gens du commun ne trouvent pas de diffrence entre les hommes._"

The typical and unvarying Hodge ceased to exist. He had been

disintegrated into a number of varied fellow-creatures--beings of

many minds, beings infinite in difference; some happy, many serene, a

few depressed, one here and there bright even to genius, some stupid,

others wanton, others austere; some mutely Miltonic, some potentially

Cromwellian--into men who had private views of each other, as he had

of his friends; who could applaud or condemn each other, amuse or

sadden themselves by the contemplation of each other's foibles or

vices; men every one of whom walked in his own individual way the

road to dusty death.

Unexpectedly he began to like the outdoor life for its own sake,

and for what it brought, apart from its bearing on his own proposed

career. Considering his position he became wonderfully free from the

chronic melancholy which is taking hold of the civilized races with

the decline of belief in a beneficent Power. For the first time of

late years he could read as his musings inclined him, without any eye

to cramming for a profession, since the few farming handbooks which

he deemed it desirable to master occupied him but little time.

He grew away from old associations, and saw something new in life and

humanity. Secondarily, he made close acquaintance with phenomena

which he had before known but darkly--the seasons in their moods,

morning and evening, night and noon, winds in their different

tempers, trees, waters and mists, shades and silences, and the voices

of inanimate things.

The early mornings were still sufficiently cool to render a fire

acceptable in the large room wherein they breakfasted; and, by

Mrs Crick's orders, who held that he was too genteel to mess at

their table, it was Angel Clare's custom to sit in the yawning

chimney-corner during the meal, his cup-and-saucer and plate being

placed on a hinged flap at his elbow. The light from the long, wide,

mullioned window opposite shone in upon his nook, and, assisted by a

secondary light of cold blue quality which shone down the chimney,

enabled him to read there easily whenever disposed to do so. Between

Clare and the window was the table at which his companions sat, their

munching profiles rising sharp against the panes; while to the side

was the milk-house door, through which were visible the rectangular

leads in rows, full to the brim with the morning's milk. At the

further end the great churn could be seen revolving, and its

slip-slopping heard--the moving power being discernible through the

window in the form of a spiritless horse walking in a circle and

driven by a boy.

For several days after Tess's arrival Clare, sitting abstractedly

reading from some book, periodical, or piece of music just come by

post, hardly noticed that she was present at table. She talked so

little, and the other maids talked so much, that the babble did not

strike him as possessing a new note, and he was ever in the habit

of neglecting the particulars of an outward scene for the general

impression. One day, however, when he had been conning one of his

music-scores, and by force of imagination was hearing the tune in

his head, he lapsed into listlessness, and the music-sheet rolled

to the hearth. He looked at the fire of logs, with its one flame

pirouetting on the top in a dying dance after the breakfast-cooking

and boiling, and it seemed to jig to his inward tune; also at the two

chimney crooks dangling down from the cotterel, or cross-bar, plumed

with soot, which quivered to the same melody; also at the half-empty

kettle whining an accompaniment. The conversation at the table mixed

in with his phantasmal orchestra till he thought: "What a fluty voice

one of those milkmaids has! I suppose it is the new one."

Clare looked round upon her, seated with the others.

She was not looking towards him. Indeed, owing to his long silence,

his presence in the room was almost forgotten.

"I don't know about ghosts," she was saying; "but I do know that our

souls can be made to go outside our bodies when we are alive."

The dairyman turned to her with his mouth full, his eyes charged

with serious inquiry, and his great knife and fork (breakfasts were

breakfasts here) planted erect on the table, like the beginning of

a gallows.

"What--really now? And is it so, maidy?" he said.

"A very easy way to feel 'em go," continued Tess, "is to lie on the

grass at night and look straight up at some big bright star; and, by

fixing your mind upon it, you will soon find that you are hundreds

and hundreds o' miles away from your body, which you don't seem to

want at all."

The dairyman removed his hard gaze from Tess, and fixed it on his

wife.

"Now that's a rum thing, Christianer--hey? To think o' the miles

I've vamped o' starlight nights these last thirty year, courting, or

trading, or for doctor, or for nurse, and yet never had the least

notion o' that till now, or feeled my soul rise so much as an inch

above my shirt-collar."

The general attention being drawn to her, including that of the

dairyman's pupil, Tess flushed, and remarking evasively that it was

only a fancy, resumed her breakfast.

Clare continued to observe her. She soon finished her eating, and

having a consciousness that Clare was regarding her, began to trace

imaginary patterns on the tablecloth with her forefinger with the

constraint of a domestic animal that perceives itself to be watched.

"What a fresh and virginal daughter of Nature that milkmaid is!" he

said to himself.

And then he seemed to discern in her something that was familiar,

something which carried him back into a joyous and unforeseeing past,

before the necessity of taking thought had made the heavens gray. He

concluded that he had beheld her before; where he could not tell. A

casual encounter during some country ramble it certainly had been,

and he was not greatly curious about it. But the circumstance was

sufficient to lead him to select Tess in preference to the other

pretty milkmaids when he wished to contemplate contiguous womankind.

XIX

In general the cows were milked as they presented themselves, without

fancy or choice. But certain cows will show a fondness for a

particular pair of hands, sometimes carrying this predilection so far

as to refuse to stand at all except to their favourite, the pail of a

stranger being unceremoniously kicked over.

It was Dairyman Crick's rule to insist on breaking down these

partialities and aversions by constant interchange, since otherwise,

in the event of a milkman or maid going away from the dairy, he was

placed in a difficulty. The maids' private aims, however, were the

reverse of the dairyman's rule, the daily selection by each damsel of

the eight or ten cows to which she had grown accustomed rendering the

operation on their willing udders surprisingly easy and effortless.

Tess, like her compeers, soon discovered which of the cows had a

preference for her style of manipulation, and her fingers having

become delicate from the long domiciliary imprisonments to which

she had subjected herself at intervals during the last two or three

years, she would have been glad to meet the milchers' views in

this respect. Out of the whole ninety-five there were eight in

particular--Dumpling, Fancy, Lofty, Mist, Old Pretty, Young Pretty,

Tidy, and Loud--who, though the teats of one or two were as hard as

carrots, gave down to her with a readiness that made her work on them

a mere touch of the fingers. Knowing, however, the dairyman's wish,

she endeavoured conscientiously to take the animals just as they

came, expecting the very hard yielders which she could not yet

manage.

But she soon found a curious correspondence between the ostensibly

chance position of the cows and her wishes in this matter, till she

felt that their order could not be the result of accident. The

dairyman's pupil had lent a hand in getting the cows together of

late, and at the fifth or sixth time she turned her eyes, as she

rested against the cow, full of sly inquiry upon him.

"Mr Clare, you have ranged the cows!" she said, blushing; and in

making the accusation, symptoms of a smile gently lifted her upper

lip in spite of her, so as to show the tips of her teeth, the lower

lip remaining severely still.

"Well, it makes no difference," said he. "You will always be here to

milk them."

"Do you think so? I HOPE I shall! But I don't KNOW."

She was angry with herself afterwards, thinking that he, unaware of

her grave reasons for liking this seclusion, might have mistaken her

meaning. She had spoken so earnestly to him, as if his presence

were somehow a factor in her wish. Her misgiving was such that at

dusk, when the milking was over, she walked in the garden alone, to

continue her regrets that she had disclosed to him her discovery of

his considerateness.

It was a typical summer evening in June, the atmosphere being in

such delicate equilibrium and so transmissive that inanimate objects

seemed endowed with two or three senses, if not five. There was no

distinction between the near and the far, and an auditor felt close

to everything within the horizon. The soundlessness impressed her as

a positive entity rather than as the mere negation of noise. It was

broken by the strumming of strings.

Tess had heard those notes in the attic above her head. Dim,

flattened, constrained by their confinement, they had never appealed

to her as now, when they wandered in the still air with a stark

quality like that of nudity. To speak absolutely, both instrument

and execution were poor; but the relative is all, and as she listened

Tess, like a fascinated bird, could not leave the spot. Far from

leaving she drew up towards the performer, keeping behind the hedge

that he might not guess her presence.

The outskirt of the garden in which Tess found herself had been

left uncultivated for some years, and was now damp and rank with

juicy grass which sent up mists of pollen at a touch; and with tall

blooming weeds emitting offensive smells--weeds whose red and yellow

and purple hues formed a polychrome as dazzling as that of cultivated

flowers. She went stealthily as a cat through this profusion of

growth, gathering cuckoo-spittle on her skirts, cracking snails that

were underfoot, staining her hands with thistle-milk and slug-slime,

and rubbing off upon her naked arms sticky blights which, though

snow-white on the apple-tree trunks, made madder stains on her skin;

thus she drew quite near to Clare, still unobserved of him.

Tess was conscious of neither time nor space. The exaltation which

she had described as being producible at will by gazing at a star

came now without any determination of hers; she undulated upon the

thin notes of the second-hand harp, and their harmonies passed like

breezes through her, bringing tears into her eyes. The floating

pollen seemed to be his notes made visible, and the dampness of

the garden the weeping of the garden's sensibility. Though near

nightfall, the rank-smelling weed-flowers glowed as if they would not

close for intentness, and the waves of colour mixed with the waves of

sound.

The light which still shone was derived mainly from a large hole in

the western bank of cloud; it was like a piece of day left behind

by accident, dusk having closed in elsewhere. He concluded his

plaintive melody, a very simple performance, demanding no great

skill; and she waited, thinking another might be begun. But, tired

of playing, he had desultorily come round the fence, and was rambling

up behind her. Tess, her cheeks on fire, moved away furtively, as if

hardly moving at all.

Angel, however, saw her light summer gown, and he spoke; his low

tones reaching her, though he was some distance off.

"What makes you draw off in that way, Tess?" said he. "Are you

afraid?"

"Oh no, sir--not of outdoor things; especially just now when the

apple-blooth is falling, and everything is so green."

"But you have your indoor fears--eh?"

"Well--yes, sir."

"What of?"

"I couldn't quite say."

"The milk turning sour?"

"No."

"Life in general?"

"Yes, sir."

"Ah--so have I, very often. This hobble of being alive is rather

serious, don't you think so?"

"It is--now you put it that way."

"All the same, I shouldn't have expected a young girl like you to see

it so just yet. How is it you do?"

She maintained a hesitating silence.

"Come, Tess, tell me in confidence."

She thought that he meant what were the aspects of things to her, and

replied shyly--

"The trees have inquisitive eyes, haven't they?--that is, seem as

if they had. And the river says,--'Why do ye trouble me with your

looks?' And you seem to see numbers of to-morrows just all in a

line, the first of them the biggest and clearest, the others getting

smaller and smaller as they stand farther away; but they all seem

very fierce and cruel and as if they said, 'I'm coming! Beware of

me! Beware of me!' ... But YOU, sir, can raise up dreams with your

music, and drive all such horrid fancies away!"

He was surprised to find this young woman--who though but a milkmaid

had just that touch of rarity about her which might make her the

envied of her housemates--shaping such sad imaginings. She was

expressing in her own native phrases--assisted a little by her Sixth

Standard training--feelings which might almost have been called those

of the age--the ache of modernism. The perception arrested him less

when he reflected that what are called advanced ideas are really in

great part but the latest fashion in definition--a more accurate

expression, by words in _logy_ and _ism_, of sensations which men and

women have vaguely grasped for centuries.

Still, it was strange that they should have come to her while yet so

young; more than strange; it was impressive, interesting, pathetic.

Not guessing the cause, there was nothing to remind him that

experience is as to intensity, and not as to duration. Tess's

passing corporeal blight had been her mental harvest.

Tess, on her part, could not understand why a man of clerical family

and good education, and above physical want, should look upon it as a

mishap to be alive. For the unhappy pilgrim herself there was very

good reason. But how could this admirable and poetic man ever have

descended into the Valley of Humiliation, have felt with the man of

Uz--as she herself had felt two or three years ago--"My soul chooseth

strangling and death rather than my life. I loathe it; I would not

live alway."

It was true that he was at present out of his class. But she knew

that was only because, like Peter the Great in a shipwright's yard,

he was studying what he wanted to know. He did not milk cows because

he was obliged to milk cows, but because he was learning to be a

rich and prosperous dairyman, landowner, agriculturist, and breeder

of cattle. He would become an American or Australian Abraham,

commanding like a monarch his flocks and his herds, his spotted

and his ring-straked, his men-servants and his maids. At times,

nevertheless, it did seem unaccountable to her that a decidedly

bookish, musical, thinking young man should have chosen deliberately

to be a farmer, and not a clergyman, like his father and brothers.

Thus, neither having the clue to the other's secret, they were

respectively puzzled at what each revealed, and awaited new knowledge

of each other's character and mood without attempting to pry into

each other's history.

Every day, every hour, brought to him one more little stroke of

her nature, and to her one more of his. Tess was trying to lead a

repressed life, but she little divined the strength of her own

vitality.

At first Tess seemed to regard Angel Clare as an intelligence rather

than as a man. As such she compared him with herself; and at every

discovery of the abundance of his illuminations, of the distance

between her own modest mental standpoint and the unmeasurable, Andean

altitude of his, she became quite dejected, disheartened from all

further effort on her own part whatever.

He observed her dejection one day, when he had casually mentioned

something to her about pastoral life in ancient Greece. She was

gathering the buds called "lords and ladies" from the bank while he

spoke.

"Why do you look so woebegone all of a sudden?" he asked.

"Oh, 'tis only--about my own self," she said, with a frail laugh of

sadness, fitfully beginning to peel "a lady" meanwhile. "Just a

sense of what might have been with me! My life looks as if it had

been wasted for want of chances! When I see what you know, what you

have read, and seen, and thought, I feel what a nothing I am! I'm

like the poor Queen of Sheba who lived in the Bible. There is no

more spirit in me."

"Bless my soul, don't go troubling about that! Why," he said with

some enthusiasm, "I should be only too glad, my dear Tess, to help

you to anything in the way of history, or any line of reading you

would like to take up--"

"It is a lady again," interrupted she, holding out the bud she had

peeled.

"What?"

"I meant that there are always more ladies than lords when you come

to peel them."

"Never mind about the lords and ladies. Would you like to take up

any course of study--history, for example?"

"Sometimes I feel I don't want to know anything more about it than I

know already."

"Why not?"

"Because what's the use of learning that I am one of a long row

only--finding out that there is set down in some old book somebody

just like me, and to know that I shall only act her part; making me

sad, that's all. The best is not to remember that your nature and

your past doings have been just like thousands' and thousands', and

that your coming life and doings 'll be like thousands's and

thousands'."

"What, really, then, you don't want to learn anything?"

"I shouldn't mind learning why--why the sun do shine on the just and

the unjust alike," she answered, with a slight quaver in her voice.

"But that's what books will not tell me."

"Tess, fie for such bitterness!" Of course he spoke with a

conventional sense of duty only, for that sort of wondering had not

been unknown to himself in bygone days. And as he looked at the

unpracticed mouth and lips, he thought that such a daughter of the

soil could only have caught up the sentiment by rote. She went on

peeling the lords and ladies till Clare, regarding for a moment the

wave-like curl of her lashes as they dropped with her bent gaze on

her soft cheek, lingeringly went away. When he was gone she stood

awhile, thoughtfully peeling the last bud; and then, awakening

from her reverie, flung it and all the crowd of floral nobility

impatiently on the ground, in an ebullition of displeasure with

herself for her _niaiserie_, and with a quickening warmth in her

heart of hearts.

How stupid he must think her! In an access of hunger for his good

opinion she bethought herself of what she had latterly endeavoured to

forget, so unpleasant had been its issues--the identity of her family

with that of the knightly d'Urbervilles. Barren attribute as it was,

disastrous as its discovery had been in many ways to her, perhaps

Mr Clare, as a gentleman and a student of history, would respect

her sufficiently to forget her childish conduct with the lords and

ladies if he knew that those Purbeck-marble and alabaster people in

Kingsbere Church really represented her own lineal forefathers; that

she was no spurious d'Urberville, compounded of money and ambition

like those at Trantridge, but true d'Urberville to the bone.

But, before venturing to make the revelation, dubious Tess indirectly

sounded the dairyman as to its possible effect upon Mr Clare, by

asking the former if Mr Clare had any great respect for old county

families when they had lost all their money and land.

"Mr Clare," said the dairyman emphatically, "is one of the most

rebellest rozums you ever knowed--not a bit like the rest of his

family; and if there's one thing that he do hate more than another

'tis the notion of what's called a' old family. He says that it

stands to reason that old families have done their spurt of work in

past days, and can't have anything left in 'em now. There's the

Billets and the Drenkhards and the Greys and the St Quintins and

the Hardys and the Goulds, who used to own the lands for miles down

this valley; you could buy 'em all up now for an old song a'most.

Why, our little Retty Priddle here, you know, is one of the

Paridelles--the old family that used to own lots o' the lands out by

King's Hintock, now owned by the Earl o' Wessex, afore even he or

his was heard of. Well, Mr Clare found this out, and spoke quite

scornful to the poor girl for days. 'Ah!' he says to her, 'you'll

never make a good dairymaid! All your skill was used up ages ago

in Palestine, and you must lie fallow for a thousand years to git

strength for more deeds!' A boy came here t'other day asking for

a job, and said his name was Matt, and when we asked him his surname

he said he'd never heard that 'a had any surname, and when we asked

why, he said he supposed his folks hadn't been 'stablished long

enough. 'Ah! you're the very boy I want!' says Mr Clare, jumping

up and shaking hands wi'en; 'I've great hopes of you;' and gave him

half-a-crown. O no! he can't stomach old families!"

After hearing this caricature of Clare's opinion poor Tess was glad

that she had not said a word in a weak moment about her family--even

though it was so unusually old almost to have gone round the circle

and become a new one. Besides, another diary-girl was as good as

she, it seemed, in that respect. She held her tongue about the

d'Urberville vault and the Knight of the Conqueror whose name she

bore. The insight afforded into Clare's character suggested to her

that it was largely owing to her supposed untraditional newness that

she had won interest in his eyes.

XX

The season developed and matured. Another year's instalment of

flowers, leaves, nightingales, thrushes, finches, and such ephemeral

creatures, took up their positions where only a year ago others had

stood in their place when these were nothing more than germs and

inorganic particles. Rays from the sunrise drew forth the buds and

stretched them into long stalks, lifted up sap in noiseless streams,

opened petals, and sucked out scents in invisible jets and

breathings.

Dairyman Crick's household of maids and men lived on comfortably,

placidly, even merrily. Their position was perhaps the happiest of

all positions in the social scale, being above the line at which

neediness ends, and below the line at which the _convenances_ begin

to cramp natural feelings, and the stress of threadbare modishness

makes too little of enough.

Thus passed the leafy time when arborescence seems to be the one

thing aimed at out of doors. Tess and Clare unconsciously studied

each other, ever balanced on the edge of a passion, yet apparently

keeping out of it. All the while they were converging, under an

irresistible law, as surely as two streams in one vale.

Tess had never in her recent life been so happy as she was now,

possibly never would be so happy again. She was, for one thing,

physically and mentally suited among these new surroundings. The

sapling which had rooted down to a poisonous stratum on the spot of

its sowing had been transplanted to a deeper soil. Moreover she, and

Clare also, stood as yet on the debatable land between predilection

and love; where no profundities have been reached; no reflections

have set in, awkwardly inquiring, "Whither does this new current tend

to carry me? What does it mean to my future? How does it stand

towards my past?"

Tess was the merest stray phenomenon to Angel Clare as yet--a rosy,

warming apparition which had only just acquired the attribute of

persistence in his consciousness. So he allowed his mind to be

occupied with her, deeming his preoccupation to be no more than a

philosopher's regard of an exceedingly novel, fresh, and interesting

specimen of womankind.

They met continually; they could not help it. They met daily in that

strange and solemn interval, the twilight of the morning, in the

violet or pink dawn; for it was necessary to rise early, so very

early, here. Milking was done betimes; and before the milking came

the skimming, which began at a little past three. It usually fell

to the lot of some one or other of them to wake the rest, the first

being aroused by an alarm-clock; and, as Tess was the latest arrival,

and they soon discovered that she could be depended upon not to sleep

though the alarm as others did, this task was thrust most frequently

upon her. No sooner had the hour of three struck and whizzed,

than she left her room and ran to the dairyman's door; then up the

ladder to Angel's, calling him in a loud whisper; then woke her

fellow-milkmaids. By the time that Tess was dressed Clare was

downstairs and out in the humid air. The remaining maids and the

dairyman usually gave themselves another turn on the pillow, and did

not appear till a quarter of an hour later.

The gray half-tones of daybreak are not the gray half-tones of the

day's close, though the degree of their shade may be the same. In

the twilight of the morning, light seems active, darkness passive;

in the twilight of evening it is the darkness which is active and

crescent, and the light which is the drowsy reverse.

Being so often--possibly not always by chance--the first two persons

to get up at the dairy-house, they seemed to themselves the first

persons up of all the world. In these early days of her residence

here Tess did not skim, but went out of doors at once after rising,

where he was generally awaiting her. The spectral, half-compounded,

aqueous light which pervaded the open mead impressed them with

a feeling of isolation, as if they were Adam and Eve. At this

dim inceptive stage of the day Tess seemed to Clare to exhibit a

dignified largeness both of disposition and physique, an almost

regnant power, possibly because he knew that at that preternatural

time hardly any woman so well endowed in person as she was likely to

be walking in the open air within the boundaries of his horizon; very

few in all England. Fair women are usually asleep at mid-summer

dawns. She was close at hand, and the rest were nowhere.

The mixed, singular, luminous gloom in which they walked along

together to the spot where the cows lay often made him think of the

Resurrection hour. He little thought that the Magdalen might be

at his side. Whilst all the landscape was in neutral shade his

companion's face, which was the focus of his eyes, rising above the

mist stratum, seemed to have a sort of phosphorescence upon it. She

looked ghostly, as if she were merely a soul at large. In reality

her face, without appearing to do so, had caught the cold gleam of

day from the north-east; his own face, though he did not think of

it, wore the same aspect to her.

It was then, as has been said, that she impressed him most deeply.

She was no longer the milkmaid, but a visionary essence of woman--a

whole sex condensed into one typical form. He called her Artemis,

Demeter, and other fanciful names half teasingly, which she did not

like because she did not understand them.

"Call me Tess," she would say askance; and he did.

Then it would grow lighter, and her features would become simply

feminine; they had changed from those of a divinity who could confer

bliss to those of a being who craved it.

At these non-human hours they could get quite close to the waterfowl.

Herons came, with a great bold noise as of opening doors and

shutters, out of the boughs of a plantation which they frequented at

the side of the mead; or, if already on the spot, hardily maintained

their standing in the water as the pair walked by, watching them by

moving their heads round in a slow, horizontal, passionless wheel,

like the turn of puppets by clockwork.

They could then see the faint summer fogs in layers, woolly, level,

and apparently no thicker than counterpanes, spread about the meadows

in detached remnants of small extent. On the gray moisture of the

grass were marks where the cows had lain through the night--dark-green

islands of dry herbage the size of their carcasses, in the general

sea of dew. From each island proceeded a serpentine trail, by which

the cow had rambled away to feed after getting up, at the end of

which trail they found her; the snoring puff from her nostrils, when

she recognized them, making an intenser little fog of her own amid

the prevailing one. Then they drove the animals back to the barton,

or sat down to milk them on the spot, as the case might require.

Or perhaps the summer fog was more general, and the meadows lay like

a white sea, out of which the scattered trees rose like dangerous

rocks. Birds would soar through it into the upper radiance, and

hang on the wing sunning themselves, or alight on the wet rails

subdividing the mead, which now shone like glass rods. Minute

diamonds of moisture from the mist hung, too, upon Tess's eyelashes,

and drops upon her hair, like seed pearls. When the day grew quite

strong and commonplace these dried off her; moreover, Tess then

lost her strange and ethereal beauty; her teeth, lips, and eyes

scintillated in the sunbeams and she was again the dazzlingly fair

dairymaid only, who had to hold her own against the other women of

the world.

About this time they would hear Dairyman Crick's voice, lecturing the

non-resident milkers for arriving late, and speaking sharply to old

Deborah Fyander for not washing her hands.

"For Heaven's sake, pop thy hands under the pump, Deb! Upon my soul,

if the London folk only knowed of thee and thy slovenly ways, they'd

swaller their milk and butter more mincing than they do a'ready; and

that's saying a good deal."

The milking progressed, till towards the end Tess and Clare, in

common with the rest, could hear the heavy breakfast table dragged

out from the wall in the kitchen by Mrs Crick, this being the

invariable preliminary to each meal; the same horrible scrape

accompanying its return journey when the table had been cleared.

XXI

There was a great stir in the milk-house just after breakfast. The

churn revolved as usual, but the butter would not come. Whenever

this happened the dairy was paralyzed. Squish, squash echoed the

milk in the great cylinder, but never arose the sound they waited

for.

Dairyman Crick and his wife, the milkmaids Tess, Marian, Retty

Priddle, Izz Huett, and the married ones from the cottages; also

Mr Clare, Jonathan Kail, old Deborah, and the rest, stood gazing

hopelessly at the churn; and the boy who kept the horse going outside

put on moon-like eyes to show his sense of the situation. Even the

melancholy horse himself seemed to look in at the window in inquiring

despair at each walk round.

"'Tis years since I went to Conjuror Trendle's son in Egdon--years!"

said the dairyman bitterly. "And he was nothing to what his father

had been. I have said fifty times, if I have said once, that I DON'T

believe in en; though 'a do cast folks' waters very true. But I

shall have to go to 'n if he's alive. O yes, I shall have to go to

'n, if this sort of thing continnys!"

Even Mr Clare began to feel tragical at the dairyman's desperation.

"Conjuror Fall, t'other side of Casterbridge, that they used to call

'Wide-O', was a very good man when I was a boy," said Jonathan Kail.

"But he's rotten as touchwood by now."

"My grandfather used to go to Conjuror Mynterne, out at Owlscombe,

and a clever man a' were, so I've heard grandf'er say," continued Mr

Crick. "But there's no such genuine folk about nowadays!"

Mrs Crick's mind kept nearer to the matter in hand.

"Perhaps somebody in the house is in love," she said tentatively.

"I've heard tell in my younger days that that will cause it. Why,

Crick--that maid we had years ago, do ye mind, and how the butter

didn't come then--"

"Ah yes, yes!--but that isn't the rights o't. It had nothing to do

with the love-making. I can mind all about it--'twas the damage to

the churn."

He turned to Clare.

"Jack Dollop, a 'hore's-bird of a fellow we had here as milker at one

time, sir, courted a young woman over at Mellstock, and deceived her

as he had deceived many afore. But he had another sort o' woman to

reckon wi' this time, and it was not the girl herself. One Holy

Thursday of all days in the almanack, we was here as we mid be now,

only there was no churning in hand, when we zid the girl's mother

coming up to the door, wi' a great brass-mounted umbrella in her

hand that would ha' felled an ox, and saying 'Do Jack Dollop work

here?--because I want him! I have a big bone to pick with he, I

can assure 'n!' And some way behind her mother walked Jack's young

woman, crying bitterly into her handkercher. 'O Lard, here's a

time!' said Jack, looking out o' winder at 'em. 'She'll murder me!

Where shall I get--where shall I--? Don't tell her where I be!'

And with that he scrambled into the churn through the trap-door, and

shut himself inside, just as the young woman's mother busted into

the milk-house. 'The villain--where is he?' says she. 'I'll claw

his face for'n, let me only catch him!' Well, she hunted about

everywhere, ballyragging Jack by side and by seam, Jack lying

a'most stifled inside the churn, and the poor maid--or young woman

rather--standing at the door crying her eyes out. I shall never

forget it, never! 'Twould have melted a marble stone! But she

couldn't find him nowhere at all."

The dairyman paused, and one or two words of comment came from the

listeners.

Dairyman Crick's stories often seemed to be ended when they were not

really so, and strangers were betrayed into premature interjections

of finality; though old friends knew better. The narrator went on--

"Well, how the old woman should have had the wit to guess it I could

never tell, but she found out that he was inside that there churn.

Without saying a word she took hold of the winch (it was turned by

handpower then), and round she swung him, and Jack began to flop

about inside. 'O Lard! stop the churn! let me out!' says he, popping

out his head. 'I shall be churned into a pummy!' (He was a cowardly

chap in his heart, as such men mostly be). 'Not till ye make amends

for ravaging her virgin innocence!' says the old woman. 'Stop the

churn you old witch!' screams he. 'You call me old witch, do ye, you

deceiver!' says she, 'when ye ought to ha' been calling me mother-law

these last five months!' And on went the churn, and Jack's bones

rattled round again. Well, none of us ventured to interfere; and at

last 'a promised to make it right wi' her. 'Yes--I'll be as good as

my word!' he said. And so it ended that day."

While the listeners were smiling their comments there was a

quick movement behind their backs, and they looked round. Tess,

pale-faced, had gone to the door.

"How warm 'tis to-day!" she said, almost inaudibly.

It was warm, and none of them connected her withdrawal with the

reminiscences of the dairyman. He went forward and opened the door

for her, saying with tender raillery--

"Why, maidy" (he frequently, with unconscious irony, gave her this

pet name), "the prettiest milker I've got in my dairy; you mustn't

get so fagged as this at the first breath of summer weather, or we

shall be finely put to for want of 'ee by dog-days, shan't we, Mr

Clare?"

"I was faint--and--I think I am better out o' doors," she said

mechanically; and disappeared outside.

Fortunately for her the milk in the revolving churn at that moment

changed its squashing for a decided flick-flack.

"'Tis coming!" cried Mrs Crick, and the attention of all was called

off from Tess.

That fair sufferer soon recovered herself externally; but she

remained much depressed all the afternoon. When the evening milking

was done she did not care to be with the rest of them, and went out

of doors, wandering along she knew not whither. She was wretched--O

so wretched--at the perception that to her companions the dairyman's

story had been rather a humorous narration than otherwise; none of

them but herself seemed to see the sorrow of it; to a certainty, not

one knew how cruelly it touched the tender place in her experience.

The evening sun was now ugly to her, like a great inflamed wound in

the sky. Only a solitary cracked-voice reed-sparrow greeted her from

the bushes by the river, in a sad, machine-made tone, resembling that

of a past friend whose friendship she had outworn.

In these long June days the milkmaids, and, indeed, most of the

household, went to bed at sunset or sooner, the morning work before

milking being so early and heavy at a time of full pails. Tess

usually accompanied her fellows upstairs. To-night, however, she was

the first to go to their common chamber; and she had dozed when the

other girls came in. She saw them undressing in the orange light

of the vanished sun, which flushed their forms with its colour; she

dozed again, but she was reawakened by their voices, and quietly

turned her eyes towards them.

Neither of her three chamber-companions had got into bed. They were

standing in a group, in their nightgowns, barefooted, at the window,

the last red rays of the west still warming their faces and necks and

the walls around them. All were watching somebody in the garden with

deep interest, their three faces close together: a jovial and round

one, a pale one with dark hair, and a fair one whose tresses were

auburn.

"Don't push! You can see as well as I," said Retty, the

auburn-haired and youngest girl, without removing her eyes from the

window.

"'Tis no use for you to be in love with him any more than me, Retty

Priddle," said jolly-faced Marian, the eldest, slily. "His thoughts

be of other cheeks than thine!"

Retty Priddle still looked, and the others looked again.

"There he is again!" cried Izz Huett, the pale girl with dark damp

hair and keenly cut lips.

"You needn't say anything, Izz," answered Retty. "For I zid you

kissing his shade."

"WHAT did you see her doing?" asked Marian.

"Why--he was standing over the whey-tub to let off the whey, and the

shade of his face came upon the wall behind, close to Izz, who was

standing there filling a vat. She put her mouth against the wall and

kissed the shade of his mouth; I zid her, though he didn't."

"O Izz Huett!" said Marian.

A rosy spot came into the middle of Izz Huett's cheek.

"Well, there was no harm in it," she declared, with attempted

coolness. "And if I be in love wi'en, so is Retty, too; and so be

you, Marian, come to that."

Marian's full face could not blush past its chronic pinkness.

"I!" she said. "What a tale! Ah, there he is again! Dear

eyes--dear face--dear Mr Clare!"

"There--you've owned it!"

"So have you--so have we all," said Marian, with the dry frankness of

complete indifference to opinion. "It is silly to pretend otherwise

amongst ourselves, though we need not own it to other folks. I would

just marry 'n to-morrow!"

"So would I--and more," murmured Izz Huett.

"And I too," whispered the more timid Retty.

The listener grew warm.

"We can't all marry him," said Izz.

"We shan't, either of us; which is worse still," said the eldest.

"There he is again!"

They all three blew him a silent kiss.

"Why?" asked Retty quickly.

"Because he likes Tess Durbeyfield best," said Marian, lowering her

voice. "I have watched him every day, and have found it out."

There was a reflective silence.

"But she don't care anything for 'n?" at length breathed Retty.

"Well--I sometimes think that too."

"But how silly all this is!" said Izz Huett impatiently. "Of course

he won't marry any one of us, or Tess either--a gentleman's son,

who's going to be a great landowner and farmer abroad! More likely

to ask us to come wi'en as farm-hands at so much a year!"

One sighed, and another sighed, and Marian's plump figure sighed

biggest of all. Somebody in bed hard by sighed too. Tears came into

the eyes of Retty Priddle, the pretty red-haired youngest--the last

bud of the Paridelles, so important in the county annals. They

watched silently a little longer, their three faces still close

together as before, and the triple hues of their hair mingling. But

the unconscious Mr Clare had gone indoors, and they saw him no more;

and, the shades beginning to deepen, they crept into their beds.

In a few minutes they heard him ascend the ladder to his own room.

Marian was soon snoring, but Izz did not drop into forgetfulness for

a long time. Retty Priddle cried herself to sleep.

The deeper-passioned Tess was very far from sleeping even then. This

conversation was another of the bitter pills she had been obliged to

swallow that day. Scarce the least feeling of jealousy arose in her

breast. For that matter she knew herself to have the preference.

Being more finely formed, better educated, and, though the youngest

except Retty, more woman than either, she perceived that only the

slightest ordinary care was necessary for holding her own in Angel

Clare's heart against these her candid friends. But the grave

question was, ought she to do this? There was, to be sure, hardly a

ghost of a chance for either of them, in a serious sense; but there

was, or had been, a chance of one or the other inspiring him with a

passing fancy for her, and enjoying the pleasure of his attentions

while he stayed here. Such unequal attachments had led to marriage;

and she had heard from Mrs Crick that Mr Clare had one day asked, in

a laughing way, what would be the use of his marrying a fine lady,

and all the while ten thousand acres of Colonial pasture to feed,

and cattle to rear, and corn to reap. A farm-woman would be the

only sensible kind of wife for him. But whether Mr Clare had spoken

seriously or not, why should she, who could never conscientiously

allow any man to marry her now, and who had religiously determined

that she never would be tempted to do so, draw off Mr Clare's

attention from other women, for the brief happiness of sunning

herself in his eyes while he remained at Talbothays?

XXII

They came downstairs yawning next morning; but skimming and milking

were proceeded with as usual, and they went indoors to breakfast.

Dairyman Crick was discovered stamping about the house. He had

received a letter, in which a customer had complained that the butter

had a twang.

"And begad, so 't have!" said the dairyman, who held in his left hand

a wooden slice on which a lump of butter was stuck. "Yes--taste for

yourself!"

Several of them gathered round him; and Mr Clare tasted, Tess tasted,

also the other indoor milkmaids, one or two of the milking-men, and

last of all Mrs Crick, who came out from the waiting breakfast-table.

There certainly was a twang.

The dairyman, who had thrown himself into abstraction to better

realize the taste, and so divine the particular species of noxious

weed to which it appertained, suddenly exclaimed--

"'Tis garlic! and I thought there wasn't a blade left in that mead!"

Then all the old hands remembered that a certain dry mead, into which

a few of the cows had been admitted of late, had, in years gone by,

spoilt the butter in the same way. The dairyman had not recognized

the taste at that time, and thought the butter bewitched.

"We must overhaul that mead," he resumed; "this mustn't continny!"

All having armed themselves with old pointed knives, they went out

together. As the inimical plant could only be present in very

microscopic dimensions to have escaped ordinary observation, to

find it seemed rather a hopeless attempt in the stretch of rich

grass before them. However, they formed themselves into line, all

assisting, owing to the importance of the search; the dairyman at

the upper end with Mr Clare, who had volunteered to help; then

Tess, Marian, Izz Huett, and Retty; then Bill Lewell, Jonathan, and

the married dairywomen--Beck Knibbs, with her wooly black hair and

rolling eyes; and flaxen Frances, consumptive from the winter damps

of the water-meads--who lived in their respective cottages.

With eyes fixed upon the ground they crept slowly across a strip of

the field, returning a little further down in such a manner that,

when they should have finished, not a single inch of the pasture but

would have fallen under the eye of some one of them. It was a most

tedious business, not more than half a dozen shoots of garlic being

discoverable in the whole field; yet such was the herb's pungency

that probably one bite of it by one cow had been sufficient to season

the whole dairy's produce for the day.

Differing one from another in natures and moods so greatly as they

did, they yet formed, bending, a curiously uniform row--automatic,

noiseless; and an alien observer passing down the neighbouring lane

might well have been excused for massing them as "Hodge". As they

crept along, stooping low to discern the plant, a soft yellow gleam

was reflected from the buttercups into their shaded faces, giving

them an elfish, moonlit aspect, though the sun was pouring upon their

backs in all the strength of noon.

Angel Clare, who communistically stuck to his rule of taking part

with the rest in everything, glanced up now and then. It was not,

of course, by accident that he walked next to Tess.

"Well, how are you?" he murmured.

"Very well, thank you, sir," she replied demurely.

As they had been discussing a score of personal matters only

half-an-hour before, the introductory style seemed a little

superfluous. But they got no further in speech just then. They

crept and crept, the hem of her petticoat just touching his gaiter,

and his elbow sometimes brushing hers. At last the dairyman, who

came next, could stand it no longer.

"Upon my soul and body, this here stooping do fairly make my back

open and shut!" he exclaimed, straightening himself slowly with an

excruciated look till quite upright. "And you, maidy Tess, you

wasn't well a day or two ago--this will make your head ache finely!

Don't do any more, if you feel fainty; leave the rest to finish it."

Dairyman Crick withdrew, and Tess dropped behind. Mr Clare also

stepped out of line, and began privateering about for the weed. When

she found him near her, her very tension at what she had heard the

night before made her the first to speak.

"Don't they look pretty?" she said.

"Who?"

"Izzy Huett and Retty."

Tess had moodily decided that either of these maidens would make a

good farmer's wife, and that she ought to recommend them, and obscure

her own wretched charms.

"Pretty? Well, yes--they are pretty girls--fresh looking. I have

often thought so."

"Though, poor dears, prettiness won't last long!"

"O no, unfortunately."

"They are excellent dairywomen."

"Yes: though not better than you."

"They skim better than I."

"Do they?"

Clare remained observing them--not without their observing him.

"She is colouring up," continued Tess heroically.

"Who?"

"Retty Priddle."

"Oh! Why it that?"

"Because you are looking at her."

Self-sacrificing as her mood might be, Tess could not well go further

and cry, "Marry one of them, if you really do want a dairywoman and

not a lady; and don't think of marrying me!" She followed Dairyman

Crick, and had the mournful satisfaction of seeing that Clare

remained behind.

From this day she forced herself to take pains to avoid him--never

allowing herself, as formerly, to remain long in his company, even if

their juxtaposition were purely accidental. She gave the other three

every chance.

Tess was woman enough to realize from their avowals to herself that

Angel Clare had the honour of all the dairymaids in his keeping, and

her perception of his care to avoid compromising the happiness of

either in the least degree bred a tender respect in Tess for what she

deemed, rightly or wrongly, the self-controlling sense of duty shown

by him, a quality which she had never expected to find in one of the

opposite sex, and in the absence of which more than one of the simple

hearts who were his house-mates might have gone weeping on her

pilgrimage.

XXIII

The hot weather of July had crept upon them unawares, and the

atmosphere of the flat vale hung heavy as an opiate over the

dairy-folk, the cows, and the trees. Hot steaming rains fell

frequently, making the grass where the cows fed yet more rank, and

hindering the late hay-making in the other meads.

It was Sunday morning; the milking was done; the outdoor milkers

had gone home. Tess and the other three were dressing themselves

rapidly, the whole bevy having agreed to go together to Mellstock

Church, which lay some three or four miles distant from the

dairy-house. She had now been two months at Talbothays, and this

was her first excursion.

All the preceding afternoon and night heavy thunderstorms had hissed

down upon the meads, and washed some of the hay into the river; but

this morning the sun shone out all the more brilliantly for the

deluge, and the air was balmy and clear.

The crooked lane leading from their own parish to Mellstock ran along

the lowest levels in a portion of its length, and when the girls

reached the most depressed spot they found that the result of the

rain had been to flood the lane over-shoe to a distance of some fifty

yards. This would have been no serious hindrance on a week-day; they

would have clicked through it in their high patterns and boots quite

unconcerned; but on this day of vanity, this Sun's-day, when flesh

went forth to coquet with flesh while hypocritically affecting

business with spiritual things; on this occasion for wearing their

white stockings and thin shoes, and their pink, white, and lilac

gowns, on which every mud spot would be visible, the pool was an

awkward impediment. They could hear the church-bell calling--as yet

nearly a mile off.

"Who would have expected such a rise in the river in summer-time!"

said Marian, from the top of the roadside bank on which they had

climbed, and were maintaining a precarious footing in the hope of

creeping along its slope till they were past the pool.

"We can't get there anyhow, without walking right through it, or else

going round the Turnpike way; and that would make us so very late!"

said Retty, pausing hopelessly.

"And I do colour up so hot, walking into church late, and all the

people staring round," said Marian, "that I hardly cool down again

till we get into the That-it-may-please-Thees."

While they stood clinging to the bank they heard a splashing round

the bend of the road, and presently appeared Angel Clare, advancing

along the lane towards them through the water.

Four hearts gave a big throb simultaneously.

His aspect was probably as un-Sabbatarian a one as a dogmatic

parson's son often presented; his attire being his dairy clothes,

long wading boots, a cabbage-leaf inside his hat to keep his head

cool, with a thistle-spud to finish him off. "He's not going to

church," said Marian.

"No--I wish he was!" murmured Tess.

Angel, in fact, rightly or wrongly (to adopt the safe phrase of

evasive controversialists), preferred sermons in stones to sermons in

churches and chapels on fine summer days. This morning, moreover,

he had gone out to see if the damage to the hay by the flood was

considerable or not. On his walk he observed the girls from a long

distance, though they had been so occupied with their difficulties of

passage as not to notice him. He knew that the water had risen at

that spot, and that it would quite check their progress. So he had

hastened on, with a dim idea of how he could help them--one of them

in particular.

The rosy-cheeked, bright-eyed quartet looked so charming in their

light summer attire, clinging to the roadside bank like pigeons on a

roof-slope, that he stopped a moment to regard them before coming

close. Their gauzy skirts had brushed up from the grass innumerable

flies and butterflies which, unable to escape, remained caged in

the transparent tissue as in an aviary. Angel's eye at last fell

upon Tess, the hindmost of the four; she, being full of suppressed

laughter at their dilemma, could not help meeting his glance

radiantly.

He came beneath them in the water, which did not rise over his long

boots; and stood looking at the entrapped flies and butterflies.

"Are you trying to get to church?" he said to Marian, who was in

front, including the next two in his remark, but avoiding Tess.

"Yes, sir; and 'tis getting late; and my colour do come up so--"

"I'll carry you through the pool--every Jill of you."

The whole four flushed as if one heart beat through them.

"I think you can't, sir," said Marian.

"It is the only way for you to get past. Stand still. Nonsense--you

are not too heavy! I'd carry you all four together. Now, Marian,

attend," he continued, "and put your arms round my shoulders, so.

Now! Hold on. That's well done."

Marian had lowered herself upon his arm and shoulder as directed, and

Angel strode off with her, his slim figure, as viewed from behind,

looking like the mere stem to the great nosegay suggested by hers.

They disappeared round the curve of the road, and only his sousing

footsteps and the top ribbon of Marian's bonnet told where they were.

In a few minutes he reappeared. Izz Huett was the next in order upon

the bank.

"Here he comes," she murmured, and they could hear that her lips were

dry with emotion. "And I have to put my arms round his neck and look

into his face as Marian did."

"There's nothing in that," said Tess quickly.

"There's a time for everything," continued Izz, unheeding. "A time

to embrace, and a time to refrain from embracing; the first is now

going to be mine."

"Fie--it is Scripture, Izz!"

"Yes," said Izz, "I've always a' ear at church for pretty verses."

Angel Clare, to whom three-quarters of this performance was a

commonplace act of kindness, now approached Izz. She quietly and

dreamily lowered herself into his arms, and Angel methodically

marched off with her. When he was heard returning for the third time

Retty's throbbing heart could be almost seen to shake her. He went

up to the red-haired girl, and while he was seizing her he glanced at

Tess. His lips could not have pronounced more plainly, "It will soon

be you and I." Her comprehension appeared in her face; she could not

help it. There was an understanding between them.

Poor little Retty, though by far the lightest weight, was the most

troublesome of Clare's burdens. Marian had been like a sack of meal,

a dead weight of plumpness under which he has literally staggered.

Izz had ridden sensibly and calmly. Retty was a bunch of hysterics.

However, he got through with the disquieted creature, deposited her,

and returned. Tess could see over the hedge the distant three in a

group, standing as he had placed them on the next rising ground. It

was now her turn. She was embarrassed to discover that excitement at

the proximity of Mr Clare's breath and eyes, which she had contemned

in her companions, was intensified in herself; and as if fearful of

betraying her secret, she paltered with him at the last moment.

"I may be able to clim' along the bank perhaps--I can clim' better

than they. You must be so tired, Mr Clare!"

"No, no, Tess," said he quickly. And almost before she was aware,

she was seated in his arms and resting against his shoulder.

"Three Leahs to get one Rachel," he whispered.

"They are better women than I," she replied, magnanimously sticking

to her resolve.

"Not to me," said Angel.

He saw her grow warm at this; and they went some steps in silence.

"I hope I am not too heavy?" she said timidly.

"O no. You should lift Marian! Such a lump. You are like an

undulating billow warmed by the sun. And all this fluff of muslin

about you is the froth."

"It is very pretty--if I seem like that to you."

"Do you know that I have undergone three-quarters of this labour

entirely for the sake of the fourth quarter?"

"No."

"I did not expect such an event to-day."

"Nor I... The water came up so sudden."

That the rise in the water was what she understood him to refer to,

the state of breathing belied. Clare stood still and inclinced his

face towards hers.

"O Tessy!" he exclaimed.

The girl's cheeks burned to the breeze, and she could not look into

his eyes for her emotion. It reminded Angel that he was somewhat

unfairly taking advantage of an accidental position; and he went no

further with it. No definite words of love had crossed their lips

as yet, and suspension at this point was desirable now. However,

he walked slowly, to make the remainder of the distance as long as

possible; but at last they came to the bend, and the rest of their

progress was in full view of the other three. The dry land was

reached, and he set her down.

Her friends were looking with round thoughtful eyes at her and him,

and she could see that they had been talking of her. He hastily bade

them farewell, and splashed back along the stretch of submerged road.

The four moved on together as before, till Marian broke the silence

by saying--

"No--in all truth; we have no chance against her!" She looked

joylessly at Tess.

"What do you mean?" asked the latter.

"He likes 'ee best--the very best! We could see it as he brought

'ee. He would have kissed 'ee, if you had encouraged him to do it,

ever so little."

"No, no," said she.

The gaiety with which they had set out had somehow vanished; and

yet there was no enmity or malice between them. They were generous

young souls; they had been reared in the lonely country nooks where

fatalism is a strong sentiment, and they did not blame her. Such

supplanting was to be.

Tess's heart ached. There was no concealing from herself the fact

that she loved Angel Clare, perhaps all the more passionately from

knowing that the others had also lost their hearts to him. There is

contagion in this sentiment, especially among women. And yet that

same hungry nature had fought against this, but too feebly, and the

natural result had followed.

"I will never stand in your way, nor in the way of either of you!"

she declared to Retty that night in the bedroom (her tears running

down). "I can't help this, my dear! I don't think marrying is in

his mind at all; but if he were ever to ask me I should refuse him,

as I should refuse any man."

"Oh! would you? Why?" said wondering Retty.

"It cannot be! But I will be plain. Putting myself quite on one

side, I don't think he will choose either of you."

"I have never expected it--thought of it!" moaned Retty. "But O! I

wish I was dead!"

The poor child, torn by a feeling which she hardly understood, turned

to the other two girls who came upstairs just then.

"We be friends with her again," she said to them. "She thinks no

more of his choosing her than we do."

So the reserve went off, and they were confiding and warm.

"I don't seem to care what I do now," said Marian, whose mood was

turned to its lowest bass. "I was going to marry a dairyman at

Stickleford, who's asked me twice; but--my soul--I would put an end

to myself rather'n be his wife now! Why don't ye speak, Izz?"

"To confess, then," murmured Izz, "I made sure to-day that he was

going to kiss me as he held me; and I lay still against his breast,

hoping and hoping, and never moved at all. But he did not. I don't

like biding here at Talbothays any longer! I shall go hwome."

The air of the sleeping-chamber seemed to palpitate with the

hopeless passion of the girls. They writhed feverishly under the

oppressiveness of an emotion thrust on them by cruel Nature's law--an

emotion which they had neither expected nor desired. The incident

of the day had fanned the flame that was burning the inside of their

hearts out, and the torture was almost more than they could endure.

The differences which distinguished them as individuals were

abstracted by this passion, and each was but portion of one organism

called sex. There was so much frankness and so little jealousy

because there was no hope. Each one was a girl of fair common sense,

and she did not delude herself with any vain conceits, or deny her

love, or give herself airs, in the idea of outshining the others.

The full recognition of the futility of their infatuation, from a

social point of view; its purposeless beginning; its self-bounded

outlook; its lack of everything to justify its existence in the eye

of civilization (while lacking nothing in the eye of Nature); the one

fact that it did exist, ecstasizing them to a killing joy--all this

imparted to them a resignation, a dignity, which a practical and

sordid expectation of winning him as a husband would have destroyed.

They tossed and turned on their little beds, and the cheese-wring

dripped monotonously downstairs.

"B' you awake, Tess?" whispered one, half-an-hour later.

It was Izz Huett's voice.

Tess replied in the affirmative, whereupon also Retty and Marian

suddenly flung the bedclothes off them, and sighed--

"So be we!"

"I wonder what she is like--the lady they say his family have looked

out for him!"

"I wonder," said Izz.

"Some lady looked out for him?" gasped Tess, starting. "I have never

heard o' that!"

"O yes--'tis whispered; a young lady of his own rank, chosen by his

family; a Doctor of Divinity's daughter near his father's parish of

Emminster; he don't much care for her, they say. But he is sure to

marry her."

They had heard so very little of this; yet it was enough to build up

wretched dolorous dreams upon, there in the shade of the night. They

pictured all the details of his being won round to consent, of the

wedding preparations, of the bride's happiness, of her dress and

veil, of her blissful home with him, when oblivion would have fallen

upon themselves as far as he and their love were concerned. Thus

they talked, and ached, and wept till sleep charmed their sorrow

away.

After this disclosure Tess nourished no further foolish thought that

there lurked any grave and deliberate import in Clare's attentions

to her. It was a passing summer love of her face, for love's own

temporary sake--nothing more. And the thorny crown of this sad

conception was that she whom he really did prefer in a cursory way

to the rest, she who knew herself to be more impassioned in nature,

cleverer, more beautiful than they, was in the eyes of propriety far

less worthy of him than the homelier ones whom he ignored.

XXIV

Amid the oozing fatness and warm ferments of the Froom Vale, at a

season when the rush of juices could almost be heard below the hiss

of fertilization, it was impossible that the most fanciful love

should not grow passionate. The ready bosoms existing there were

impregnated by their surroundings.

July passed over their heads, and the Thermidorean weather which came

in its wake seemed an effort on the part of Nature to match the state

of hearts at Talbothays Dairy. The air of the place, so fresh in the

spring and early summer, was stagnant and enervating now. Its heavy

scents weighed upon them, and at mid-day the landscape seemed lying

in a swoon. Ethiopic scorchings browned the upper slopes of the

pastures, but there was still bright green herbage here where the

watercourses purled. And as Clare was oppressed by the outward

heats, so was he burdened inwardly by waxing fervour of passion for

the soft and silent Tess.

The rains having passed, the uplands were dry. The wheels of the

dairyman's spring-cart, as he sped home from market, licked up the

pulverized surface of the highway, and were followed by white ribands

of dust, as if they had set a thin powder-train on fire. The cows

jumped wildly over the five-barred barton-gate, maddened by the

gad-fly; Dairyman Crick kept his shirt-sleeves permanently rolled up

from Monday to Saturday; open windows had no effect in ventilation

without open doors, and in the dairy-garden the blackbirds and

thrushes crept about under the currant-bushes, rather in the manner

of quadrupeds than of winged creatures. The flies in the kitchen

were lazy, teasing, and familiar, crawling about in the unwonted

places, on the floors, into drawers, and over the backs of the

milkmaids' hands. Conversations were concerning sunstroke; while

butter-making, and still more butter-keeping, was a despair.

They milked entirely in the meads for coolness and convenience,

without driving in the cows. During the day the animals obsequiously

followed the shadow of the smallest tree as it moved round the stem

with the diurnal roll; and when the milkers came they could hardly

stand still for the flies.

On one of these afternoons four or five unmilked cows chanced to

stand apart from the general herd, behind the corner of a hedge,

among them being Dumpling and Old Pretty, who loved Tess's hands

above those of any other maid. When she rose from her stool under a

finished cow, Angel Clare, who had been observing her for some time,

asked her if she would take the aforesaid creatures next. She

silently assented, and with her stool at arm's length, and the pail

against her knee, went round to where they stood. Soon the sound of

Old Pretty's milk fizzing into the pail came through the hedge, and

then Angel felt inclined to go round the corner also, to finish off a

hard-yielding milcher who had strayed there, he being now as capable

of this as the dairyman himself.

All the men, and some of the women, when milking, dug their foreheads

into the cows and gazed into the pail. But a few--mainly the younger

ones--rested their heads sideways. This was Tess Durbeyfield's

habit, her temple pressing the milcher's flank, her eyes fixed on

the far end of the meadow with the quiet of one lost in meditation.

She was milking Old Pretty thus, and the sun chancing to be on the

milking-side, it shone flat upon her pink-gowned form and her white

curtain-bonnet, and upon her profile, rendering it keen as a cameo

cut from the dun background of the cow.

She did not know that Clare had followed her round, and that he sat

under his cow watching her. The stillness of her head and features

was remarkable: she might have been in a trance, her eyes open, yet

unseeing. Nothing in the picture moved but Old Pretty's tail and

Tess's pink hands, the latter so gently as to be a rhythmic pulsation

only, as if they were obeying a reflex stimulus, like a beating

heart.

How very lovable her face was to him. Yet there was nothing ethereal

about it; all was real vitality, real warmth, real incarnation. And

it was in her mouth that this culminated. Eyes almost as deep and

speaking he had seen before, and cheeks perhaps as fair; brows as

arched, a chin and throat almost as shapely; her mouth he had seen

nothing to equal on the face of the earth. To a young man with the

least fire in him that little upward lift in the middle of her red

top lip was distracting, infatuating, maddening. He had never before

seen a woman's lips and teeth which forced upon his mind with such

persistent iteration the old Elizabethan simile of roses filled with

snow. Perfect, he, as a lover, might have called them off-hand. But

no--they were not perfect. And it was the touch of the imperfect

upon the would-be perfect that gave the sweetness, because it was

that which gave the humanity.

Clare had studied the curves of those lips so many times that he

could reproduce them mentally with ease: and now, as they again

confronted him, clothed with colour and life, they sent an _aura_

over his flesh, a breeze through his nerves, which well nigh produced

a qualm; and actually produced, by some mysterious physiological

process, a prosaic sneeze.

She then became conscious that he was observing her; but she would

not show it by any change of position, though the curious dream-like

fixity disappeared, and a close eye might easily have discerned that

the rosiness of her face deepened, and then faded till only a tinge

of it was left.

The influence that had passed into Clare like an excitation from the

sky did not die down. Resolutions, reticences, prudences, fears,

fell back like a defeated battalion. He jumped up from his seat,

and, leaving his pail to be kicked over if the milcher had such a

mind, went quickly towards the desire of his eyes, and, kneeling down

beside her, clasped her in his arms.

Tess was taken completely by surprise, and she yielded to his embrace

with unreflecting inevitableness. Having seen that it was really her

lover who had advanced, and no one else, her lips parted, and she

sank upon him in her momentary joy, with something very like an

ecstatic cry.

He had been on the point of kissing that too tempting mouth, but he

checked himself, for tender conscience' sake.

"Forgive me, Tess dear!" he whispered. "I ought to have asked.

I--did not know what I was doing. I do not mean it as a liberty.

I am devoted to you, Tessy, dearest, in all sincerity!"

Old Pretty by this time had looked round, puzzled; and seeing two

people crouching under her where, by immemorial custom, there should

have been only one, lifted her hind leg crossly.

"She is angry--she doesn't know what we mean--she'll kick over the

milk!" exclaimed Tess, gently striving to free herself, her eyes

concerned with the quadruped's actions, her heart more deeply

concerned with herself and Clare.

She slipped up from her seat, and they stood together, his arm still

encircling her. Tess's eyes, fixed on distance, began to fill.

"Why do you cry, my darling?" he said.

"O--I don't know!" she murmured.

As she saw and felt more clearly the position she was in she became

agitated and tried to withdraw.

"Well, I have betrayed my feeling, Tess, at last," said he, with a

curious sigh of desperation, signifying unconsciously that his heart

had outrun his judgement. "That I--love you dearly and truly I need

not say. But I--it shall go no further now--it distresses you--I am

as surprised as you are. You will not think I have presumed upon

your defencelessness--been too quick and unreflecting, will you?"

"N'--I can't tell."

He had allowed her to free herself; and in a minute or two the

milking of each was resumed. Nobody had beheld the gravitation of

the two into one; and when the dairyman came round by that screened

nook a few minutes later, there was not a sign to reveal that

the markedly sundered pair were more to each other than mere

acquaintance. Yet in the interval since Crick's last view of them

something had occurred which changed the pivot of the universe for

their two natures; something which, had he known its quality, the

dairyman would have despised, as a practical man; yet which was based

upon a more stubborn and resistless tendency than a whole heap of

so-called practicalities. A veil had been whisked aside; the tract

of each one's outlook was to have a new horizon thenceforward--for a

short time or for a long.

END OF PHASE THE THIRD

Phase the Fourth: The Consequence

XXV

Clare, restless, went out into the dusk when evening drew on, she who

had won him having retired to her chamber.

The night was as sultry as the day. There was no coolness after dark

unless on the grass. Roads, garden-paths, the house-fronts, the

barton-walls were warm as hearths, and reflected the noontime

temperature into the noctambulist's face.

He sat on the east gate of the dairy-yard, and knew not what to think

of himself. Feeling had indeed smothered judgement that day.

Since the sudden embrace, three hours before, the twain had kept

apart. She seemed stilled, almost alarmed, at what had occurred,

while the novelty, unpremeditation, mastery of circumstance

disquieted him--palpitating, contemplative being that he was. He

could hardly realize their true relations to each other as yet, and

what their mutual bearing should be before third parties

thenceforward.

Angel had come as pupil to this dairy in the idea that his temporary

existence here was to be the merest episode in his life, soon passed

through and early forgotten; he had come as to a place from which

as from a screened alcove he could calmly view the absorbing world

without, and, apostrophizing it with Walt Whitman--

Crowds of men and women attired in the usual costumes,

How curious you are to me!--

resolve upon a plan for plunging into that world anew. But behold,

the absorbing scene had been imported hither. What had been the

engrossing world had dissolved into an uninteresting outer dumb-show;

while here, in this apparently dim and unimpassioned place, novelty

had volcanically started up, as it had never, for him, started up

elsewhere.

Every window of the house being open, Clare could hear across the

yard each trivial sound of the retiring household. The dairy-house,

so humble, so insignificant, so purely to him a place of constrained

sojourn that he had never hitherto deemed it of sufficient importance

to be reconnoitred as an object of any quality whatever in the

landscape; what was it now? The aged and lichened brick gables

breathed forth "Stay!" The windows smiled, the door coaxed and

beckoned, the creeper blushed confederacy. A personality within

it was so far-reaching in her influence as to spread into and make

the bricks, mortar, and whole overhanging sky throb with a burning

sensibility. Whose was this mighty personality? A milkmaid's.

It was amazing, indeed, to find how great a matter the life of the

obscure dairy had become to him. And though new love was to be held

partly responsible for this, it was not solely so. Many besides

Angel have learnt that the magnitude of lives is not as to their

external displacements, but as to their subjective experiences. The

impressionable peasant leads a larger, fuller, more dramatic life

than the pachydermatous king. Looking at it thus, he found that life

was to be seen of the same magnitude here as elsewhere.

Despite his heterodoxy, faults, and weaknesses, Clare was a man with

a conscience. Tess was no insignificant creature to toy with and

dismiss; but a woman living her precious life--a life which, to

herself who endured or enjoyed it, possessed as great a dimension

as the life of the mightiest to himself. Upon her sensations

the whole world depended to Tess; through her existence all her

fellow-creatures existed, to her. The universe itself only came into

being for Tess on the particular day in the particular year in which

she was born.

This consciousness upon which he had intruded was the single

opportunity of existence ever vouchsafed to Tess by an unsympathetic

First Cause--her all; her every and only chance. How then should he

look upon her as of less consequence than himself; as a pretty trifle

to caress and grow weary of; and not deal in the greatest seriousness

with the affection which he knew that he had awakened in her--so

fervid and so impressionable as she was under her reserve--in order

that it might not agonize and wreck her?

To encounter her daily in the accustomed manner would be to develop

what had begun. Living in such close relations, to meet meant to

fall into endearment; flesh and blood could not resist it; and,

having arrived at no conclusion as to the issue of such a tendency,

he decided to hold aloof for the present from occupations in which

they would be mutually engaged. As yet the harm done was small.

But it was not easy to carry out the resolution never to approach

her. He was driven towards her by every heave of his pulse.

He thought he would go and see his friends. It might be possible

to sound them upon this. In less than five months his term here

would have ended, and after a few additional months spent upon other

farms he would be fully equipped in agricultural knowledge and in

a position to start on his own account. Would not a farmer want a

wife, and should a farmer's wife be a drawing-room wax-figure, or a

woman who understood farming? Notwithstanding the pleasing answer

returned to him by the silence, he resolved to go his journey.

One morning when they sat down to breakfast at Talbothays Dairy some

maid observed that she had not seen anything of Mr Clare that day.

"O no," said Dairyman Crick. "Mr Clare has gone hwome to Emminster

to spend a few days wi' his kinsfolk."

For four impassioned ones around that table the sunshine of the

morning went out at a stroke, and the birds muffled their song.

But neither girl by word or gesture revealed her blankness. "He's

getting on towards the end of his time wi' me," added the dairyman,

with a phlegm which unconsciously was brutal; "and so I suppose he

is beginning to see about his plans elsewhere."

"How much longer is he to bide here?" asked Izz Huett, the only

one of the gloom-stricken bevy who could trust her voice with the

question.

The others waited for the dairyman's answer as if their lives hung

upon it; Retty, with parted lips, gazing on the tablecloth, Marian

with heat added to her redness, Tess throbbing and looking out at

the meads.

"Well, I can't mind the exact day without looking at my

memorandum-book," replied Crick, with the same intolerable unconcern.

"And even that may be altered a bit. He'll bide to get a little

practice in the calving out at the straw-yard, for certain. He'll

hang on till the end of the year I should say."

Four months or so of torturing ecstasy in his society--of "pleasure

girdled about with pain". After that the blackness of unutterable

night.

At this moment of the morning Angel Clare was riding along a narrow

lane ten miles distant from the breakfasters, in the direction of

his father's Vicarage at Emminster, carrying, as well as he could,

a little basket which contained some black-puddings and a bottle of

mead, sent by Mrs Crick, with her kind respects, to his parents. The

white lane stretched before him, and his eyes were upon it; but they

were staring into next year, and not at the lane. He loved her;

ought he to marry her? Dared he to marry her? What would his mother

and his brothers say? What would he himself say a couple of years

after the event? That would depend upon whether the germs of staunch

comradeship underlay the temporary emotion, or whether it were a

sensuous joy in her form only, with no substratum of everlastingness.

His father's hill-surrounded little town, the Tudor church-tower of

red stone, the clump of trees near the Vicarage, came at last into

view beneath him, and he rode down towards the well-known gate.

Casting a glance in the direction of the church before entering his

home, he beheld standing by the vestry-door a group of girls, of

ages between twelve and sixteen, apparently awaiting the arrival of

some other one, who in a moment became visible; a figure somewhat

older than the school-girls, wearing a broad-brimmed hat and

highly-starched cambric morning-gown, with a couple of books in her

hand.

Clare knew her well. He could not be sure that she observed him; he

hoped she did not, so as to render it unnecessary that he should go

and speak to her, blameless creature that she was. An overpowering

reluctance to greet her made him decide that she had not seen him.

The young lady was Miss Mercy Chant, the only daughter of his

father's neighbour and friend, whom it was his parents' quiet hope

that he might wed some day. She was great at Antinomianism and

Bible-classes, and was plainly going to hold a class now. Clare's

mind flew to the impassioned, summer-steeped heathens in the Var

Vale, their rosy faces court-patched with cow-droppings; and to one

the most impassioned of them all.

It was on the impulse of the moment that he had resolved to trot

over to Emminster, and hence had not written to apprise his mother

and father, aiming, however, to arrive about the breakfast hour,

before they should have gone out to their parish duties. He was

a little late, and they had already sat down to the morning meal.

The group at the table jumped up to welcome him as soon as he

entered. They were his father and mother, his brother the Reverend

Felix--curate at a town in the adjoining county, home for the inside

of a fortnight--and his other brother, the Reverend Cuthbert, the

classical scholar, and Fellow and Dean of his College, down from

Cambridge for the long vacation. His mother appeared in a cap and

silver spectacles, and his father looked what in fact he was--an

earnest, God-fearing man, somewhat gaunt, in years about sixty-five,

his pale face lined with thought and purpose. Over their heads hung

the picture of Angel's sister, the eldest of the family, sixteen

years his senior, who had married a missionary and gone out to

Africa.

Old Mr Clare was a clergyman of a type which, within the last twenty

years, has well nigh dropped out of contemporary life. A spiritual

descendant in the direct line from Wycliff, Huss, Luther, Calvin; an

Evangelical of the Evangelicals, a Conversionist, a man of Apostolic

simplicity in life and thought, he had in his raw youth made up his

mind once for all in the deeper questions of existence, and admitted

no further reasoning on them thenceforward. He was regarded even by

those of his own date and school of thinking as extreme; while, on

the other hand, those totally opposed to him were unwillingly won

to admiration for his thoroughness, and for the remarkable power he

showed in dismissing all question as to principles in his energy for

applying them. He loved Paul of Tarsus, liked St John, hated St

James as much as he dared, and regarded with mixed feelings Timothy,

Titus, and Philemon. The New Testament was less a Christiad then a

Pauliad to his intelligence--less an argument than an intoxication.

His creed of determinism was such that it almost amounted to a

vice, and quite amounted, on its negative side, to a renunciative

philosophy which had cousinship with that of Schopenhauer and

Leopardi. He despised the Canons and Rubric, swore by the Articles,

and deemed himself consistent through the whole category--which in a

way he might have been. One thing he certainly was--sincere.

To the aesthetic, sensuous, pagan pleasure in natural life and lush

womanhood which his son Angel had lately been experiencing in Var

Vale, his temper would have been antipathetic in a high degree, had

he either by inquiry or imagination been able to apprehend it. Once

upon a time Angel had been so unlucky as to say to his father, in

a moment of irritation, that it might have resulted far better for

mankind if Greece had been the source of the religion of modern

civilization, and not Palestine; and his father's grief was of that

blank description which could not realize that there might lurk a

thousandth part of a truth, much less a half truth or a whole truth,

in such a proposition. He had simply preached austerely at Angel for

some time after. But the kindness of his heart was such that he

never resented anything for long, and welcomed his son to-day with a

smile which was as candidly sweet as a child's.

Angel sat down, and the place felt like home; yet he did not so much

as formerly feel himself one of the family gathered there. Every

time that he returned hither he was conscious of this divergence,

and since he had last shared in the Vicarage life it had grown even

more distinctly foreign to his own than usual. Its transcendental

aspirations--still unconsciously based on the geocentric view of

things, a zenithal paradise, a nadiral hell--were as foreign to his

own as if they had been the dreams of people on another planet.

Latterly he had seen only Life, felt only the great passionate pulse

of existence, unwarped, uncontorted, untrammelled by those creeds

which futilely attempt to check what wisdom would be content to

regulate.

On their part they saw a great difference in him, a growing

divergence from the Angel Clare of former times. It was chiefly a

difference in his manner that they noticed just now, particularly

his brothers. He was getting to behave like a farmer; he flung his

legs about; the muscles of his face had grown more expressive; his

eyes looked as much information as his tongue spoke, and more. The

manner of the scholar had nearly disappeared; still more the manner

of the drawing-room young man. A prig would have said that he had

lost culture, and a prude that he had become coarse. Such was the

contagion of domiciliary fellowship with the Talbothays nymphs and

swains.

After breakfast he walked with his two brothers, non-evangelical,

well-educated, hall-marked young men, correct to their remotest

fibre, such unimpeachable models as are turned out yearly by

the lathe of a systematic tuition. They were both somewhat

short-sighted, and when it was the custom to wear a single eyeglass

and string they wore a single eyeglass and string; when it was the

custom to wear a double glass they wore a double glass; when it was

the custom to wear spectacles they wore spectacles straightway, all

without reference to the particular variety of defect in their own

vision. When Wordsworth was enthroned they carried pocket copies;

and when Shelley was belittled they allowed him to grow dusty on

their shelves. When Correggio's Holy Families were admired, they

admired Correggio's Holy Families; when he was decried in favour

of Velasquez, they sedulously followed suit without any personal

objection.

If these two noticed Angel's growing social ineptness, he noticed

their growing mental limitations. Felix seemed to him all Church;

Cuthbert all College. His Diocesan Synod and Visitations were the

mainsprings of the world to the one; Cambridge to the other. Each

brother candidly recognized that there were a few unimportant score

of millions of outsiders in civilized society, persons who were

neither University men nor churchmen; but they were to be tolerated

rather than reckoned with and respected.

They were both dutiful and attentive sons, and were regular in their

visits to their parents. Felix, though an offshoot from a far more

recent point in the devolution of theology than his father, was less

self-sacrificing and disinterested. More tolerant than his father of

a contradictory opinion, in its aspect as a danger to its holder, he

was less ready than his father to pardon it as a slight to his own

teaching. Cuthbert was, upon the whole, the more liberal-minded,

though, with greater subtlety, he had not so much heart.

As they walked along the hillside Angel's former feeling revived

in him--that whatever their advantages by comparison with himself,

neither saw or set forth life as it really was lived. Perhaps, as

with many men, their opportunities of observation were not so good

as their opportunities of expression. Neither had an adequate

conception of the complicated forces at work outside the smooth and

gentle current in which they and their associates floated. Neither

saw the difference between local truth and universal truth; that what

the inner world said in their clerical and academic hearing was quite

a different thing from what the outer world was thinking.

"I suppose it is farming or nothing for you now, my dear fellow,"

Felix was saying, among other things, to his youngest brother, as

he looked through his spectacles at the distant fields with sad

austerity. "And, therefore, we must make the best of it. But I do

entreat you to endeavour to keep as much as possible in touch with

moral ideals. Farming, of course, means roughing it externally; but

high thinking may go with plain living, nevertheless."

"Of course it may," said Angel. "Was it not proved nineteen hundred

years ago--if I may trespass upon your domain a little? Why should

you think, Felix, that I am likely to drop my high thinking and my

moral ideals?"

"Well, I fancied, from the tone of your letters and our

conversation--it may be fancy only--that you were somehow losing

intellectual grasp. Hasn't it struck you, Cuthbert?"

"Now, Felix," said Angel drily, "we are very good friends, you

know; each of us treading our allotted circles; but if it comes to

intellectual grasp, I think you, as a contented dogmatist, had

better leave mine alone, and inquire what has become of yours."

They returned down the hill to dinner, which was fixed at any time at

which their father's and mother's morning work in the parish usually

concluded. Convenience as regarded afternoon callers was the last

thing to enter into the consideration of unselfish Mr and Mrs Clare;

though the three sons were sufficiently in unison on this matter to

wish that their parents would conform a little to modern notions.

The walk had made them hungry, Angel in particular, who was now

an outdoor man, accustomed to the profuse _dapes inemptae_ of the

dairyman's somewhat coarsely-laden table. But neither of the old

people had arrived, and it was not till the sons were almost tired of

waiting that their parents entered. The self-denying pair had been

occupied in coaxing the appetites of some of their sick parishioners,

whom they, somewhat inconsistently, tried to keep imprisoned in the

flesh, their own appetites being quite forgotten.

The family sat down to table, and a frugal meal of cold viands

was deposited before them. Angel looked round for Mrs Crick's

black-puddings, which he had directed to be nicely grilled as they

did them at the dairy, and of which he wished his father and mother

to appreciate the marvellous herbal savours as highly as he did

himself.

"Ah! you are looking for the black-puddings, my dear boy," observed

Clare's mother. "But I am sure you will not mind doing without them

as I am sure your father and I shall not, when you know the reason.

I suggested to him that we should take Mrs Crick's kind present to

the children of the man who can earn nothing just now because of his

attacks of delirium tremens; and he agreed that it would be a great

pleasure to them; so we did."

"Of course," said Angel cheerfully, looking round for the mead.

"I found the mead so extremely alcoholic," continued his mother,

"that it was quite unfit for use as a beverage, but as valuable

as rum or brandy in an emergency; so I have put it in my

medicine-closet."

"We never drink spirits at this table, on principle," added his

father.

"But what shall I tell the dairyman's wife?" said Angel.

"The truth, of course," said his father.

"I rather wanted to say we enjoyed the mead and the black-puddings

very much. She is a kind, jolly sort of body, and is sure to ask me

directly I return."

"You cannot, if we did not," Mr Clare answered lucidly.

"Ah--no; though that mead was a drop of pretty tipple."

"A what?" said Cuthbert and Felix both.

"Oh--'tis an expression they use down at Talbothays," replied Angel,

blushing. He felt that his parents were right in their practice if

wrong in their want of sentiment, and said no more.

XXVI

It was not till the evening, after family prayers, that Angel found

opportunity of broaching to his father one or two subjects near his

heart. He had strung himself up to the purpose while kneeling behind

his brothers on the carpet, studying the little nails in the heels of

their walking boots. When the service was over they went out of the

room with their mother, and Mr Clare and himself were left alone.

The young man first discussed with the elder his plans for the

attainment of his position as a farmer on an extensive scale--either

in England or in the Colonies. His father then told him that, as he

had not been put to the expense of sending Angel up to Cambridge, he

had felt it his duty to set by a sum of money every year towards the

purchase or lease of land for him some day, that he might not feel

himself unduly slighted.

"As far as worldly wealth goes," continued his father, "you will no

doubt stand far superior to your brothers in a few years."

This considerateness on old Mr Clare's part led Angel onward to the

other and dearer subject. He observed to his father that he was

then six-and-twenty, and that when he should start in the farming

business he would require eyes in the back of his head to see to all

matters--some one would be necessary to superintend the domestic

labours of his establishment whilst he was afield. Would it not be

well, therefore, for him to marry?

His father seemed to think this idea not unreasonable; and then Angel

put the question--

"What kind of wife do you think would be best for me as a thrifty

hard-working farmer?"

"A truly Christian woman, who will be a help and a comfort to you in

your goings-out and your comings-in. Beyond that, it really matters

little. Such an one can be found; indeed, my earnest-minded friend

and neighbour, Dr Chant--"

"But ought she not primarily to be able to milk cows, churn good

butter, make immense cheeses; know how to sit hens and turkeys and

rear chickens, to direct a field of labourers in an emergency, and

estimate the value of sheep and calves?"

"Yes; a farmer's wife; yes, certainly. It would be desirable." Mr

Clare, the elder, had plainly never thought of these points before.

"I was going to add," he said, "that for a pure and saintly woman you

will not find one more to your true advantage, and certainly not more

to your mother's mind and my own, than your friend Mercy, whom you

used to show a certain interest in. It is true that my neighbour

Chant's daughter had lately caught up the fashion of the younger

clergy round about us for decorating the Communion-table--altar, as I

was shocked to hear her call it one day--with flowers and other stuff

on festival occasions. But her father, who is quite as opposed to

such flummery as I, says that can be cured. It is a mere girlish

outbreak which, I am sure, will not be permanent."

"Yes, yes; Mercy is good and devout, I know. But, father, don't you

think that a young woman equally pure and virtuous as Miss Chant,

but one who, in place of that lady's ecclesiastical accomplishments,

understands the duties of farm life as well as a farmer himself,

would suit me infinitely better?"

His father persisted in his conviction that a knowledge of a farmer's

wife's duties came second to a Pauline view of humanity; and the

impulsive Angel, wishing to honour his father's feelings and to

advance the cause of his heart at the same time, grew specious.

He said that fate or Providence had thrown in his way a woman who

possessed every qualification to be the helpmate of an agriculturist,

and was decidedly of a serious turn of mind. He would not say

whether or not she had attached herself to the sound Low Church

School of his father; but she would probably be open to conviction

on that point; she was a regular church-goer of simple faith;

honest-hearted, receptive, intelligent, graceful to a degree, chaste

as a vestal, and, in personal appearance, exceptionally beautiful.

"Is she of a family such as you would care to marry into--a lady, in

short?" asked his startled mother, who had come softly into the study

during the conversation.

"She is not what in common parlance is called a lady," said Angel,

unflinchingly, "for she is a cottager's daughter, as I am proud to

say. But she IS a lady, nevertheless--in feeling and nature."

"Mercy Chant is of a very good family."

"Pooh!--what's the advantage of that, mother?" said Angel quickly.

"How is family to avail the wife of a man who has to rough it as I

have, and shall have to do?"

"Mercy is accomplished. And accomplishments have their charm,"

returned his mother, looking at him through her silver spectacles.

"As to external accomplishments, what will be the use of them in the

life I am going to lead?--while as to her reading, I can take that

in hand. She'll be apt pupil enough, as you would say if you knew

her. She's brim full of poetry--actualized poetry, if I may use the

expression. She LIVES what paper-poets only write... And she is an

unimpeachable Christian, I am sure; perhaps of the very tribe, genus,

and species you desire to propagate."

"O Angel, you are mocking!"

"Mother, I beg pardon. But as she really does attend Church almost

every Sunday morning, and is a good Christian girl, I am sure you

will tolerate any social shortcomings for the sake of that quality,

and feel that I may do worse than choose her." Angel waxed quite

earnest on that rather automatic orthodoxy in his beloved Tess which

(never dreaming that it might stand him in such good stead) he had

been prone to slight when observing it practised by her and the other

milkmaids, because of its obvious unreality amid beliefs essentially

naturalistic.

In their sad doubts as to whether their son had himself any right

whatever to the title he claimed for the unknown young woman, Mr and

Mrs Clare began to feel it as an advantage not to be overlooked that

she at least was sound in her views; especially as the conjunction of

the pair must have arisen by an act of Providence; for Angel never

would have made orthodoxy a condition of his choice. They said

finally that it was better not to act in a hurry, but that they would

not object to see her.

Angel therefore refrained from declaring more particulars now.

He felt that, single-minded and self-sacrificing as his parents

were, there yet existed certain latent prejudices of theirs, as

middle-class people, which it would require some tact to overcome.

For though legally at liberty to do as he chose, and though their

daughter-in-law's qualifications could make no practical difference

to their lives, in the probability of her living far away from them,

he wished for affection's sake not to wound their sentiment in the

most important decision of his life.

He observed his own inconsistencies in dwelling upon accidents in

Tess's life as if they were vital features. It was for herself that

he loved Tess; her soul, her heart, her substance--not for her skill

in the dairy, her aptness as his scholar, and certainly not for

her simple formal faith-professions. Her unsophisticated open-air

existence required no varnish of conventionality to make it palatable

to him. He held that education had as yet but little affected the

beats of emotion and impulse on which domestic happiness depends. It

was probable that, in the lapse of ages, improved systems of moral

and intellectual training would appreciably, perhaps considerably,

elevate the involuntary and even the unconscious instincts of human

nature; but up to the present day, culture, as far as he could see,

might be said to have affected only the mental epiderm of those

lives which had been brought under its influence. This belief was

confirmed by his experience of women, which, having latterly been

extended from the cultivated middle-class into the rural community,

had taught him how much less was the intrinsic difference between the

good and wise woman of one social stratum and the good and wise woman

of another social stratum, than between the good and bad, the wise

and the foolish, of the same stratum or class.

It was the morning of his departure. His brothers had already left

the Vicarage to proceed on a walking tour in the north, whence one

was to return to his college, and the other to his curacy. Angel

might have accompanied them, but preferred to rejoin his sweetheart

at Talbothays. He would have been an awkward member of the

party; for, though the most appreciative humanist, the most ideal

religionist, even the best-versed Christologist of the three, there

was alienation in the standing consciousness that his squareness

would not fit the round hole that had been prepared for him. To

neither Felix nor Cuthbert had he ventured to mention Tess.

His mother made him sandwiches, and his father accompanied him,

on his own mare, a little way along the road. Having fairly well

advanced his own affairs, Angel listened in a willing silence, as

they jogged on together through the shady lanes, to his father's

account of his parish difficulties, and the coldness of brother

clergymen whom he loved, because of his strict interpretations of

the New Testament by the light of what they deemed a pernicious

Calvinistic doctrine.

"Pernicious!" said Mr Clare, with genial scorn; and he proceeded to

recount experiences which would show the absurdity of that idea.

He told of wondrous conversions of evil livers of which he had been

the instrument, not only amongst the poor, but amongst the rich and

well-to-do; and he also candidly admitted many failures.

As an instance of the latter, he mentioned the case of a young

upstart squire named d'Urberville, living some forty miles off, in

the neighbourhood of Trantridge.

"Not one of the ancient d'Urbervilles of Kingsbere and other places?"

asked his son. "That curiously historic worn-out family with its

ghostly legend of the coach-and-four?"

"O no. The original d'Urbervilles decayed and disappeared sixty

or eighty years ago--at least, I believe so. This seems to be a

new family which had taken the name; for the credit of the former

knightly line I hope they are spurious, I'm sure. But it is odd

to hear you express interest in old families. I thought you set less

store by them even than I."

"You misapprehend me, father; you often do," said Angel with a

little impatience. "Politically I am sceptical as to the virtue of

their being old. Some of the wise even among themselves 'exclaim

against their own succession,' as Hamlet puts it; but lyrically,

dramatically, and even historically, I am tenderly attached to them."

This distinction, though by no means a subtle one, was yet too

subtle for Mr Clare the elder, and he went on with the story he had

been about to relate; which was that after the death of the senior

so-called d'Urberville, the young man developed the most culpable

passions, though he had a blind mother, whose condition should have

made him know better. A knowledge of his career having come to

the ears of Mr Clare, when he was in that part of the country

preaching missionary sermons, he boldly took occasion to speak to

the delinquent on his spiritual state. Though he was a stranger,

occupying another's pulpit, he had felt this to be his duty, and

took for his text the words from St Luke: "Thou fool, this night thy

soul shall be required of thee!" The young man much resented this

directness of attack, and in the war of words which followed when

they met he did not scruple publicly to insult Mr Clare, without

respect for his gray hairs.

Angel flushed with distress.

"Dear father," he said sadly, "I wish you would not expose yourself

to such gratuitous pain from scoundrels!"

"Pain?" said his father, his rugged face shining in the ardour of

self-abnegation. "The only pain to me was pain on his account, poor,

foolish young man. Do you suppose his incensed words could give

me any pain, or even his blows? 'Being reviled we bless; being

persecuted we suffer it; being defamed we entreat; we are made as the

filth of the world, and as the offscouring of all things unto this

day.' Those ancient and noble words to the Corinthians are strictly

true at this present hour."

"Not blows, father? He did not proceed to blows?"

"No, he did not. Though I have borne blows from men in a mad state

of intoxication."

"No!"

"A dozen times, my boy. What then? I have saved them from the guilt

of murdering their own flesh and blood thereby; and they have lived

to thank me, and praise God."

"May this young man do the same!" said Angel fervently. "But I fear

otherwise, from what you say."

"We'll hope, nevertheless," said Mr Clare. "And I continue to pray

for him, though on this side of the grave we shall probably never

meet again. But, after all, one of those poor words of mine may

spring up in his heart as a good seed some day."

Now, as always, Clare's father was sanguine as a child; and though

the younger could not accept his parent's narrow dogma, he revered

his practice and recognized the hero under the pietist. Perhaps he

revered his father's practice even more now than ever, seeing that,

in the question of making Tessy his wife, his father had not once

thought of inquiring whether she were well provided or penniless.

The same unworldliness was what had necessitated Angel's getting

a living as a farmer, and would probably keep his brothers in the

position of poor parsons for the term of their activities; yet Angel

admired it none the less. Indeed, despite his own heterodoxy, Angel

often felt that he was nearer to his father on the human side than

was either of his brethren.

XXVII

An up-hill and down-hill ride of twenty-odd miles through a garish

mid-day atmosphere brought him in the afternoon to a detached knoll

a mile or two west of Talbothays, whence he again looked into that

green trough of sappiness and humidity, the valley of the Var or

Froom. Immediately he began to descend from the upland to the fat

alluvial soil below, the atmosphere grew heavier; the languid perfume

of the summer fruits, the mists, the hay, the flowers, formed therein

a vast pool of odour which at this hour seemed to make the animals,

the very bees and butterflies drowsy. Clare was now so familiar with

the spot that he knew the individual cows by their names when, a long

distance off, he saw them dotted about the meads. It was with a

sense of luxury that he recognized his power of viewing life here

from its inner side, in a way that had been quite foreign to him in

his student-days; and, much as he loved his parents, he could not

help being aware that to come here, as now, after an experience of

home-life, affected him like throwing off splints and bandages; even

the one customary curb on the humours of English rural societies

being absent in this place, Talbothays having no resident landlord.

Not a human being was out of doors at the dairy. The denizens were

all enjoying the usual afternoon nap of an hour or so which the

exceedingly early hours kept in summer-time rendered a necessity.

At the door the wood-hooped pails, sodden and bleached by infinite

scrubbings, hung like hats on a stand upon the forked and peeled limb

of an oak fixed there for that purpose; all of them ready and dry

for the evening milking. Angel entered, and went through the silent

passages of the house to the back quarters, where he listened for a

moment. Sustained snores came from the cart-house, where some of

the men were lying down; the grunt and squeal of sweltering pigs

arose from the still further distance. The large-leaved rhubarb and

cabbage plants slept too, their broad limp surfaces hanging in the

sun like half-closed umbrellas.

He unbridled and fed his horse, and as he re-entered the house the

clock struck three. Three was the afternoon skimming-hour; and, with

the stroke, Clare heard the creaking of the floor-boards above, and

then the touch of a descending foot on the stairs. It was Tess's,

who in another moment came down before his eyes.

She had not heard him enter, and hardly realized his presence there.

She was yawning, and he saw the red interior of her mouth as if it

had been a snake's. She had stretched one arm so high above her

coiled-up cable of hair that he could see its satin delicacy above

the sunburn; her face was flushed with sleep, and her eyelids hung

heavy over their pupils. The brim-fulness of her nature breathed

from her. It was a moment when a woman's soul is more incarnate than

at any other time; when the most spiritual beauty bespeaks itself

flesh; and sex takes the outside place in the presentation.

Then those eyes flashed brightly through their filmy heaviness,

before the remainder of her face was well awake. With an oddly

compounded look of gladness, shyness, and surprise, she exclaimed--"O

Mr Clare! How you frightened me--I--"

There had not at first been time for her to think of the changed

relations which his declaration had introduced; but the full sense of

the matter rose up in her face when she encountered Clare's tender

look as he stepped forward to the bottom stair.

"Dear, darling Tessy!" he whispered, putting his arm round her, and

his face to her flushed cheek. "Don't, for Heaven's sake, Mister me

any more. I have hastened back so soon because of you!"

Tess's excitable heart beat against his by way of reply; and there

they stood upon the red-brick floor of the entry, the sun slanting in

by the window upon his back, as he held her tightly to his breast;

upon her inclining face, upon the blue veins of her temple, upon her

naked arm, and her neck, and into the depths of her hair. Having

been lying down in her clothes she was warm as a sunned cat. At

first she would not look straight up at him, but her eyes soon

lifted, and his plumbed the deepness of the ever-varying pupils, with

their radiating fibrils of blue, and black, and gray, and violet,

while she regarded him as Eve at her second waking might have

regarded Adam.

"I've got to go a-skimming," she pleaded, "and I have on'y old Deb to

help me to-day. Mrs Crick is gone to market with Mr Crick, and Retty

is not well, and the others are gone out somewhere, and won't be home

till milking."

As they retreated to the milk-house Deborah Fyander appeared on the

stairs.

"I have come back, Deborah," said Mr Clare, upwards. "So I can help

Tess with the skimming; and, as you are very tired, I am sure, you

needn't come down till milking-time."

Possibly the Talbothays milk was not very thoroughly skimmed that

afternoon. Tess was in a dream wherein familiar objects appeared

as having light and shade and position, but no particular outline.

Every time she held the skimmer under the pump to cool it for the

work her hand trembled, the ardour of his affection being so palpable

that she seemed to flinch under it like a plant in too burning a sun.

Then he pressed her again to his side, and when she had done running

her forefinger round the leads to cut off the cream-edge, he cleaned

it in nature's way; for the unconstrained manners of Talbothays dairy

came convenient now.

"I may as well say it now as later, dearest," he resumed gently. "I

wish to ask you something of a very practical nature, which I have

been thinking of ever since that day last week in the meads. I shall

soon want to marry, and, being a farmer, you see I shall require for

my wife a woman who knows all about the management of farms. Will

you be that woman, Tessy?"

He put it that way that she might not think he had yielded to an

impulse of which his head would disapprove.

She turned quite careworn. She had bowed to the inevitable result of

proximity, the necessity of loving him; but she had not calculated

upon this sudden corollary, which, indeed, Clare had put before her

without quite meaning himself to do it so soon. With pain that was

like the bitterness of dissolution she murmured the words of her

indispensable and sworn answer as an honourable woman.

"O Mr Clare--I cannot be your wife--I cannot be!"

The sound of her own decision seemed to break Tess's very heart, and

she bowed her face in her grief.

"But, Tess!" he said, amazed at her reply, and holding her still more

greedily close. "Do you say no? Surely you love me?"

"O yes, yes! And I would rather be yours than anybody's in the

world," returned the sweet and honest voice of the distressed girl.

"But I CANNOT marry you!"

"Tess," he said, holding her at arm's length, "you are engaged to

marry some one else!"

"No, no!"

"Then why do you refuse me?"

"I don't want to marry! I have not thought of doing it. I cannot!

I only want to love you."

"But why?"

Driven to subterfuge, she stammered--

"Your father is a parson, and your mother wouldn' like you to marry

such as me. She will want you to marry a lady."

"Nonsense--I have spoken to them both. That was partly why I went

home."

"I feel I cannot--never, never!" she echoed.

"Is it too sudden to be asked thus, my Pretty?"

"Yes--I did not expect it."

"If you will let it pass, please, Tessy, I will give you time," he

said. "It was very abrupt to come home and speak to you all at once.

I'll not allude to it again for a while."

She again took up the shining skimmer, held it beneath the pump, and

began anew. But she could not, as at other times, hit the exact

under-surface of the cream with the delicate dexterity required, try

as she might; sometimes she was cutting down into the milk, sometimes

in the air. She could hardly see, her eyes having filled with two

blurring tears drawn forth by a grief which, to this her best friend

and dear advocate, she could never explain.

"I can't skim--I can't!" she said, turning away from him.

Not to agitate and hinder her longer, the considerate Clare began

talking in a more general way:

You quite misapprehend my parents. They are the most simple-mannered

people alive, and quite unambitious. They are two of the few

remaining Evangelical school. Tessy, are you an Evangelical?"

"I don't know."

"You go to church very regularly, and our parson here is not very

High, they tell me."

Tess's ideas on the views of the parish clergyman, whom she heard

every week, seemed to be rather more vague than Clare's, who had

never heard him at all.

"I wish I could fix my mind on what I hear there more firmly than I

do," she remarked as a safe generality. "It is often a great sorrow

to me."

She spoke so unaffectedly that Angel was sure in his heart that his

father could not object to her on religious grounds, even though she

did not know whether her principles were High, Low or Broad. He

himself knew that, in reality, the confused beliefs which she held,

apparently imbibed in childhood, were, if anything, Tractarian as to

phraseology, and Pantheistic as to essence. Confused or otherwise,

to disturb them was his last desire:

Leave thou thy sister, when she prays,

Her early Heaven, her happy views;

Nor thou with shadow'd hint confuse

A life that leads melodious days.

He had occasionally thought the counsel less honest than musical; but

he gladly conformed to it now.

He spoke further of the incidents of his visit, of his father's mode

of life, of his zeal for his principles; she grew serener, and the

undulations disappeared from her skimming; as she finished one lead

after another he followed her, and drew the plugs for letting down

the milk.

"I fancied you looked a little downcast when you came in," she

ventured to observe, anxious to keep away from the subject of

herself.

"Yes--well, my father had been talking a good deal to me of his

troubles and difficulties, and the subject always tends to depress

me. He is so zealous that he gets many snubs and buffetings from

people of a different way of thinking from himself, and I don't

like to hear of such humiliations to a man of his age, the more

particularly as I don't think earnestness does any good when carried

so far. He has been telling me of a very unpleasant scene in

which he took part quite recently. He went as the deputy of some

missionary society to preach in the neighbourhood of Trantridge, a

place forty miles from here, and made it his business to expostulate

with a lax young cynic he met with somewhere about there--son of some

landowner up that way--and who has a mother afflicted with blindness.

My father addressed himself to the gentleman point-blank, and there

was quite a disturbance. It was very foolish of my father, I

must say, to intrude his conversation upon a stranger when the

probabilities were so obvious that it would be useless. But whatever

he thinks to be his duty, that he'll do, in season or out of season;

and, of course, he makes many enemies, not only among the absolutely

vicious, but among the easy-going, who hate being bothered. He says

he glories in what happened, and that good may be done indirectly;

but I wish he would not wear himself out now he is getting old, and

would leave such pigs to their wallowing."

Tess's look had grown hard and worn, and her ripe mouth tragical; but

she no longer showed any tremulousness. Clare's revived thoughts of

his father prevented his noticing her particularly; and so they went

on down the white row of liquid rectangles till they had finished

and drained them off, when the other maids returned, and took their

pails, and Deb came to scald out the leads for the new milk. As

Tess withdrew to go afield to the cows he said to her softly--

"And my question, Tessy?"

"O no--no!" replied she with grave hopelessness, as one who had

heard anew the turmoil of her own past in the allusion to Alec

d'Urberville. "It CAN'T be!"

She went out towards the mead, joining the other milkmaids with

a bound, as if trying to make the open air drive away her sad

constraint. All the girls drew onward to the spot where the cows

were grazing in the farther mead, the bevy advancing with the bold

grace of wild animals--the reckless, unchastened motion of women

accustomed to unlimited space--in which they abandoned themselves to

the air as a swimmer to the wave. It seemed natural enough to him

now that Tess was again in sight to choose a mate from unconstrained

Nature, and not from the abodes of Art.

XXVIII

Her refusal, though unexpected, did not permanently daunt Clare.

His experience of women was great enough for him to be aware that

the negative often meant nothing more than the preface to the

affirmative; and it was little enough for him not to know that in

the manner of the present negative there lay a great exception to

the dallyings of coyness. That she had already permitted him to

make love to her he read as an additional assurance, not fully

trowing that in the fields and pastures to "sigh gratis" is by no

means deemed waste; love-making being here more often accepted

inconsiderately and for its own sweet sake than in the carking,

anxious homes of the ambitious, where a girl's craving for an

establishment paralyzes her healthy thought of a passion as an end.

"Tess, why did you say 'no' in such a positive way?" he asked her in

the course of a few days.

She started.

"Don't ask me. I told you why--partly. I am not good enough--not

worthy enough."

"How? Not fine lady enough?"

"Yes--something like that," murmured she. "Your friends would scorn

me."

"Indeed, you mistake them--my father and mother. As for my brothers,

I don't care--" He clasped his fingers behind her back to keep her

from slipping away. "Now--you did not mean it, sweet?--I am sure you

did not! You have made me so restless that I cannot read, or play,

or do anything. I am in no hurry, Tess, but I want to know--to hear

from your own warm lips--that you will some day be mine--any time you

may choose; but some day?"

She could only shake her head and look away from him.

Clare regarded her attentively, conned the characters of her face as

if they had been hieroglyphics. The denial seemed real.

"Then I ought not to hold you in this way--ought I? I have no

right to you--no right to seek out where you are, or walk with you!

Honestly, Tess, do you love any other man?"

"How can you ask?" she said, with continued self-suppression.

"I almost know that you do not. But then, why do you repulse me?"

"I don't repulse you. I like you to--tell me you love me; and you

may always tell me so as you go about with me--and never offend me."

"But you will not accept me as a husband?"

"Ah--that's different--it is for your good, indeed, my dearest!

O, believe me, it is only for your sake! I don't like to give

myself the great happiness o' promising to be yours in that

way--because--because I am SURE I ought not to do it."

"But you will make me happy!"

"Ah--you think so, but you don't know!"

At such times as this, apprehending the grounds of her refusal to be

her modest sense of incompetence in matters social and polite, he

would say that she was wonderfully well-informed and versatile--which

was certainly true, her natural quickness and her admiration for him

having led her to pick up his vocabulary, his accent, and fragments

of his knowledge, to a surprising extent. After these tender

contests and her victory she would go away by herself under the

remotest cow, if at milking-time, or into the sedge or into her room,

if at a leisure interval, and mourn silently, not a minute after an

apparently phlegmatic negative.

The struggle was so fearful; her own heart was so strongly on the

side of his--two ardent hearts against one poor little conscience--

that she tried to fortify her resolution by every means in her power.

She had come to Talbothays with a made-up mind. On no account could

she agree to a step which might afterwards cause bitter rueing to her

husband for his blindness in wedding her. And she held that what her

conscience had decided for her when her mind was unbiassed ought not

to be overruled now.

"Why don't somebody tell him all about me?" she said. "It was only

forty miles off--why hasn't it reached here? Somebody must know!"

Yet nobody seemed to know; nobody told him.

For two or three days no more was said. She guessed from the sad

countenances of her chamber companions that they regarded her not

only as the favourite, but as the chosen; but they could see for

themselves that she did not put herself in his way.

Tess had never before known a time in which the thread of her life

was so distinctly twisted of two strands, positive pleasure and

positive pain. At the next cheese-making the pair were again left

alone together. The dairyman himself had been lending a hand; but

Mr Crick, as well as his wife, seemed latterly to have acquired a

suspicion of mutual interest between these two; though they walked

so circumspectly that suspicion was but of the faintest. Anyhow, the

dairyman left them to themselves.

They were breaking up the masses of curd before putting them into

the vats. The operation resembled the act of crumbling bread on a

large scale; and amid the immaculate whiteness of the curds Tess

Durbeyfield's hands showed themselves of the pinkness of the rose.

Angel, who was filling the vats with his handful, suddenly ceased,

and laid his hands flat upon hers. Her sleeves were rolled far above

the elbow, and bending lower he kissed the inside vein of her soft

arm.

Although the early September weather was sultry, her arm, from

her dabbling in the curds, was as cold and damp to his mouth as a

new-gathered mushroom, and tasted of the whey. But she was such

a sheaf of susceptibilities that her pulse was accelerated by the

touch, her blood driven to her finder-ends, and the cool arms

flushed hot. Then, as though her heart had said, "Is coyness longer

necessary? Truth is truth between man and woman, as between man and

man," she lifted her eyes and they beamed devotedly into his, as her

lip rose in a tender half-smile.

"Do you know why I did that, Tess?" he said.

"Because you love me very much!"

"Yes, and as a preliminary to a new entreaty."

"Not AGAIN!"

She looked a sudden fear that her resistance might break down under

her own desire.

"O, Tessy!" he went on, "I CANNOT think why you are so tantalizing.

Why do you disappoint me so? You seem almost like a coquette, upon

my life you do--a coquette of the first urban water! They blow

hot and blow cold, just as you do, and it is the very last sort of

thing to expect to find in a retreat like Talbothays. ... And yet,

dearest," he quickly added, observing now the remark had cut her, "I

know you to be the most honest, spotless creature that ever lived.

So how can I suppose you a flirt? Tess, why don't you like the idea

of being my wife, if you love me as you seem to do?"

"I have never said I don't like the idea, and I never could say it;

because--it isn't true!"

The stress now getting beyond endurance, her lip quivered, and she

was obliged to go away. Clare was so pained and perplexed that he

ran after and caught her in the passage.

"Tell me, tell me!" he said, passionately clasping her, in

forgetfulness of his curdy hands: "do tell me that you won't belong

to anybody but me!"

"I will, I will tell you!" she exclaimed. "And I will give you a

complete answer, if you will let me go now. I will tell you my

experiences--all about myself--all!"

"Your experiences, dear; yes, certainly; any number." He expressed

assent in loving satire, looking into her face. "My Tess, no doubt,

almost as many experiences as that wild convolvulus out there on the

garden hedge, that opened itself this morning for the first time.

Tell me anything, but don't use that wretched expression any more

about not being worthy of me."

"I will try--not! And I'll give you my reasons to-morrow--next

week."

"Say on Sunday?"

"Yes, on Sunday."

At last she got away, and did not stop in her retreat till she was in

the thicket of pollard willows at the lower side of the barton, where

she could be quite unseen. Here Tess flung herself down upon the

rustling undergrowth of spear-grass, as upon a bed, and remained

crouching in palpitating misery broken by momentary shoots of joy,

which her fears about the ending could not altogether suppress.

In reality, she was drifting into acquiescence. Every see-saw of her

breath, every wave of her blood, every pulse singing in her ears, was

a voice that joined with nature in revolt against her scrupulousness.

Reckless, inconsiderate acceptance of him; to close with him at the

altar, revealing nothing, and chancing discovery; to snatch ripe

pleasure before the iron teeth of pain could have time to shut upon

her: that was what love counselled; and in almost a terror of ecstasy

Tess divined that, despite her many months of lonely self-chastisement,

wrestlings, communings, schemes to lead a future of austere

isolation, love's counsel would prevail.

The afternoon advanced, and still she remained among the willows.

She heard the rattle of taking down the pails from the forked stands;

the "waow-waow!" which accompanied the getting together of the cows.

But she did not go to the milking. They would see her agitation;

and the dairyman, thinking the cause to be love alone, would

good-naturedly tease her; and that harassment could not be borne.

Her lover must have guessed her overwrought state, and invented some

excuse for her non-appearance, for no inquiries were made or calls

given. At half-past six the sun settled down upon the levels with

the aspect of a great forge in the heavens; and presently a monstrous

pumpkin-like moon arose on the other hand. The pollard willows,

tortured out of their natural shape by incessant choppings, became

spiny-haired monsters as they stood up against it. She went in and

upstairs without a light.

It was now Wednesday. Thursday came, and Angel looked thoughtfully

at her from a distance, but intruded in no way upon her. The indoor

milkmaids, Marian and the rest, seemed to guess that something

definite was afoot, for they did not force any remarks upon her in

the bedchamber. Friday passed; Saturday. To-morrow was the day.

"I shall give way--I shall say yes--I shall let myself marry

him--I cannot help it!" she jealously panted, with her hot face to

the pillow that night, on hearing one of the other girls sigh his

name in her sleep. "I can't bear to let anybody have him but me!

Yet it is a wrong to him, and may kill him when he knows! O my

heart--O--O--O!"

XXIX

"Now, who mid ye think I've heard news o' this morning?" said

Dairyman Crick, as he sat down to breakfast next day, with a riddling

gaze round upon the munching men and maids. "Now, just who mid ye

think?"

One guessed, and another guessed. Mrs Crick did not guess, because

she knew already.

"Well," said the dairyman, "'tis that slack-twisted 'hore's-bird of a

feller, Jack Dollop. He's lately got married to a widow-woman."

"Not Jack Dollop? A villain--to think o' that!" said a milker.

The name entered quickly into Tess Durbeyfield's consciousness, for

it was the name of the lover who had wronged his sweetheart, and had

afterwards been so roughly used by the young woman's mother in the

butter-churn.

"And had he married the valiant matron's daughter, as he promised?"

asked Angel Clare absently, as he turned over the newspaper he was

reading at the little table to which he was always banished by Mrs

Crick, in her sense of his gentility.

"Not he, sir. Never meant to," replied the dairyman. "As I say, 'tis

a widow-woman, and she had money, it seems--fifty poun' a year or so;

and that was all he was after. They were married in a great hurry;

and then she told him that by marrying she had lost her fifty poun'

a year. Just fancy the state o' my gentleman's mind at that news!

Never such a cat-and-dog life as they've been leading ever since!

Serves him well beright. But onluckily the poor woman gets the worst

o't."

"Well, the silly body should have told en sooner that the ghost of

her first man would trouble him," said Mrs Crick.

"Ay, ay," responded the dairyman indecisively. "Still, you can see

exactly how 'twas. She wanted a home, and didn't like to run the

risk of losing him. Don't ye think that was something like it,

maidens?"

He glanced towards the row of girls.

"She ought to ha' told him just before they went to church, when he

could hardly have backed out," exclaimed Marian.

"Yes, she ought," agreed Izz.

"She must have seen what he was after, and should ha' refused him,"

cried Retty spasmodically.

"And what do you say, my dear?" asked the dairyman of Tess.

"I think she ought--to have told him the true state of things--or

else refused him--I don't know," replied Tess, the bread-and-butter

choking her.

"Be cust if I'd have done either o't," said Beck Knibbs, a married

helper from one of the cottages. "All's fair in love and war. I'd

ha' married en just as she did, and if he'd said two words to me

about not telling him beforehand anything whatsomdever about my first

chap that I hadn't chose to tell, I'd ha' knocked him down wi' the

rolling-pin--a scram little feller like he! Any woman could do it."

The laughter which followed this sally was supplemented only by a

sorry smile, for form's sake, from Tess. What was comedy to them was

tragedy to her; and she could hardly bear their mirth. She soon rose

from table, and, with an impression that Clare would soon follow her,

went along a little wriggling path, now stepping to one side of the

irrigating channels, and now to the other, till she stood by the main

stream of the Var. Men had been cutting the water-weeds higher up

the river, and masses of them were floating past her--moving islands

of green crow-foot, whereon she might almost have ridden; long locks

of which weed had lodged against the piles driven to keep the cows

from crossing.

Yes, there was the pain of it. This question of a woman telling her

story--the heaviest of crosses to herself--seemed but amusement to

others. It was as if people should laugh at martyrdom.

"Tessy!" came from behind her, and Clare sprang across the gully,

alighting beside her feet. "My wife--soon!"

"No, no; I cannot. For your sake, O Mr Clare; for your sake, I say

no!"

"Tess!"

"Still I say no!" she repeated.

Not expecting this, he had put his arm lightly round her waist the

moment after speaking, beneath her hanging tail of hair. (The

younger dairymaids, including Tess, breakfasted with their hair loose

on Sunday mornings before building it up extra high for attending

church, a style they could not adopt when milking with their heads

against the cows.) If she had said "Yes" instead of "No" he

would have kissed her; it had evidently been his intention; but

her determined negative deterred his scrupulous heart. Their

condition of domiciliary comradeship put her, as the woman, to such

disadvantage by its enforced intercourse, that he felt it unfair to

her to exercise any pressure of blandishment which he might have

honestly employed had she been better able to avoid him. He released

her momentarily-imprisoned waist, and withheld the kiss.

It all turned on that release. What had given her strength to refuse

him this time was solely the tale of the widow told by the dairyman;

and that would have been overcome in another moment. But Angel said

no more; his face was perplexed; he went away.

Day after day they met--somewhat less constantly than before; and

thus two or three weeks went by. The end of September drew near, and

she could see in his eye that he might ask her again.

His plan of procedure was different now--as though he had made up

his mind that her negatives were, after all, only coyness and youth

startled by the novelty of the proposal. The fitful evasiveness of

her manner when the subject was under discussion countenanced the

idea. So he played a more coaxing game; and while never going beyond

words, or attempting the renewal of caresses, he did his utmost

orally.

In this way Clare persistently wooed her in undertones like that of

the purling milk--at the cow's side, at skimmings, at butter-makings,

at cheese-makings, among broody poultry, and among farrowing pigs--as

no milkmaid was ever wooed before by such a man.

Tess knew that she must break down. Neither a religious sense of a

certain moral validity in the previous union nor a conscientious wish

for candour could hold out against it much longer. She loved him so

passionately, and he was so godlike in her eyes; and being, though

untrained, instinctively refined, her nature cried for his tutelary

guidance. And thus, though Tess kept repeating to herself, "I can

never be his wife," the words were vain. A proof of her weakness lay

in the very utterance of what calm strength would not have taken the

trouble to formulate. Every sound of his voice beginning on the old

subject stirred her with a terrifying bliss, and she coveted the

recantation she feared.

His manner was--what man's is not?--so much that of one who would

love and cherish and defend her under any conditions, changes,

charges, or revelations, that her gloom lessened as she basked in it.

The season meanwhile was drawing onward to the equinox, and though

it was still fine, the days were much shorter. The dairy had again

worked by morning candlelight for a long time; and a fresh renewal

of Clare's pleading occurred one morning between three and four.

She had run up in her bedgown to his door to call him as usual;

then had gone back to dress and call the others; and in ten minutes

was walking to the head of the stairs with the candle in her

hand. At the same moment he came down his steps from above in his

shirt-sleeves and put his arm across the stairway.

"Now, Miss Flirt, before you go down," he said peremptorily. "It is a

fortnight since I spoke, and this won't do any longer. You MUST tell

me what you mean, or I shall have to leave this house. My door was

ajar just now, and I saw you. For your own safety I must go. You

don't know. Well? Is it to be yes at last?"

"I am only just up, Mr Clare, and it is too early to take me to

task!" she pouted. "You need not call me Flirt. 'Tis cruel and

untrue. Wait till by and by. Please wait till by and by! I will

really think seriously about it between now and then. Let me go

downstairs!"

She looked a little like what he said she was as, holding the candle

sideways, she tried to smile away the seriousness of her words.

"Call me Angel, then, and not Mr Clare."

"Angel."

"Angel dearest--why not?"

"'Twould mean that I agree, wouldn't it?"

"It would only mean that you love me, even if you cannot marry me;

and you were so good as to own that long ago."

"Very well, then, 'Angel dearest', if I MUST," she murmured, looking

at her candle, a roguish curl coming upon her mouth, notwithstanding

her suspense.

Clare had resolved never to kiss her until he had obtained her

promise; but somehow, as Tess stood there in her prettily tucked-up

milking gown, her hair carelessly heaped upon her head till there

should be leisure to arrange it when skimming and milking were done,

he broke his resolve, and brought his lips to her cheek for one

moment. She passed downstairs very quickly, never looking back at

him or saying another word. The other maids were already down,

and the subject was not pursued. Except Marian, they all looked

wistfully and suspiciously at the pair, in the sad yellow rays which

the morning candles emitted in contrast with the first cold signals

of the dawn without.

When skimming was done--which, as the milk diminished with the

approach of autumn, was a lessening process day by day--Retty and

the rest went out. The lovers followed them.

"Our tremulous lives are so different from theirs, are they not?" he

musingly observed to her, as he regarded the three figures tripping

before him through the frigid pallor of opening day.

"Not so very different, I think," she said.

"Why do you think that?"

"There are very few women's lives that are not--tremulous," Tess

replied, pausing over the new word as if it impressed her. "There's

more in those three than you think."

"What is in them?"

"Almost either of 'em," she began, "would make--perhaps would

make--a properer wife than I. And perhaps they love you as well

as I--almost."

"O, Tessy!"

There were signs that it was an exquisite relief to her to hear the

impatient exclamation, though she had resolved so intrepidly to let

generosity make one bid against herself. That was now done, and she

had not the power to attempt self-immolation a second time then.

They were joined by a milker from one of the cottages, and no more

was said on that which concerned them so deeply. But Tess knew that

this day would decide it.

In the afternoon several of the dairyman's household and assistants

went down to the meads as usual, a long way from the dairy, where

many of the cows were milked without being driven home. The

supply was getting less as the animals advanced in calf, and the

supernumerary milkers of the lush green season had been dismissed.

The work progressed leisurely. Each pailful was poured into tall

cans that stood in a large spring-waggon which had been brought

upon the scene; and when they were milked, the cows trailed away.

Dairyman Crick, who was there with the rest, his wrapper gleaming

miraculously white against a leaden evening sky, suddenly looked

at his heavy watch.

"Why, 'tis later than I thought," he said. "Begad! We shan't be

soon enough with this milk at the station, if we don't mind. There's

no time to-day to take it home and mix it with the bulk afore sending

off. It must go to station straight from here. Who'll drive it

across?"

Mr Clare volunteered to do so, though it was none of his business,

asking Tess to accompany him. The evening, though sunless, had

been warm and muggy for the season, and Tess had come out with

her milking-hood only, naked-armed and jacketless; certainly not

dressed for a drive. She therefore replied by glancing over her

scant habiliments; but Clare gently urged her. She assented by

relinquishing her pail and stool to the dairyman to take home, and

mounted the spring-waggon beside Clare.

XXX

In the diminishing daylight they went along the level roadway through

the meads, which stretched away into gray miles, and were backed in

the extreme edge of distance by the swarthy and abrupt slopes of

Egdon Heath. On its summit stood clumps and stretches of fir-trees,

whose notched tips appeared like battlemented towers crowning

black-fronted castles of enchantment.

They were so absorbed in the sense of being close to each other that

they did not begin talking for a long while, the silence being broken

only by the clucking of the milk in the tall cans behind them.

The lane they followed was so solitary that the hazel nuts had

remained on the boughs till they slipped from their shells, and the

blackberries hung in heavy clusters. Every now and then Angel would

fling the lash of his whip round one of these, pluck it off, and give

it to his companion.

The dull sky soon began to tell its meaning by sending down

herald-drops of rain, and the stagnant air of the day changed into

a fitful breeze which played about their faces. The quick-silvery

glaze on the rivers and pools vanished; from broad mirrors of light

they changed to lustreless sheets of lead, with a surface like a

rasp. But that spectacle did not affect her preoccupation. Her

countenance, a natural carnation slightly embrowned by the season,

had deepened its tinge with the beating of the rain-drops; and her

hair, which the pressure of the cows' flanks had, as usual, caused to

tumble down from its fastenings and stray beyond the curtain of her

calico bonnet, was made clammy by the moisture, till it hardly was

better than seaweed.

"I ought not to have come, I suppose," she murmured, looking at the

sky.

"I am sorry for the rain," said he. "But how glad I am to have you

here!"

Remote Egdon disappeared by degree behind the liquid gauze. The

evening grew darker, and the roads being crossed by gates, it was

not safe to drive faster than at a walking pace. The air was rather

chill.

"I am so afraid you will get cold, with nothing upon your arms and

shoulders," he said. "Creep close to me, and perhaps the drizzle

won't hurt you much. I should be sorrier still if I did not think

that the rain might be helping me."

She imperceptibly crept closer, and he wrapped round them both a

large piece of sail-cloth, which was sometimes used to keep the sun

off the milk-cans. Tess held it from slipping off him as well as

herself, Clare's hands being occupied.

"Now we are all right again. Ah--no we are not! It runs down into

my neck a little, and it must still more into yours. That's better.

Your arms are like wet marble, Tess. Wipe them in the cloth. Now,

if you stay quiet, you will not get another drop. Well, dear--about

that question of mine--that long-standing question?"

The only reply that he could hear for a little while was the smack of

the horse's hoofs on the moistening road, and the cluck of the milk

in the cans behind them.

"Do you remember what you said?"

"I do," she replied.

"Before we get home, mind."

"I'll try."

He said no more then. As they drove on, the fragment of an old manor

house of Caroline date rose against the sky, and was in due course

passed and left behind.

"That," he observed, to entertain her, "is an interesting old

place--one of the several seats which belonged to an ancient Norman

family formerly of great influence in this county, the d'Urbervilles.

I never pass one of their residences without thinking of them. There

is something very sad in the extinction of a family of renown, even

if it was fierce, domineering, feudal renown."

"Yes," said Tess.

They crept along towards a point in the expanse of shade just at hand

at which a feeble light was beginning to assert its presence, a spot

where, by day, a fitful white streak of steam at intervals upon the

dark green background denoted intermittent moments of contact between

their secluded world and modern life. Modern life stretched out its

steam feeler to this point three or four times a day, touched the

native existences, and quickly withdrew its feeler again, as if what

it touched had been uncongenial.

They reached the feeble light, which came from the smoky lamp of a

little railway station; a poor enough terrestrial star, yet in one

sense of more importance to Talbothays Dairy and mankind than the

celestial ones to which it stood in such humiliating contrast. The

cans of new milk were unladen in the rain, Tess getting a little

shelter from a neighbouring holly tree.

Then there was the hissing of a train, which drew up almost silently

upon the wet rails, and the milk was rapidly swung can by can into

the truck. The light of the engine flashed for a second upon Tess

Durbeyfield's figure, motionless under the great holly tree. No

object could have looked more foreign to the gleaming cranks and

wheels than this unsophisticated girl, with the round bare arms, the

rainy face and hair, the suspended attitude of a friendly leopard at

pause, the print gown of no date or fashion, and the cotton bonnet

drooping on her brow.

She mounted again beside her lover, with a mute obedience

characteristic of impassioned natures at times, and when they had

wrapped themselves up over head and ears in the sailcloth again, they

plunged back into the now thick night. Tess was so receptive that

the few minutes of contact with the whirl of material progress

lingered in her thought.

"Londoners will drink it at their breakfasts to-morrow, won't they?"

she asked. "Strange people that we have never seen."

"Yes--I suppose they will. Though not as we send it. When its

strength has been lowered, so that it may not get up into their

heads."

"Noble men and noble women, ambassadors and centurions, ladies and

tradeswomen, and babies who have never seen a cow."

"Well, yes; perhaps; particularly centurions."

"Who don't know anything of us, and where it comes from; or think how

we two drove miles across the moor to-night in the rain that it might

reach 'em in time?"

"We did not drive entirely on account of these precious Londoners; we

drove a little on our own--on account of that anxious matter which

you will, I am sure, set at rest, dear Tess. Now, permit me to put

it in this way. You belong to me already, you know; your heart, I

mean. Does it not?"

"You know as well as I. O yes--yes!"

"Then, if your heart does, why not your hand?"

"My only reason was on account of you--on account of a question. I

have something to tell you--"

"But suppose it to be entirely for my happiness, and my worldly

convenience also?"

"O yes; if it is for your happiness and worldly convenience. But my

life before I came here--I want--"

"Well, it is for my convenience as well as my happiness. If I have a

very large farm, either English or colonial, you will be invaluable

as a wife to me; better than a woman out of the largest mansion in

the country. So please--please, dear Tessy, disabuse your mind of

the feeling that you will stand in my way."

"But my history. I want you to know it--you must let me tell

you--you will not like me so well!"

"Tell it if you wish to, dearest. This precious history then. Yes,

I was born at so and so, Anno Domini--"

"I was born at Marlott," she said, catching at his words as a help,

lightly as they were spoken. "And I grew up there. And I was in the

Sixth Standard when I left school, and they said I had great aptness,

and should make a good teacher, so it was settled that I should

be one. But there was trouble in my family; father was not very

industrious, and he drank a little."

"Yes, yes. Poor child! Nothing new." He pressed her more closely

to his side.

"And then--there is something very unusual about it--about me. I--I

was--"

Tess's breath quickened.

"Yes, dearest. Never mind."

"I--I--am not a Durbeyfield, but a d'Urberville--a descendant of the

same family as those that owned the old house we passed. And--we are

all gone to nothing!"

"A d'Urberville!--Indeed! And is that all the trouble, dear Tess?"

"Yes," she answered faintly.

"Well--why should I love you less after knowing this?"

"I was told by the dairyman that you hated old families."

He laughed.

"Well, it is true, in one sense. I do hate the aristocratic

principle of blood before everything, and do think that as reasoners

the only pedigrees we ought to respect are those spiritual ones of

the wise and virtuous, without regard to corporal paternity. But

I am extremely interested in this news--you can have no idea how

interested I am! Are you not interested yourself in being one of

that well-known line?"

"No. I have thought it sad--especially since coming here, and

knowing that many of the hills and fields I see once belonged to

my father's people. But other hills and field belonged to Retty's

people, and perhaps others to Marian's, so that I don't value it

particularly."

"Yes--it is surprising how many of the present tillers of the soil

were once owners of it, and I sometimes wonder that a certain school

of politicians don't make capital of the circumstance; but they don't

seem to know it... I wonder that I did not see the resemblance of

your name to d'Urberville, and trace the manifest corruption. And

this was the carking secret!"

She had not told. At the last moment her courage had failed her;

she feared his blame for not telling him sooner; and her instinct

of self-preservation was stronger than her candour.

"Of course," continued the unwitting Clare, "I should have been glad

to know you to be descended exclusively from the long-suffering,

dumb, unrecorded rank and file of the English nation, and not from

the self-seeking few who made themselves powerful at the expense of

the rest. But I am corrupted away from that by my affection for you,

Tess (he laughed as he spoke), and made selfish likewise. For your

own sake I rejoice in your descent. Society is hopelessly snobbish,

and this fact of your extraction may make an appreciable difference

to its acceptance of you as my wife, after I have made you the

well-read woman that I mean to make you. My mother too, poor soul,

will think so much better of you on account of it. Tess, you must

spell your name correctly--d'Urberville--from this very day."

"I like the other way rather best."

"But you MUST, dearest! Good heavens, why dozens of mushroom

millionaires would jump at such a possession! By the bye, there's

one of that kidney who has taken the name--where have I heard of

him?--Up in the neighbourhood of The Chase, I think. Why, he is the

very man who had that rumpus with my father I told you of. What an

odd coincidence!"

"Angel, I think I would rather not take the name! It is unlucky,

perhaps!"

She was agitated.

"Now then, Mistress Teresa d'Urberville, I have you. Take my name,

and so you will escape yours! The secret is out, so why should you

any longer refuse me?"

"If it is SURE to make you happy to have me as your wife, and you

feel that you do wish to marry me, VERY, VERY much--"

"I do, dearest, of course!"

"I mean, that it is only your wanting me very much, and being hardly

able to keep alive without me, whatever my offences, that would make

me feel I ought to say I will."

"You will--you do say it, I know! You will be mine for ever and

ever."

He clasped her close and kissed her.

"Yes!"

She had no sooner said it than she burst into a dry hard sobbing, so

violent that it seemed to rend her. Tess was not a hysterical girl

by any means, and he was surprised.

"Why do you cry, dearest?"

"I can't tell--quite!--I am so glad to think--of being yours, and

making you happy!"

"But this does not seem very much like gladness, my Tessy!"

"I mean--I cry because I have broken down in my vow! I said I would

die unmarried!"

"But, if you love me you would like me to be your husband?"

"Yes, yes, yes! But O, I sometimes wish I had never been born!"

"Now, my dear Tess, if I did not know that you are very much excited,

and very inexperienced, I should say that remark was not very

complimentary. How came you to wish that if you care for me? Do you

care for me? I wish you would prove it in some way."

"How can I prove it more than I have done?" she cried, in a

distraction of tenderness. "Will this prove it more?"

She clasped his neck, and for the first time Clare learnt what an

impassioned woman's kisses were like upon the lips of one whom she

loved with all her heart and soul, as Tess loved him.

"There--now do you believe?" she asked, flushed, and wiping her eyes.

"Yes. I never really doubted--never, never!"

So they drove on through the gloom, forming one bundle inside the

sail-cloth, the horse going as he would, and the rain driving against

them. She had consented. She might as well have agreed at first.

The "appetite for joy" which pervades all creation, that tremendous

force which sways humanity to its purpose, as the tide sways the

helpless weed, was not to be controlled by vague lucubrations over

the social rubric.

"I must write to my mother," she said. "You don't mind my doing

that?"

"Of course not, dear child. You are a child to me, Tess, not to know

how very proper it is to write to your mother at such a time, and how

wrong it would be in me to object. Where does she live?"

"At the same place--Marlott. On the further side of Blackmoor Vale."

"Ah, then I HAVE seen you before this summer--"

"Yes; at that dance on the green; but you would not dance with me.

O, I hope that is of no ill-omen for us now!"

XXXI

Tess wrote a most touching and urgent letter to her mother the very

next day, and by the end of the week a response to her communication

arrived in Joan Durbeyfield's wandering last-century hand.

DEAR TESS,--

J write these few lines Hoping they will find you well,

as they leave me at Present, thank God for it. Dear

Tess, we are all glad to Hear that you are going really

to be married soon. But with respect to your question,

Tess, J say between ourselves, quite private but very

strong, that on no account do you say a word of your

Bygone Trouble to him. J did not tell everything

to your Father, he being so Proud on account of his

Respectability, which, perhaps, your Intended is

the same. Many a woman--some of the Highest in the

Land--have had a Trouble in their time; and why should

you Trumpet yours when others don't Trumpet theirs? No

girl would be such a Fool, specially as it is so long

ago, and not your Fault at all. J shall answer the

same if you ask me fifty times. Besides, you must bear

in mind that, knowing it to be your Childish Nature to

tell all that's in your heart--so simple!--J made you

promise me never to let it out by Word or Deed, having

your Welfare in my Mind; and you most solemnly did

promise it going from this Door. J have not named

either that Question or your coming marriage to your

Father, as he would blab it everywhere, poor Simple

Man.

Dear Tess, keep up your Spirits, and we mean to send

you a Hogshead of Cyder for you Wedding, knowing there

is not much in your parts, and thin Sour Stuff what

there is. So no more at present, and with kind love

to your Young Man.--From your affectte. Mother,

J. DURBEYFIELD

"O mother, mother!" murmured Tess.

She was recognizing how light was the touch of events the most

oppressive upon Mrs Durbeyfield's elastic spirit. Her mother did not

see life as Tess saw it. That haunting episode of bygone days was

to her mother but a passing accident. But perhaps her mother was

right as to the course to be followed, whatever she might be in her

reasons. Silence seemed, on the face of it, best for her adored

one's happiness: silence it should be.

Thus steadied by a command from the only person in the world who had

any shadow of right to control her action, Tess grew calmer. The

responsibility was shifted, and her heart was lighter than it had

been for weeks. The days of declining autumn which followed her

assent, beginning with the month of October, formed a season through

which she lived in spiritual altitudes more nearly approaching

ecstasy than any other period of her life.

There was hardly a touch of earth in her love for Clare. To her

sublime trustfulness he was all that goodness could be--knew all that

a guide, philosopher, and friend should know. She thought every line

in the contour of his person the perfection of masculine beauty, his

soul the soul of a saint, his intellect that of a seer. The wisdom

of her love for him, as love, sustained her dignity; she seemed to be

wearing a crown. The compassion of his love for her, as she saw it,

made her lift up her heart to him in devotion. He would sometimes

catch her large, worshipful eyes, that had no bottom to them looking

at him from their depths, as if she saw something immortal before

her.

She dismissed the past--trod upon it and put it out, as one treads on

a coal that is smouldering and dangerous.

She had not known that men could be so disinterested, chivalrous,

protective, in their love for women as he. Angel Clare was far from

all that she thought him in this respect; absurdly far, indeed;

but he was, in truth, more spiritual than animal; he had himself

well in hand, and was singularly free from grossness. Though not

cold-natured, he was rather bright than hot--less Byronic than

Shelleyan; could love desperately, but with a love more especially

inclined to the imaginative and ethereal; it was a fastidious emotion

which could jealously guard the loved one against his very self.

This amazed and enraptured Tess, whose slight experiences had been so

infelicitous till now; and in her reaction from indignation against

the male sex she swerved to excess of honour for Clare.

They unaffectedly sought each other's company; in her honest faith

she did not disguise her desire to be with him. The sum of her

instincts on this matter, if clearly stated, would have been that the

elusive quality of her sex which attracts men in general might be

distasteful to so perfect a man after an avowal of love, since it

must in its very nature carry with it a suspicion of art.

The country custom of unreserved comradeship out of doors during

betrothal was the only custom she knew, and to her it had no

strangeness; though it seemed oddly anticipative to Clare till he

saw how normal a thing she, in common with all the other dairy-folk,

regarded it. Thus, during this October month of wonderful afternoons

they roved along the meads by creeping paths which followed the

brinks of trickling tributary brooks, hopping across by little wooden

bridges to the other side, and back again. They were never out of

the sound of some purling weir, whose buzz accompanied their own

murmuring, while the beams of the sun, almost as horizontal as the

mead itself, formed a pollen of radiance over the landscape. They

saw tiny blue fogs in the shadows of trees and hedges, all the time

that there was bright sunshine elsewhere. The sun was so near the

ground, and the sward so flat, that the shadows of Clare and Tess

would stretch a quarter of a mile ahead of them, like two long

fingers pointing afar to where the green alluvial reaches abutted

against the sloping sides of the vale.

Men were at work here and there--for it was the season for "taking

up" the meadows, or digging the little waterways clear for the winter

irrigation, and mending their banks where trodden down by the cows.

The shovelfuls of loam, black as jet, brought there by the river

when it was as wide as the whole valley, were an essence of soils,

pounded champaigns of the past, steeped, refined, and subtilized to

extraordinary richness, out of which came all the fertility of the

mead, and of the cattle grazing there.

Clare hardily kept his arm round her waist in sight of these

watermen, with the air of a man who was accustomed to public

dalliance, though actually as shy as she who, with lips parted and

eyes askance on the labourers, wore the look of a wary animal the

while.

"You are not ashamed of owning me as yours before them!" she said

gladly.

"O no!"

"But if it should reach the ears of your friends at Emminster that

you are walking about like this with me, a milkmaid--"

"The most bewitching milkmaid ever seen."

"They might feel it a hurt to their dignity."

"My dear girl--a d'Urberville hurt the dignity of a Clare! It is a

grand card to play--that of your belonging to such a family, and I

am reserving it for a grand effect when we are married, and have

the proofs of your descent from Parson Tringham. Apart from that,

my future is to be totally foreign to my family--it will not affect

even the surface of their lives. We shall leave this part of

England--perhaps England itself--and what does it matter how people

regard us here? You will like going, will you not?"

She could answer no more than a bare affirmative, so great was the

emotion aroused in her at the thought of going through the world with

him as his own familiar friend. Her feelings almost filled her ears

like a babble of waves, and surged up to her eyes. She put her hand

in his, and thus they went on, to a place where the reflected sun

glared up from the river, under a bridge, with a molten-metallic glow

that dazzled their eyes, though the sun itself was hidden by the

bridge. They stood still, whereupon little furred and feathered

heads popped up from the smooth surface of the water; but, finding

that the disturbing presences had paused, and not passed by, they

disappeared again. Upon this river-brink they lingered till the fog

began to close round them--which was very early in the evening at

this time of the year--settling on the lashes of her eyes, where it

rested like crystals, and on his brows and hair.

They walked later on Sundays, when it was quite dark. Some of the

dairy-people, who were also out of doors on the first Sunday evening

after their engagement, heard her impulsive speeches, ecstasized to

fragments, though they were too far off to hear the words discoursed;

noted the spasmodic catch in her remarks, broken into syllables by

the leapings of her heart, as she walked leaning on his arm; her

contented pauses, the occasional little laugh upon which her soul

seemed to ride--the laugh of a woman in company with the man she

loves and has won from all other women--unlike anything else in

nature. They marked the buoyancy of her tread, like the skim of a

bird which has not quite alighted.

Her affection for him was now the breath and life of Tess's being;

it enveloped her as a photosphere, irradiated her into forgetfulness

of her past sorrows, keeping back the gloomy spectres that would

persist in their attempts to touch her--doubt, fear, moodiness, care,

shame. She knew that they were waiting like wolves just outside the

circumscribing light, but she had long spells of power to keep them

in hungry subjection there.

A spiritual forgetfulness co-existed with an intellectual

remembrance. She walked in brightness, but she knew that in the

background those shapes of darkness were always spread. They might

be receding, or they might be approaching, one or the other, a little

every day.

One evening Tess and Clare were obliged to sit indoors keeping house,

all the other occupants of the domicile being away. As they talked

she looked thoughtfully up at him, and met his two appreciative eyes.

"I am not worthy of you--no, I am not!" she burst out, jumping up

from her low stool as though appalled at his homage, and the fulness

of her own joy thereat.

Clare, deeming the whole basis of her excitement to be that which was

only the smaller part of it, said--

"I won't have you speak like it, dear Tess! Distinction does not

consist in the facile use of a contemptible set of conventions, but

in being numbered among those who are true, and honest, and just, and

pure, and lovely, and of good report--as you are, my Tess."

She struggled with the sob in her throat. How often had that string

of excellences made her young heart ache in church of late years, and

how strange that he should have cited them now.

"Why didn't you stay and love me when I--was sixteen; living with my

little sisters and brothers, and you danced on the green? O, why

didn't you, why didn't you!" she said, impetuously clasping her

hands.

Angel began to comfort and reassure her, thinking to himself, truly

enough, what a creature of moods she was, and how careful he would

have to be of her when she depended for her happiness entirely on

him.

"Ah--why didn't I stay!" he said. "That is just what I feel. If I

had only known! But you must not be so bitter in your regret--why

should you be?"

With the woman's instinct to hide she diverged hastily--

"I should have had four years more of your heart than I can ever have

now. Then I should not have wasted my time as I have done--I should

have had so much longer happiness!"

It was no mature woman with a long dark vista of intrigue behind her

who was tormented thus, but a girl of simple life, not yet one-and

twenty, who had been caught during her days of immaturity like a bird

in a springe. To calm herself the more completely, she rose from her

little stool and left the room, overturning the stool with her skirts

as she went.

He sat on by the cheerful firelight thrown from a bundle of green

ash-sticks laid across the dogs; the sticks snapped pleasantly, and

hissed out bubbles of sap from their ends. When she came back she

was herself again.

"Do you not think you are just a wee bit capricious, fitful, Tess?"

he said, good-humouredly, as he spread a cushion for her on the

stool, and seated himself in the settle beside her. "I wanted to

ask you something, and just then you ran away."

"Yes, perhaps I am capricious," she murmured. She suddenly

approached him, and put a hand upon each of his arms. "No, Angel,

I am not really so--by nature, I mean!" The more particularly to

assure him that she was not, she placed herself close to him in the

settle, and allowed her head to find a resting-place against Clare's

shoulder. "What did you want to ask me--I am sure I will answer it,"

she continued humbly.

"Well, you love me, and have agreed to marry me, and hence there

follows a thirdly, 'When shall the day be?'"

"I like living like this."

"But I must think of starting in business on my own hook with the

new year, or a little later. And before I get involved in the

multifarious details of my new position, I should like to have

secured my partner."

"But," she timidly answered, "to talk quite practically, wouldn't it

be best not to marry till after all that?--Though I can't bear the

thought o' your going away and leaving me here!"

"Of course you cannot--and it is not best in this case. I want you

to help me in many ways in making my start. When shall it be? Why

not a fortnight from now?"

"No," she said, becoming grave: "I have so many things to think of

first."

"But--"

He drew her gently nearer to him.

The reality of marriage was startling when it loomed so near. Before

discussion of the question had proceeded further there walked round

the corner of the settle into the full firelight of the apartment Mr

Dairyman Crick, Mrs Crick, and two of the milkmaids.

Tess sprang like an elastic ball from his side to her feet, while her

face flushed and her eyes shone in the firelight.

"I knew how it would be if I sat so close to him!" she cried, with

vexation. "I said to myself, they are sure to come and catch us!

But I wasn't really sitting on his knee, though it might ha' seemed

as if I was almost!"

"Well--if so be you hadn't told us, I am sure we shouldn't ha'

noticed that ye had been sitting anywhere at all in this light,"

replied the dairyman. He continued to his wife, with the stolid

mien of a man who understood nothing of the emotions relating to

matrimony--"Now, Christianer, that shows that folks should never

fancy other folks be supposing things when they bain't. O no, I

should never ha' thought a word of where she was a sitting to, if

she hadn't told me--not I."

"We are going to be married soon," said Clare, with improvised

phlegm.

"Ah--and be ye! Well, I am truly glad to hear it, sir. I've

thought you mid do such a thing for some time. She's too good for a

dairymaid--I said so the very first day I zid her--and a prize for

any man; and what's more, a wonderful woman for a gentleman-farmer's

wife; he won't be at the mercy of his baily wi' her at his side."

Somehow Tess disappeared. She had been even more struck with the

look of the girls who followed Crick than abashed by Crick's blunt

praise.

After supper, when she reached her bedroom, they were all present. A

light was burning, and each damsel was sitting up whitely in her bed,

awaiting Tess, the whole like a row of avenging ghosts.

But she saw in a few moments that there was no malice in their mood.

They could scarcely feel as a loss what they had never expected to

have. Their condition was objective, contemplative.

"He's going to marry her!" murmured Retty, never taking eyes off

Tess. "How her face do show it!"

"You BE going to marry him?" asked Marian.

"Yes," said Tess.

"When?"

"Some day."

They thought that this was evasiveness only.

"YES--going to MARRY him--a gentleman!" repeated Izz Huett.

And by a sort of fascination the three girls, one after another,

crept out of their beds, and came and stood barefooted round Tess.

Retty put her hands upon Tess's shoulders, as if to realize her

friend's corporeality after such a miracle, and the other two laid

their arms round her waist, all looking into her face.

"How it do seem! Almost more than I can think of!" said Izz Huett.

Marian kissed Tess. "Yes," she murmured as she withdrew her lips.

"Was that because of love for her, or because other lips have touched

there by now?" continued Izz drily to Marian.

"I wasn't thinking o' that," said Marian simply. "I was on'y feeling

all the strangeness o't--that she is to be his wife, and nobody else.

I don't say nay to it, nor either of us, because we did not think

of it--only loved him. Still, nobody else is to marry'n in the

world--no fine lady, nobody in silks and satins; but she who do live

like we."

"Are you sure you don't dislike me for it?" said Tess in a low voice.

They hung about her in their white nightgowns before replying, as if

they considered their answer might lie in her look.

"I don't know--I don't know," murmured Retty Priddle. "I want to

hate 'ee; but I cannot!"

"That's how I feel," echoed Izz and Marian. "I can't hate her.

Somehow she hinders me!"

"He ought to marry one of you," murmured Tess.

"Why?"

"You are all better than I."

"We better than you?" said the girls in a low, slow whisper. "No,

no, dear Tess!"

"You are!" she contradicted impetuously. And suddenly tearing away

from their clinging arms she burst into a hysterical fit of tears,

bowing herself on the chest of drawers and repeating incessantly,

"O yes, yes, yes!"

Having once given way she could not stop her weeping.

"He ought to have had one of you!" she cried. "I think I ought to

make him even now! You would be better for him than--I don't know

what I'm saying! O! O!"

They went up to her and clasped her round, but still her sobs tore

her.

"Get some water," said Marian, "She's upset by us, poor thing, poor

thing!"

They gently led her back to the side of her bed, where they kissed

her warmly.

"You are best for'n," said Marian. "More ladylike, and a better

scholar than we, especially since he had taught 'ee so much. But

even you ought to be proud. You BE proud, I'm sure!"

"Yes, I am," she said; "and I am ashamed at so breaking down."

When they were all in bed, and the light was out, Marian whispered

across to her--

"You will think of us when you be his wife, Tess, and of how we told

'ee that we loved him, and how we tried not to hate you, and did not

hate you, and could not hate you, because you were his choice, and

we never hoped to be chose by him."

They were not aware that, at these words, salt, stinging tears

trickled down upon Tess's pillow anew, and how she resolved, with a

bursting heart, to tell all her history to Angel Clare, despite her

mother's command--to let him for whom she lived and breathed despise

her if he would, and her mother regard her as a fool, rather then

preserve a silence which might be deemed a treachery to him, and

which somehow seemed a wrong to these.

XXXII

This penitential mood kept her from naming the wedding-day. The

beginning of November found its date still in abeyance, though he

asked her at the most tempting times. But Tess's desire seemed to be

for a perpetual betrothal in which everything should remain as it was

then.

The meads were changing now; but it was still warm enough in early

afternoons before milking to idle there awhile, and the state of

dairy-work at this time of year allowed a spare hour for idling.

Looking over the damp sod in the direction of the sun, a glistening

ripple of gossamer webs was visible to their eyes under the luminary,

like the track of moonlight on the sea. Gnats, knowing nothing

of their brief glorification, wandered across the shimmer of this

pathway, irradiated as if they bore fire within them, then passed out

of its line, and were quite extinct. In the presence of these things

he would remind her that the date was still the question.

Or he would ask her at night, when he accompanied her on some mission

invented by Mrs Crick to give him the opportunity. This was mostly a

journey to the farmhouse on the slopes above the vale, to inquire how

the advanced cows were getting on in the straw-barton to which they

were relegated. For it was a time of the year that brought great

changes to the world of kine. Batches of the animals were sent away

daily to this lying-in hospital, where they lived on straw till their

calves were born, after which event, and as soon as the calf could

walk, mother and offspring were driven back to the dairy. In the

interval which elapsed before the calves were sold there was, of

course, little milking to be done, but as soon as the calf had been

taken away the milkmaids would have to set to work as usual.

Returning from one of these dark walks they reached a great

gravel-cliff immediately over the levels, where they stood still and

listened. The water was now high in the streams, squirting through

the weirs, and tinkling under culverts; the smallest gullies were all

full; there was no taking short cuts anywhere, and foot-passengers

were compelled to follow the permanent ways. From the whole extent

of the invisible vale came a multitudinous intonation; it forced upon

their fancy that a great city lay below them, and that the murmur was

the vociferation of its populace.

"It seems like tens of thousands of them," said Tess; "holding

public-meetings in their market-places, arguing, preaching,

quarrelling, sobbing, groaning, praying, and cursing."

Clare was not particularly heeding.

"Did Crick speak to you to-day, dear, about his not wanting much

assistance during the winter months?"

"No."

"The cows are going dry rapidly."

"Yes. Six or seven went to the straw-barton yesterday, and three the

day before, making nearly twenty in the straw already. Ah--is it

that the farmer don't want my help for the calving? O, I am not

wanted here any more! And I have tried so hard to--"

"Crick didn't exactly say that he would no longer require you. But,

knowing what our relations were, he said in the most good-natured

and respectful manner possible that he supposed on my leaving at

Christmas I should take you with me, and on my asking what he would

do without you he merely observed that, as a matter of fact, it was a

time of year when he could do with a very little female help. I am

afraid I was sinner enough to feel rather glad that he was in this

way forcing your hand."

"I don't think you ought to have felt glad, Angel. Because 'tis

always mournful not to be wanted, even if at the same time 'tis

convenient."

"Well, it is convenient--you have admitted that." He put his finger

upon her cheek. "Ah!" he said.

"What?"

"I feel the red rising up at her having been caught! But why should

I trifle so! We will not trifle--life is too serious."

"It is. Perhaps I saw that before you did."

She was seeing it then. To decline to marry him after all--in

obedience to her emotion of last night--and leave the dairy, meant

to go to some strange place, not a dairy; for milkmaids were not in

request now calving-time was coming on; to go to some arable farm

where no divine being like Angel Clare was. She hated the thought,

and she hated more the thought of going home.

"So that, seriously, dearest Tess," he continued, "since you will

probably have to leave at Christmas, it is in every way desirable and

convenient that I should carry you off then as my property. Besides,

if you were not the most uncalculating girl in the world you would

know that we could not go on like this for ever."

"I wish we could. That it would always be summer and autumn, and you

always courting me, and always thinking as much of me as you have

done through the past summer-time!"

"I always shall."

"O, I know you will!" she cried, with a sudden fervour of faith

in him. "Angel, I will fix the day when I will become yours for

always!"

Thus at last it was arranged between them, during that dark walk

home, amid the myriads of liquid voices on the right and left.

When they reached the dairy Mr and Mrs Crick were promptly told--with

injunctions of secrecy; for each of the lovers was desirous that the

marriage should be kept as private as possible. The dairyman, though

he had thought of dismissing her soon, now made a great concern about

losing her. What should he do about his skimming? Who would make

the ornamental butter-pats for the Anglebury and Sandbourne ladies?

Mrs Crick congratulated Tess on the shilly-shallying having at last

come to an end, and said that directly she set eyes on Tess she

divined that she was to be the chosen one of somebody who was no

common outdoor man; Tess had looked so superior as she walked across

the barton on that afternoon of her arrival; that she was of a good

family she could have sworn. In point of fact Mrs Crick did remember

thinking that Tess was graceful and good-looking as she approached;

but the superiority might have been a growth of the imagination aided

by subsequent knowledge.

Tess was now carried along upon the wings of the hours, without the

sense of a will. The word had been given; the number of the day

written down. Her naturally bright intelligence had begun to admit

the fatalistic convictions common to field-folk and those who

associate more extensively with natural phenomena than with their

fellow-creatures; and she accordingly drifted into that passive

responsiveness to all things her lover suggested, characteristic of

the frame of mind.

But she wrote anew to her mother, ostensibly to notify the

wedding-day; really to again implore her advice. It was a gentleman

who had chosen her, which perhaps her mother had not sufficiently

considered. A post-nuptial explanation, which might be accepted with

a light heart by a rougher man, might not be received with the same

feeling by him. But this communication brought no reply from Mrs

Durbeyfield.

Despite Angel Clare's plausible representation to himself and to Tess

of the practical need for their immediate marriage, there was in

truth an element of precipitancy in the step, as became apparent at a

later date. He loved her dearly, though perhaps rather ideally and

fancifully than with the impassioned thoroughness of her feeling for

him. He had entertained no notion, when doomed as he had thought to

an unintellectual bucolic life, that such charms as he beheld in this

idyllic creature would be found behind the scenes. Unsophistication

was a thing to talk of; but he had not known how it really struck one

until he came here. Yet he was very far from seeing his future track

clearly, and it might be a year or two before he would be able to

consider himself fairly started in life. The secret lay in the tinge

of recklessness imparted to his career and character by the sense

that he had been made to miss his true destiny through the prejudices

of his family.

"Don't you think 'twould have been better for us to wait till you

were quite settled in your midland farm?" she once asked timidly.

(A midland farm was the idea just then.)

"To tell the truth, my Tess, I don't like you to be left anywhere

away from my protection and sympathy."

The reason was a good one, so far as it went. His influence over her

had been so marked that she had caught his manner and habits, his

speech and phrases, his likings and his aversions. And to leave her

in farmland would be to let her slip back again out of accord with

him. He wished to have her under his charge for another reason.

His parents had naturally desired to see her once at least before he

carried her off to a distant settlement, English or colonial; and

as no opinion of theirs was to be allowed to change his intention,

he judged that a couple of months' life with him in lodgings

whilst seeking for an advantageous opening would be of some social

assistance to her at what she might feel to be a trying ordeal--her

presentation to his mother at the Vicarage.

Next, he wished to see a little of the working of a flour-mill,

having an idea that he might combine the use of one with

corn-growing. The proprietor of a large old water-mill at

Wellbridge--once the mill of an Abbey--had offered him the inspection

of his time-honoured mode of procedure, and a hand in the operations

for a few days, whenever he should choose to come. Clare paid a

visit to the place, some few miles distant, one day at this time,

to inquire particulars, and returned to Talbothays in the evening.

She found him determined to spend a short time at the Wellbridge

flour-mills. And what had determined him? Less the opportunity of an

insight into grinding and bolting than the casual fact that lodgings

were to be obtained in that very farmhouse which, before its

mutilation, had been the mansion of a branch of the d'Urberville

family. This was always how Clare settled practical questions; by

a sentiment which had nothing to do with them. They decided to go

immediately after the wedding, and remain for a fortnight, instead

of journeying to towns and inns.

"Then we will start off to examine some farms on the other side of

London that I have heard of," he said, "and by March or April we will

pay a visit to my father and mother."

Questions of procedure such as these arose and passed, and the day,

the incredible day, on which she was to become his, loomed large in

the near future. The thirty-first of December, New Year's Eve, was

the date. His wife, she said to herself. Could it ever be? Their

two selves together, nothing to divide them, every incident shared

by them; why not? And yet why?

One Sunday morning Izz Huett returned from church, and spoke

privately to Tess.

"You was not called home this morning."

"What?"

"It should ha' been the first time of asking to-day," she answered,

looking quietly at Tess. "You meant to be married New Year's Eve,

deary?"

The other returned a quick affirmative.

"And there must be three times of asking. And now there be only two

Sundays left between."

Tess felt her cheek paling; Izz was right; of course there must be

three. Perhaps he had forgotten! If so, there must be a week's

postponement, and that was unlucky. How could she remind her lover?

She who had been so backward was suddenly fired with impatience and

alarm lest she should lose her dear prize.

A natural incident relieved her anxiety. Izz mentioned the omission

of the banns to Mrs Crick, and Mrs Crick assumed a matron's privilege

of speaking to Angel on the point.

"Have ye forgot 'em, Mr Clare? The banns, I mean."

"No, I have not forgot 'em," says Clare.

As soon as he caught Tess alone he assured her:

"Don't let them tease you about the banns. A licence will be quieter

for us, and I have decided on a licence without consulting you.

So if you go to church on Sunday morning you will not hear your own

name, if you wished to."

"I didn't wish to hear it, dearest," she said proudly.

But to know that things were in train was an immense relief to Tess

notwithstanding, who had well-nigh feared that somebody would stand

up and forbid the banns on the ground of her history. How events

were favouring her!

"I don't quite feel easy," she said to herself. "All this good

fortune may be scourged out of me afterwards by a lot of ill. That's

how Heaven mostly does. I wish I could have had common banns!"

But everything went smoothly. She wondered whether he would like her

to be married in her present best white frock, or if she ought to

buy a new one. The question was set at rest by his forethought,

disclosed by the arrival of some large packages addressed to her.

Inside them she found a whole stock of clothing, from bonnet to

shoes, including a perfect morning costume, such as would well suit

the simple wedding they planned. He entered the house shortly after

the arrival of the packages, and heard her upstairs undoing them.

A minute later she came down with a flush on her face and tears in

her eyes.

"How thoughtful you've been!" she murmured, her cheek upon his

shoulder. "Even to the gloves and handkerchief! My own love--how

good, how kind!"

"No, no, Tess; just an order to a tradeswoman in London--nothing

more."

And to divert her from thinking too highly of him, he told her to go

upstairs, and take her time, and see if it all fitted; and, if not,

to get the village sempstress to make a few alterations.

She did return upstairs, and put on the gown. Alone, she stood for a

moment before the glass looking at the effect of her silk attire; and

then there came into her head her mother's ballad of the mystic

robe--

That never would become that wife

That had once done amiss,

which Mrs Durbeyfield had used to sing to her as a child, so blithely

and so archly, her foot on the cradle, which she rocked to the tune.

Suppose this robe should betray her by changing colour, as her robe

had betrayed Queen Guinevere. Since she had been at the dairy she

had not once thought of the lines till now.

XXXIII

Angel felt that he would like to spend a day with her before the

wedding, somewhere away from the dairy, as a last jaunt in her

company while there were yet mere lover and mistress; a romantic day,

in circumstances that would never be repeated; with that other and

greater day beaming close ahead of them. During the preceding week,

therefore, he suggested making a few purchases in the nearest town,

and they started together.

Clare's life at the dairy had been that of a recluse in respect the

world of his own class. For months he had never gone near a town,

and, requiring no vehicle, had never kept one, hiring the dairyman's

cob or gig if he rode or drove. They went in the gig that day.

And then for the first time in their lives they shopped as partners

in one concern. It was Christmas Eve, with its loads a holly and

mistletoe, and the town was very full of strangers who had come in

from all parts of the country on account of the day. Tess paid the

penalty of walking about with happiness superadded to beauty on her

countenance by being much stared at as she moved amid them on his

arm.

In the evening they returned to the inn at which they had put up, and

Tess waited in the entry while Angel went to see the horse and gig

brought to the door. The general sitting-room was full of guests,

who were continually going in and out. As the door opened and shut

each time for the passage of these, the light within the parlour fell

full upon Tess's face. Two men came out and passed by her among the

rest. One of them had stared her up and down in surprise, and she

fancied he was a Trantridge man, though that village lay so many

miles off that Trantridge folk were rarities here.

"A comely maid that," said the other.

"True, comely enough. But unless I make a great mistake--" And he

negatived the remainder of the definition forthwith.

Clare had just returned from the stable-yard, and, confronting the

man on the threshold, heard the words, and saw the shrinking of

Tess. The insult to her stung him to the quick, and before he had

considered anything at all he struck the man on the chin with the

full force of his fist, sending him staggering backwards into the

passage.

The man recovered himself, and seemed inclined to come on, and Clare,

stepping outside the door, put himself in a posture of defence. But

his opponent began to think better of the matter. He looked anew at

Tess as he passed her, and said to Clare--

"I beg pardon, sir; 'twas a complete mistake. I thought she was

another woman, forty miles from here."

Clare, feeling then that he had been too hasty, and that he was,

moreover, to blame for leaving her standing in an inn-passage, did

what he usually did in such cases, gave the man five shillings to

plaster the blow; and thus they parted, bidding each other a pacific

good night. As soon as Clare had taken the reins from the ostler,

and the young couple had driven off, the two men went in the other

direction.

"And was it a mistake?" said the second one.

"Not a bit of it. But I didn't want to hurt the gentleman's

feelings--not I."

In the meantime the lovers were driving onward.

"Could we put off our wedding till a little later?" Tess asked in a

dry dull voice. "I mean if we wished?"

"No, my love. Calm yourself. Do you mean that the fellow may have

time to summon me for assault?" he asked good-humouredly.

"No--I only meant--if it should have to be put off."

What she meant was not very clear, and he directed her to dismiss

such fancies from her mind, which she obediently did as well as she

could. But she was grave, very grave, all the way home; till she

thought, "We shall go away, a very long distance, hundreds of miles

from these parts, and such as this can never happen again, and no

ghost of the past reach there."

They parted tenderly that night on the landing, and Clare ascended to

his attic. Tess sat up getting on with some little requisites, lest

the few remaining days should not afford sufficient time. While she

sat she heard a noise in Angel's room overhead, a sound of thumping

and struggling. Everybody else in the house was asleep, and in her

anxiety lest Clare should be ill she ran up and knocked at his door,

and asked him what was the matter.

"Oh, nothing, dear," he said from within. "I am so sorry I disturbed

you! But the reason is rather an amusing one: I fell asleep and

dreamt that I was fighting that fellow again who insulted you,

and the noise you heard was my pummelling away with my fists at

my portmanteau, which I pulled out to-day for packing. I am

occasionally liable to these freaks in my sleep. Go to bed and

think of it no more."

This was the last drachm required to turn the scale of her

indecision. Declare the past to him by word of mouth she could not;

but there was another way. She sat down and wrote on the four pages

of a note-sheet a succinct narrative of those events of three or four

years ago, put it into an envelope, and directed it to Clare. Then,

lest the flesh should again be weak, she crept upstairs without any

shoes and slipped the note under his door.

Her night was a broken one, as it well might be, and she listened for

the first faint noise overhead. It came, as usual; he descended, as

usual. She descended. He met her at the bottom of the stairs and

kissed her. Surely it was as warmly as ever!

He looked a little disturbed and worn, she thought. But he said not

a word to her about her revelation, even when they were alone. Could

he have had it? Unless he began the subject she felt that she could

say nothing. So the day passed, and it was evident that whatever

he thought he meant to keep to himself. Yet he was frank and

affectionate as before. Could it be that her doubts were childish?

that he forgave her; that he loved her for what she was, just as she

was, and smiled at her disquiet as at a foolish nightmare? Had he

really received her note? She glanced into his room, and could see

nothing of it. It might be that he forgave her. But even if he had

not received it she had a sudden enthusiastic trust that he surely

would forgive her.

Every morning and night he was the same, and thus New Year's Eve

broke--the wedding day.

The lovers did not rise at milking-time, having through the whole of

this last week of their sojourn at the dairy been accorded something

of the position of guests, Tess being honoured with a room of her

own. When they arrived downstairs at breakfast-time they were

surprised to see what effects had been produced in the large

kitchen for their glory since they had last beheld it. At some

unnatural hour of the morning the dairyman had caused the yawning

chimney-corner to be whitened, and the brick hearth reddened, and a

blazing yellow damask blower to be hung across the arch in place of

the old grimy blue cotton one with a black sprig pattern which had

formerly done duty there. This renovated aspect of what was the

focus indeed of the room on a full winter morning threw a smiling

demeanour over the whole apartment.

"I was determined to do summat in honour o't", said the dairyman.

"And as you wouldn't hear of my gieing a rattling good randy wi'

fiddles and bass-viols complete, as we should ha' done in old times,

this was all I could think o' as a noiseless thing."

Tess's friends lived so far off that none could conveniently have

been present at the ceremony, even had any been asked; but as a fact

nobody was invited from Marlott. As for Angel's family, he had

written and duly informed them of the time, and assured them that he

would be glad to see one at least of them there for the day if he

would like to come. His brothers had not replied at all, seeming

to be indignant with him; while his father and mother had written

a rather sad letter, deploring his precipitancy in rushing into

marriage, but making the best of the matter by saying that, though

a dairywoman was the last daughter-in-law they could have expected,

their son had arrived at an age which he might be supposed to be the

best judge.

This coolness in his relations distressed Clare less than it would

have done had he been without the grand card with which he meant to

surprise them ere long. To produce Tess, fresh from the dairy, as

a d'Urberville and a lady, he had felt to be temerarious and risky;

hence he had concealed her lineage till such time as, familiarized

with worldly ways by a few months' travel and reading with him, he

could take her on a visit to his parents and impart the knowledge

while triumphantly producing her as worthy of such an ancient line.

It was a pretty lover's dream, if no more. Perhaps Tess's lineage

had more value for himself than for anybody in the world beside.

Her perception that Angel's bearing towards her still remained in no

whit altered by her own communication rendered Tess guiltily doubtful

if he could have received it. She rose from breakfast before he had

finished, and hastened upstairs. It had occurred to her to look once

more into the queer gaunt room which had been Clare's den, or rather

eyrie, for so long, and climbing the ladder she stood at the open

door of the apartment, regarding and pondering. She stooped to the

threshold of the doorway, where she had pushed in the note two or

three days earlier in such excitement. The carpet reached close to

the sill, and under the edge of the carpet she discerned the faint

white margin of the envelope containing her letter to him, which he

obviously had never seen, owing to her having in her haste thrust it

beneath the carpet as well as beneath the door.

With a feeling of faintness she withdrew the letter. There it

was--sealed up, just as it had left her hands. The mountain had

not yet been removed. She could not let him read it now, the house

being in full bustle of preparation; and descending to her own room

she destroyed the letter there.

She was so pale when he saw her again that he felt quite anxious.

The incident of the misplaced letter she had jumped at as if it

prevented a confession; but she knew in her conscience that it need

not; there was still time. Yet everything was in a stir; there

was coming and going; all had to dress, the dairyman and Mrs Crick

having been asked to accompany them as witnesses; and reflection or

deliberate talk was well-nigh impossible. The only minute Tess could

get to be alone with Clare was when they met upon the landing.

"I am so anxious to talk to you--I want to confess all my faults and

blunders!" she said with attempted lightness.

"No, no--we can't have faults talked of--you must be deemed perfect

to-day at least, my Sweet!" he cried. "We shall have plenty of time,

hereafter, I hope, to talk over our failings. I will confess mine at

the same time."

"But it would be better for me to do it now, I think, so that you

could not say--"

"Well, my quixotic one, you shall tell me anything--say, as soon as

we are settled in our lodging; not now. I, too, will tell you my

faults then. But do not let us spoil the day with them; they will

be excellent matter for a dull time."

"Then you don't wish me to, dearest?"

"I do not, Tessy, really."

The hurry of dressing and starting left no time for more than this.

Those words of his seemed to reassure her on further reflection.

She was whirled onward through the next couple of critical hours by

the mastering tide of her devotion to him, which closed up further

meditation. Her one desire, so long resisted, to make herself his,

to call him her lord, her own--then, if necessary, to die--had

at last lifted her up from her plodding reflective pathway. In

dressing, she moved about in a mental cloud of many-coloured

idealities, which eclipsed all sinister contingencies by its

brightness.

The church was a long way off, and they were obliged to drive,

particularly as it was winter. A closed carriage was ordered from

a roadside inn, a vehicle which had been kept there ever since the

old days of post-chaise travelling. It had stout wheel-spokes, and

heavy felloes a great curved bed, immense straps and springs, and a

pole like a battering-ram. The postilion was a venerable "boy" of

sixty--a martyr to rheumatic gout, the result of excessive exposure

in youth, counter-acted by strong liquors--who had stood at inn-doors

doing nothing for the whole five-and-twenty years that had elapsed

since he had no longer been required to ride professionally, as if

expecting the old times to come back again. He had a permanent

running wound on the outside of his right leg, originated by the

constant bruisings of aristocratic carriage-poles during the many

years that he had been in regular employ at the King's Arms,

Casterbridge.

Inside this cumbrous and creaking structure, and behind this decayed

conductor, the _partie carre_ took their seats--the bride and

bridegroom and Mr and Mrs Crick. Angel would have liked one at least

of his brothers to be present as groomsman, but their silence after

his gentle hint to that effect by letter had signified that they did

not care to come. They disapproved of the marriage, and could not be

expected to countenance it. Perhaps it was as well that they could

not be present. They were not worldly young fellows, but fraternizing

with dairy-folk would have struck unpleasantly upon their biased

niceness, apart from their views of the match.

Upheld by the momentum of the time, Tess knew nothing of this, did

not see anything, did not know the road they were taking to the

church. She knew that Angel was close to her; all the rest was

a luminous mist. She was a sort of celestial person, who owed

her being to poetry--one of those classical divinities Clare was

accustomed to talk to her about when they took their walks together.

The marriage being by licence there were only a dozen or so of people

in the church; had there been a thousand they would have produced

no more effect upon her. They were at stellar distances from her

present world. In the ecstatic solemnity with which she swore her

faith to him the ordinary sensibilities of sex seemed a flippancy.

At a pause in the service, while they were kneeling together, she

unconsciously inclined herself towards him, so that her shoulder

touched his arm; she had been frightened by a passing thought, and

the movement had been automatic, to assure herself that he was really

there, and to fortify her belief that his fidelity would be proof

against all things.

Clare knew that she loved him--every curve of her form showed that--

but he did not know at that time the full depth of her devotion, its

single-mindedness, its meekness; what long-suffering it guaranteed,

what honesty, what endurance, what good faith.

As they came out of church the ringers swung the bells off their

rests, and a modest peal of three notes broke forth--that limited

amount of expression having been deemed sufficient by the church

builders for the joys of such a small parish. Passing by the tower

with her husband on the path to the gate she could feel the vibrant

air humming round them from the louvred belfry in the circle of

sound, and it matched the highly-charged mental atmosphere in which

she was living.

This condition of mind, wherein she felt glorified by an irradiation

not her own, like the angel whom St John saw in the sun, lasted till

the sound of the church bells had died away, and the emotions of the

wedding-service had calmed down. Her eyes could dwell upon details

more clearly now, and Mr and Mrs Crick having directed their own gig

to be sent for them, to leave the carriage to the young couple, she

observed the build and character of that conveyance for the first

time. Sitting in silence she regarded it long.

"I fancy you seem oppressed, Tessy," said Clare.

"Yes," she answered, putting her hand to her brow. "I tremble at

many things. It is all so serious, Angel. Among other things I seem

to have seen this carriage before, to be very well acquainted with

it. It is very odd--I must have seen it in a dream."

"Oh--you have heard the legend of the d'Urberville Coach--that

well-known superstition of this county about your family when they

were very popular here; and this lumbering old thing reminds you of

it."

"I have never heard of it to my knowledge," said she. "What is the

legend--may I know it?"

"Well--I would rather not tell it in detail just now. A certain

d'Urberville of the sixteenth or seventeenth century committed a

dreadful crime in his family coach; and since that time members of

the family see or hear the old coach whenever--But I'll tell you

another day--it is rather gloomy. Evidently some dim knowledge of

it has been brought back to your mind by the sight of this venerable

caravan."

"I don't remember hearing it before," she murmured. "Is it when we

are going to die, Angel, that members of my family see it, or is it

when we have committed a crime?"

"Now, Tess!"

He silenced her by a kiss.

By the time they reached home she was contrite and spiritless. She

was Mrs Angel Clare, indeed, but had she any moral right to the name?

Was she not more truly Mrs Alexander d'Urberville? Could intensity

of love justify what might be considered in upright souls as culpable

reticence? She knew not what was expected of women in such cases;

and she had no counsellor.

However, when she found herself alone in her room for a few

minutes--the last day this on which she was ever to enter it--she

knelt down and prayed. She tried to pray to God, but it was her

husband who really had her supplication. Her idolatry of this man

was such that she herself almost feared it to be ill-omened. She was

conscious of the notion expressed by Friar Laurence: "These violent

delights have violent ends." It might be too desperate for human

conditions--too rank, to wild, too deadly.

"O my love, why do I love you so!" she whispered there alone; "for

she you love is not my real self, but one in my image; the one I

might have been!"

Afternoon came, and with it the hour for departure. They had decided

to fulfil the plan of going for a few days to the lodgings in the old

farmhouse near Wellbridge Mill, at which he meant to reside during

his investigation of flour processes. At two o'clock there was

nothing left to do but to start. All the servantry of the dairy were

standing in the red-brick entry to see them go out, the dairyman and

his wife following to the door. Tess saw her three chamber-mates

in a row against the wall, pensively inclining their heads. She

had much questioned if they would appear at the parting moment; but

there they were, stoical and staunch to the last. She knew why the

delicate Retty looked so fragile, and Izz so tragically sorrowful,

and Marian so blank; and she forgot her own dogging shadow for a

moment in contemplating theirs.

She impulsively whispered to him--

"Will you kiss 'em all, once, poor things, for the first and last

time?"

Clare had not the least objection to such a farewell formality--which

was all that it was to him--and as he passed them he kissed them in

succession where they stood, saying "Goodbye" to each as he did so.

When they reached the door Tess femininely glanced back to discern

the effect of that kiss of charity; there was no triumph in her

glance, as there might have been. If there had it would have

disappeared when she saw how moved the girls all were. The kiss had

obviously done harm by awakening feelings they were trying to subdue.

Of all this Clare was unconscious. Passing on to the wicket-gate he

shook hands with the dairyman and his wife, and expressed his last

thanks to them for their attentions; after which there was a moment

of silence before they had moved off. It was interrupted by the

crowing of a cock. The white one with the rose comb had come and

settled on the palings in front of the house, within a few yards of

them, and his notes thrilled their ears through, dwindling away like

echoes down a valley of rocks.

"Oh?" said Mrs Crick. "An afternoon crow!"

Two men were standing by the yard gate, holding it open.

"That's bad," one murmured to the other, not thinking that the words

could be heard by the group at the door-wicket.

The cock crew again--straight towards Clare.

"Well!" said the dairyman.

"I don't like to hear him!" said Tess to her husband. "Tell the man

to drive on. Goodbye, goodbye!"

The cock crew again.

"Hoosh! Just you be off, sir, or I'll twist your neck!" said the

dairyman with some irritation, turning to the bird and driving him

away. And to his wife as they went indoors: "Now, to think o' that

just to-day! I've not heard his crow of an afternoon all the year

afore."

"It only means a change in the weather," said she; "not what you

think: 'tis impossible!"

XXXIV

They drove by the level road along the valley to a distance of a few

miles, and, reaching Wellbridge, turned away from the village to the

left, and over the great Elizabethan bridge which gives the place

half its name. Immediately behind it stood the house wherein they

had engaged lodgings, whose exterior features are so well known to

all travellers through the Froom Valley; once portion of a fine

manorial residence, and the property and seat of a d'Urberville, but

since its partial demolition a farmhouse.

"Welcome to one of your ancestral mansions!" said Clare as he handed

her down. But he regretted the pleasantry; it was too near a satire.

On entering they found that, though they had only engaged a couple

of rooms, the farmer had taken advantage of their proposed presence

during the coming days to pay a New Year's visit to some friends,

leaving a woman from a neighbouring cottage to minister to their

few wants. The absoluteness of possession pleased them, and they

realized it as the first moment of their experience under their own

exclusive roof-tree.

But he found that the mouldy old habitation somewhat depressed his

bride. When the carriage was gone they ascended the stairs to wash

their hands, the charwoman showing the way. On the landing Tess

stopped and started.

"What's the matter?" said he.

"Those horrid women!" she answered with a smile. "How they

frightened me."

He looked up, and perceived two life-size portraits on panels built

into the masonry. As all visitors to the mansion are aware, these

paintings represent women of middle age, of a date some two hundred

years ago, whose lineaments once seen can never be forgotten.

The long pointed features, narrow eye, and smirk of the one, so

suggestive of merciless treachery; the bill-hook nose, large

teeth, and bold eye of the other suggesting arrogance to the point

of ferocity, haunt the beholder afterwards in his dreams.

"Whose portraits are those?" asked Clare of the charwoman.

"I have been told by old folk that they were ladies of the

d'Urberville family, the ancient lords of this manor," she said,

"Owing to their being builded into the wall they can't be moved

away."

The unpleasantness of the matter was that, in addition to their

effect upon Tess, her fine features were unquestionably traceable

in these exaggerated forms. He said nothing of this, however, and,

regretting that he had gone out of his way to choose the house for

their bridal time, went on into the adjoining room. The place having

been rather hastily prepared for them, they washed their hands in one

basin. Clare touched hers under the water.

"Which are my fingers and which are yours?" he said, looking up.

"They are very much mixed."

"They are all yours," said she, very prettily, and endeavoured

to be gayer than she was. He had not been displeased with her

thoughtfulness on such an occasion; it was what every sensible woman

would show: but Tess knew that she had been thoughtful to excess,

and struggled against it.

The sun was so low on that short last afternoon of the year that it

shone in through a small opening and formed a golden staff which

stretched across to her skirt, where it made a spot like a paint-mark

set upon her. They went into the ancient parlour to tea, and

here they shared their first common meal alone. Such was their

childishness, or rather his, that he found it interesting to use the

same bread-and-butter plate as herself, and to brush crumbs from her

lips with his own. He wondered a little that she did not enter into

these frivolities with his own zest.

Looking at her silently for a long time; "She is a dear dear Tess,"

he thought to himself, as one deciding on the true construction of

a difficult passage. "Do I realize solemnly enough how utterly and

irretrievably this little womanly thing is the creature of my good

or bad faith and fortune? I think not. I think I could not, unless

I were a woman myself. What I am in worldly estate, she is. What I

become, she must become. What I cannot be, she cannot be. And shall

I ever neglect her, or hurt her, or even forget to consider her? God

forbid such a crime!"

They sat on over the tea-table waiting for their luggage, which the

dairyman had promised to send before it grew dark. But evening began

to close in, and the luggage did not arrive, and they had brought

nothing more than they stood in. With the departure of the sun the

calm mood of the winter day changed. Out of doors there began noises

as of silk smartly rubbed; the restful dead leaves of the preceding

autumn were stirred to irritated resurrection, and whirled about

unwillingly, and tapped against the shutters. It soon began to rain.

"That cock knew the weather was going to change," said Clare.

The woman who had attended upon them had gone home for the night, but

she had placed candles upon the table, and now they lit them. Each

candle-flame drew towards the fireplace.

"These old houses are so draughty," continued Angel, looking at the

flames, and at the grease guttering down the sides. "I wonder where

that luggage is. We haven't even a brush and comb."

"I don't know," she answered, absent-minded.

"Tess, you are not a bit cheerful this evening--not at all as you

used to be. Those harridans on the panels upstairs have unsettled

you. I am sorry I brought you here. I wonder if you really love me,

after all?"

He knew that she did, and the words had no serious intent; but she

was surcharged with emotion, and winced like a wounded animal.

Though she tried not to shed tears, she could not help showing one

or two.

"I did not mean it!" said he, sorry. "You are worried at not having

your things, I know. I cannot think why old Jonathan has not come

with them. Why, it is seven o'clock? Ah, there he is!"

A knock had come to the door, and, there being nobody else to answer

it, Clare went out. He returned to the room with a small package in

his hand.

"It is not Jonathan, after all," he said.

"How vexing!" said Tess.

The packet had been brought by a special messenger, who had arrived

at Talbothays from Emminster Vicarage immediately after the departure

of the married couple, and had followed them hither, being under

injunction to deliver it into nobody's hands but theirs. Clare

brought it to the light. It was less than a foot long, sewed up in

canvas, sealed in red wax with his father's seal, and directed in his

father's hand to "Mrs Angel Clare."

"It is a little wedding-present for you, Tess," said he, handing it

to her. "How thoughtful they are!"

Tess looked a little flustered as she took it.

"I think I would rather have you open it, dearest," said she, turning

over the parcel. "I don't like to break those great seals; they look

so serious. Please open it for me!"

He undid the parcel. Inside was a case of morocco leather, on the

top of which lay a note and a key.

The note was for Clare, in the following words:

MY DEAR SON--

Possibly you have forgotten that on the death of your

godmother, Mrs Pitney, when you were a lad, she--vain,

kind woman that she was--left to me a portion of the

contents of her jewel-case in trust for your wife, if

you should ever have one, as a mark of her affection

for you and whomsoever you should choose. This trust

I have fulfilled, and the diamonds have been locked up

at my banker's ever since. Though I feel it to be a

somewhat incongruous act in the circumstances, I am, as

you will see, bound to hand over the articles to the

woman to whom the use of them for her lifetime will now

rightly belong, and they are therefore promptly sent.

They become, I believe, heirlooms, strictly speaking,

according to the terms of your godmother's will. The

precise words of the clause that refers to this matter

are enclosed.

"I do remember," said Clare; "but I had quite forgotten."

Unlocking the case, they found it to contain a necklace, with

pendant, bracelets, and ear-rings; and also some other small

ornaments.

Tess seemed afraid to touch them at first, but her eyes sparkled for

a moment as much as the stones when Clare spread out the set.

"Are they mine?" she asked incredulously.

"They are, certainly," said he.

He looked into the fire. He remembered how, when he was a lad of

fifteen, his godmother, the Squire's wife--the only rich person

with whom he had ever come in contact--had pinned her faith to his

success; had prophesied a wondrous career for him. There had seemed

nothing at all out of keeping with such a conjectured career in the

storing up of these showy ornaments for his wife and the wives of

her descendants. They gleamed somewhat ironically now. "Yet why?"

he asked himself. It was but a question of vanity throughout; and

if that were admitted into one side of the equation it should be

admitted into the other. His wife was a d'Urberville: whom could

they become better than her?

Suddenly he said with enthusiasm--

"Tess, put them on--put them on!" And he turned from the fire to

help her.

But as if by magic she had already donned them--necklace, ear-rings,

bracelets, and all.

"But the gown isn't right, Tess," said Clare. "It ought to be a low

one for a set of brilliants like that."

"Ought it?" said Tess.

"Yes," said he.

He suggested to her how to tuck in the upper edge of her bodice, so

as to make it roughly approximate to the cut for evening wear; and

when she had done this, and the pendant to the necklace hung isolated

amid the whiteness of her throat, as it was designed to do, he

stepped back to survey her.

"My heavens," said Clare, "how beautiful you are!"

As everybody knows, fine feathers make fine birds; a peasant girl but

very moderately prepossessing to the casual observer in her simple

condition and attire will bloom as an amazing beauty if clothed as a

woman of fashion with the aids that Art can render; while the beauty

of the midnight crush would often cut but a sorry figure if placed

inside the field-woman's wrapper upon a monotonous acreage of

turnips on a dull day. He had never till now estimated the artistic

excellence of Tess's limbs and features.

"If you were only to appear in a ball-room!" he said. "But

no--no, dearest; I think I love you best in the wing-bonnet and

cotton-frock--yes, better than in this, well as you support these

dignities."

Tess's sense of her striking appearance had given her a flush of

excitement, which was yet not happiness.

"I'll take them off," she said, "in case Jonathan should see me.

They are not fit for me, are they? They must be sold, I suppose?"

"Let them stay a few minutes longer. Sell them? Never. It would be

a breach of faith."

Influenced by a second thought she readily obeyed. She had something

to tell, and there might be help in these. She sat down with the

jewels upon her; and they again indulged in conjectures as to where

Jonathan could possibly be with their baggage. The ale they had

poured out for his consumption when he came had gone flat with long

standing.

Shortly after this they began supper, which was already laid on

a side-table. Ere they had finished there was a jerk in the

fire-smoke, the rising skein of which bulged out into the room, as if

some giant had laid his hand on the chimney-top for a moment. It had

been caused by the opening of the outer door. A heavy step was now

heard in the passage, and Angel went out.

"I couldn' make nobody hear at all by knocking," apologized Jonathan

Kail, for it was he at last; "and as't was raining out I opened the

door. I've brought the things, sir."

"I am very glad to see them. But you are very late."

"Well, yes, sir."

There was something subdued in Jonathan Kail's tone which had not

been there in the day, and lines of concern were ploughed upon his

forehead in addition to the lines of years. He continued--

"We've all been gallied at the dairy at what might ha' been a most

terrible affliction since you and your Mis'ess--so to name her

now--left us this a'ternoon. Perhaps you ha'nt forgot the cock's

afternoon crow?"

"Dear me;--what--"

"Well, some says it do mane one thing, and some another; but what's

happened is that poor little Retty Priddle hev tried to drown

herself."

"No! Really! Why, she bade us goodbye with the rest--"

"Yes. Well, sir, when you and your Mis'ess--so to name what she

lawful is--when you two drove away, as I say, Retty and Marian put on

their bonnets and went out; and as there is not much doing now, being

New Year's Eve, and folks mops and brooms from what's inside 'em,

nobody took much notice. They went on to Lew-Everard, where they

had summut to drink, and then on they vamped to Dree-armed Cross,

and there they seemed to have parted, Retty striking across the

water-meads as if for home, and Marian going on to the next village,

where there's another public-house. Nothing more was zeed or heard

o' Retty till the waterman, on his way home, noticed something by the

Great Pool; 'twas her bonnet and shawl packed up. In the water he

found her. He and another man brought her home, thinking a' was

dead; but she fetched round by degrees."

Angel, suddenly recollecting that Tess was overhearing this gloomy

tale, went to shut the door between the passage and the ante-room

to the inner parlour where she was; but his wife, flinging a shawl

round her, had come to the outer room and was listening to the man's

narrative, her eyes resting absently on the luggage and the drops of

rain glistening upon it.

"And, more than this, there's Marian; she's been found dead drunk

by the withy-bed--a girl who hev never been known to touch anything

before except shilling ale; though, to be sure, 'a was always a good

trencher-woman, as her face showed. It seems as if the maids had

all gone out o' their minds!"

"And Izz?" asked Tess.

"Izz is about house as usual; but 'a do say 'a can guess how it

happened; and she seems to be very low in mind about it, poor maid,

as well she mid be. And so you see, sir, as all this happened just

when we was packing your few traps and your Mis'ess's night-rail and

dressing things into the cart, why, it belated me."

"Yes. Well, Jonathan, will you get the trunks upstairs, and drink a

cup of ale, and hasten back as soon as you can, in case you should be

wanted?"

Tess had gone back to the inner parlour, and sat down by the fire,

looking wistfully into it. She heard Jonathan Kail's heavy footsteps

up and down the stairs till he had done placing the luggage, and

heard him express his thanks for the ale her husband took out to him,

and for the gratuity he received. Jonathan's footsteps then died

from the door, and his cart creaked away.

Angel slid forward the massive oak bar which secured the door, and

coming in to where she sat over the hearth, pressed her cheeks

between his hands from behind. He expected her to jump up gaily and

unpack the toilet-gear that she had been so anxious about, but as she

did not rise he sat down with her in the firelight, the candles on

the supper-table being too thin and glimmering to interfere with its

glow.

"I am so sorry you should have heard this sad story about the girls,"

he said. "Still, don't let it depress you. Retty was naturally

morbid, you know."

"Without the least cause," said Tess. "While they who have cause to

be, hide it, and pretend they are not."

This incident had turned the scale for her. They were simple and

innocent girls on whom the unhappiness of unrequited love had fallen;

they had deserved better at the hands of Fate. She had deserved

worse--yet she was the chosen one. It was wicked of her to take all

without paying. She would pay to the uttermost farthing; she would

tell, there and then. This final determination she came to when she

looked into the fire, he holding her hand.

A steady glare from the now flameless embers painted the sides

and back of the fireplace with its colour, and the well-polished

andirons, and the old brass tongs that would not meet. The underside

of the mantel-shelf was flushed with the high-coloured light, and

the legs of the table nearest the fire. Tess's face and neck

reflected the same warmth, which each gem turned into an Aldebaran

or a Sirius--a constellation of white, red, and green flashes, that

interchanged their hues with her every pulsation.

"Do you remember what we said to each other this morning about

telling our faults?" he asked abruptly, finding that she still

remained immovable. "We spoke lightly perhaps, and you may well

have done so. But for me it was no light promise. I want to make

a confession to you, Love."

This, from him, so unexpectedly apposite, had the effect upon her of

a Providential interposition.

"You have to confess something?" she said quickly, and even with

gladness and relief.

"You did not expect it? Ah--you thought too highly of me. Now

listen. Put your head there, because I want you to forgive me, and

not to be indignant with me for not telling you before, as perhaps

I ought to have done."

How strange it was! He seemed to be her double. She did not speak,

and Clare went on--

"I did not mention it because I was afraid of endangering my chance

of you, darling, the great prize of my life--my Fellowship I call

you. My brother's Fellowship was won at his college, mine at

Talbothays Dairy. Well, I would not risk it. I was going to tell

you a month ago--at the time you agreed to be mine, but I could not;

I thought it might frighten you away from me. I put it off; then I

thought I would tell you yesterday, to give you a chance at least of

escaping me. But I did not. And I did not this morning, when you

proposed our confessing our faults on the landing--the sinner that I

was! But I must, now I see you sitting there so solemnly. I wonder

if you will forgive me?"

"O yes! I am sure that--"

"Well, I hope so. But wait a minute. You don't know. To begin at

the beginning. Though I imagine my poor father fears that I am one

of the eternally lost for my doctrines, I am of course, a believer in

good morals, Tess, as much as you. I used to wish to be a teacher of

men, and it was a great disappointment to me when I found I could not

enter the Church. I admired spotlessness, even though I could lay no

claim to it, and hated impurity, as I hope I do now. Whatever one

may think of plenary inspiration, one must heartily subscribe to

these words of Paul: 'Be thou an example--in word, in conversation,

in charity, in spirit, in faith, in purity.' It is the only

safeguard for us poor human beings. '_Integer vitae_,' says a Roman

poet, who is strange company for St Paul--

"The man of upright life, from frailties free,

Stands not in need of Moorish spear or bow.

"Well, a certain place is paved with good intentions, and having felt

all that so strongly, you will see what a terrible remorse it bred

in me when, in the midst of my fine aims for other people, I myself

fell."

He then told her of that time of his life to which allusion has been

made when, tossed about by doubts and difficulties in London, like a

cork on the waves, he plunged into eight-and-forty hours' dissipation

with a stranger.

"Happily I awoke almost immediately to a sense of my folly," he

continued. "I would have no more to say to her, and I came home. I

have never repeated the offence. But I felt I should like to treat

you with perfect frankness and honour, and I could not do so without

telling this. Do you forgive me?"

She pressed his hand tightly for an answer.

"Then we will dismiss it at once and for ever!--too painful as it is

for the occasion--and talk of something lighter."

"O, Angel--I am almost glad--because now YOU can forgive ME! I have

not made my confession. I have a confession, too--remember, I said

so."

"Ah, to be sure! Now then for it, wicked little one."

"Perhaps, although you smile, it is as serious as yours, or more so."

"It can hardly be more serious, dearest."

"It cannot--O no, it cannot!" She jumped up joyfully at the hope.

"No, it cannot be more serious, certainly," she cried, "because 'tis

just the same! I will tell you now."

She sat down again.

Their hands were still joined. The ashes under the grate were lit

by the fire vertically, like a torrid waste. Imagination might have

beheld a Last Day luridness in this red-coaled glow, which fell on

his face and hand, and on hers, peering into the loose hair about her

brow, and firing the delicate skin underneath. A large shadow of her

shape rose upon the wall and ceiling. She bent forward, at which

each diamond on her neck gave a sinister wink like a toad's; and

pressing her forehead against his temple she entered on her story of

her acquaintance with Alec d'Urberville and its results, murmuring

the words without flinching, and with her eyelids drooping down.

END OF PHASE THE FOURTH

Phase the Fifth: The Woman Pays

XXXV

Her narrative ended; even its re-assertions and secondary

explanations were done. Tess's voice throughout had hardly risen

higher than its opening tone; there had been no exculpatory phrase of

any kind, and she had not wept.

But the complexion even of external things seemed to suffer

transmutation as her announcement progressed. The fire in the grate

looked impish--demoniacally funny, as if it did not care in the least

about her strait. The fender grinned idly, as if it too did not

care. The light from the water-bottle was merely engaged in a

chromatic problem. All material objects around announced their

irresponsibility with terrible iteration. And yet nothing had

changed since the moments when he had been kissing her; or rather,

nothing in the substance of things. But the essence of things had

changed.

When she ceased, the auricular impressions from their previous

endearments seemed to hustle away into the corner of their brains,

repeating themselves as echoes from a time of supremely purblind

foolishness.

Clare performed the irrelevant act of stirring the fire; the

intelligence had not even yet got to the bottom of him. After

stirring the embers he rose to his feet; all the force of her

disclosure had imparted itself now. His face had withered. In the

strenuousness of his concentration he treadled fitfully on the floor.

He could not, by any contrivance, think closely enough; that was the

meaning of his vague movement. When he spoke it was in the most

inadequate, commonplace voice of the many varied tones she had heard

from him.

"Tess!"

"Yes, dearest."

"Am I to believe this? From your manner I am to take it as true.

O you cannot be out of your mind! You ought to be! Yet you are

not... My wife, my Tess--nothing in you warrants such a supposition

as that?"

"I am not out of my mind," she said.

"And yet--" He looked vacantly at her, to resume with dazed senses:

"Why didn't you tell me before? Ah, yes, you would have told me, in a

way--but I hindered you, I remember!"

These and other of his words were nothing but the perfunctory babble

of the surface while the depths remained paralyzed. He turned away,

and bent over a chair. Tess followed him to the middle of the room,

where he was, and stood there staring at him with eyes that did not

weep. Presently she slid down upon her knees beside his foot, and

from this position she crouched in a heap.

"In the name of our love, forgive me!" she whispered with a dry

mouth. "I have forgiven you for the same!"

And, as he did not answer, she said again--

"Forgive me as you are forgiven! _I_ forgive YOU, Angel."

"You--yes, you do."

"But you do not forgive me?"

"O Tess, forgiveness does not apply to the case! You were one

person; now you are another. My God--how can forgiveness meet such

a grotesque--prestidigitation as that!"

He paused, contemplating this definition; then suddenly broke into

horrible laughter--as unnatural and ghastly as a laugh in hell.

"Don't--don't! It kills me quite, that!" she shrieked. "O have

mercy upon me--have mercy!"

He did not answer; and, sickly white, she jumped up.

"Angel, Angel! what do you mean by that laugh?" she cried out. "Do

you know what this is to me?"

He shook his head.

"I have been hoping, longing, praying, to make you happy! I have

thought what joy it will be to do it, what an unworthy wife I shall

be if I do not! That's what I have felt, Angel!"

"I know that."

"I thought, Angel, that you loved me--me, my very self! If it is

I you do love, O how can it be that you look and speak so? It

frightens me! Having begun to love you, I love you for ever--in all

changes, in all disgraces, because you are yourself. I ask no more.

Then how can you, O my own husband, stop loving me?"

"I repeat, the woman I have been loving is not you."

"But who?"

"Another woman in your shape."

She perceived in his words the realization of her own apprehensive

foreboding in former times. He looked upon her as a species of

imposter; a guilty woman in the guise of an innocent one. Terror was

upon her white face as she saw it; her cheek was flaccid, and her

mouth had almost the aspect of a round little hole. The horrible

sense of his view of her so deadened her that she staggered, and he

stepped forward, thinking she was going to fall.

"Sit down, sit down," he said gently. "You are ill; and it is

natural that you should be."

She did sit down, without knowing where she was, that strained look

still upon her face, and her eyes such as to make his flesh creep.

"I don't belong to you any more, then; do I, Angel?" she asked

helplessly. "It is not me, but another woman like me that he loved,

he says."

The image raised caused her to take pity upon herself as one who was

ill-used. Her eyes filled as she regarded her position further; she

turned round and burst into a flood of self-sympathetic tears.

Clare was relieved at this change, for the effect on her of what had

happened was beginning to be a trouble to him only less than the

woe of the disclosure itself. He waited patiently, apathetically,

till the violence of her grief had worn itself out, and her rush of

weeping had lessened to a catching gasp at intervals.

"Angel," she said suddenly, in her natural tones, the insane, dry

voice of terror having left her now. "Angel, am I too wicked for

you and me to live together?"

"I have not been able to think what we can do."

"I shan't ask you to let me live with you, Angel, because I have

no right to! I shall not write to mother and sisters to say we be

married, as I said I would do; and I shan't finish the good-hussif'

I cut out and meant to make while we were in lodgings."

"Shan't you?"

"No, I shan't do anything, unless you order me to; and if you go away

from me I shall not follow 'ee; and if you never speak to me any more

I shall not ask why, unless you tell me I may."

"And if I order you to do anything?"

"I will obey you like your wretched slave, even if it is to lie down

and die."

"You are very good. But it strikes me that there is a want of

harmony between your present mood of self-sacrifice and your past

mood of self-preservation."

These were the first words of antagonism. To fling elaborate

sarcasms at Tess, however, was much like flinging them at a dog or

cat. The charms of their subtlety passed by her unappreciated, and

she only received them as inimical sounds which meant that anger

ruled. She remained mute, not knowing that he was smothering his

affection for her. She hardly observed that a tear descended slowly

upon his cheek, a tear so large that it magnified the pores of the

skin over which it rolled, like the object lens of a microscope.

Meanwhile reillumination as to the terrible and total change that her

confession had wrought in his life, in his universe, returned to him,

and he tried desperately to advance among the new conditions in which

he stood. Some consequent action was necessary; yet what?

"Tess," he said, as gently as he could speak, "I cannot stay--in this

room--just now. I will walk out a little way."

He quietly left the room, and the two glasses of wine that he had

poured out for their supper--one for her, one for him--remained on

the table untasted. This was what their _agape_ had come to. At

tea, two or three hours earlier, they had, in the freakishness of

affection, drunk from one cup.

The closing of the door behind him, gently as it had been pulled

to, roused Tess from her stupor. He was gone; she could not stay.

Hastily flinging her cloak around her she opened the door and

followed, putting out the candles as if she were never coming back.

The rain was over and the night was now clear.

She was soon close at his heels, for Clare walked slowly and without

purpose. His form beside her light gray figure looked black,

sinister, and forbidding, and she felt as sarcasm the touch of the

jewels of which she had been momentarily so proud. Clare turned at

hearing her footsteps, but his recognition of her presence seemed

to make no difference to him, and he went on over the five yawning

arches of the great bridge in front of the house.

The cow and horse tracks in the road were full of water, the rain

having been enough to charge them, but not enough to wash them away.

Across these minute pools the reflected stars flitted in a quick

transit as she passed; she would not have known they were shining

overhead if she had not seen them there--the vastest things of the

universe imaged in objects so mean.

The place to which they had travelled to-day was in the same

valley as Talbothays, but some miles lower down the river; and the

surroundings being open, she kept easily in sight of him. Away from

the house the road wound through the meads, and along these she

followed Clare without any attempt to come up with him or to attract

him, but with dumb and vacant fidelity.

At last, however, her listless walk brought her up alongside him, and

still he said nothing. The cruelty of fooled honesty is often great

after enlightenment, and it was mighty in Clare now. The outdoor air

had apparently taken away from him all tendency to act on impulse;

she knew that he saw her without irradiation--in all her bareness;

that Time was chanting his satiric psalm at her then--

Behold, when thy face is made bare, he that loved thee

shall hate;

Thy face shall be no more fair at the fall of thy fate.

For thy life shall fall as a leaf and be shed as the rain;

And the veil of thine head shall be grief, and the crown

shall be pain.

He was still intently thinking, and her companionship had now

insufficient power to break or divert the strain of thought. What a

weak thing her presence must have become to him! She could not help

addressing Clare.

"What have I done--what HAVE I done! I have not told of anything

that interferes with or belies my love for you. You don't think I

planned it, do you? It is in your own mind what you are angry at,

Angel; it is not in me. O, it is not in me, and I am not that

deceitful woman you think me!"

"H'm--well. Not deceitful, my wife; but not the same. No, not the

same. But do not make me reproach you. I have sworn that I will

not; and I will do everything to avoid it."

But she went on pleading in her distraction; and perhaps said things

that would have been better left to silence.

"Angel!--Angel! I was a child--a child when it happened! I knew

nothing of men."

"You were more sinned against than sinning, that I admit."

"Then will you not forgive me?"

"I do forgive you, but forgiveness is not all."

"And love me?"

To this question he did not answer.

"O Angel--my mother says that it sometimes happens so!--she knows

several cases where they were worse than I, and the husband has not

minded it much--has got over it at least. And yet the woman had not

loved him as I do you!"

"Don't, Tess; don't argue. Different societies, different manners.

You almost make me say you are an unapprehending peasant woman, who

have never been initiated into the proportions of social things.

You don't know what you say."

"I am only a peasant by position, not by nature!"

She spoke with an impulse to anger, but it went as it came.

"So much the worse for you. I think that parson who unearthed your

pedigree would have done better if he had held his tongue. I cannot

help associating your decline as a family with this other fact--of

your want of firmness. Decrepit families imply decrepit wills,

decrepit conduct. Heaven, why did you give me a handle for despising

you more by informing me of your descent! Here was I thinking you a

new-sprung child of nature; there were you, the belated seedling of

an effete aristocracy!"

"Lots of families are as bad as mine in that! Retty's family were

once large landowners, and so were Dairyman Billett's. And the

Debbyhouses, who now are carters, were once the De Bayeux family.

You find such as I everywhere; 'tis a feature of our county, and I

can't help it."

"So much the worse for the county."

She took these reproaches in their bulk simply, not in their

particulars; he did not love her as he had loved her hitherto, and

to all else she was indifferent.

They wandered on again in silence. It was said afterwards that a

cottager of Wellbridge, who went out late that night for a doctor,

met two lovers in the pastures, walking very slowly, without

converse, one behind the other, as in a funeral procession, and the

glimpse that he obtained of their faces seemed to denote that they

were anxious and sad. Returning later, he passed them again in the

same field, progressing just as slowly, and as regardless of the hour

and of the cheerless night as before. It was only on account of his

preoccupation with his own affairs, and the illness in his house,

that he did not bear in mind the curious incident, which, however, he

recalled a long while after.

During the interval of the cottager's going and coming, she had said

to her husband--

"I don't see how I can help being the cause of much misery to you all

your life. The river is down there. I can put an end to myself in

it. I am not afraid."

"I don't wish to add murder to my other follies," he said.

"I will leave something to show that I did it myself--on account of

my shame. They will not blame you then."

"Don't speak so absurdly--I wish not to hear it. It is nonsense

to have such thoughts in this kind of case, which is rather one

for satirical laughter than for tragedy. You don't in the least

understand the quality of the mishap. It would be viewed in the

light of a joke by nine-tenths of the world if it were known. Please

oblige me by returning to the house, and going to bed."

"I will," said she dutifully.

They had rambled round by a road which led to the well-known ruins of

the Cistercian abbey behind the mill, the latter having, in centuries

past, been attached to the monastic establishment. The mill still

worked on, food being a perennial necessity; the abbey had perished,

creeds being transient. One continually sees the ministration of the

temporary outlasting the ministration of the eternal. Their walk

having been circuitous, they were still not far from the house, and

in obeying his direction she only had to reach the large stone bridge

across the main river and follow the road for a few yards. When she

got back, everything remained as she had left it, the fire being

still burning. She did not stay downstairs for more than a minute,

but proceeded to her chamber, whither the luggage had been taken.

Here she sat down on the edge of the bed, looking blankly around,

and presently began to undress. In removing the light towards the

bedstead its rays fell upon the tester of white dimity; something was

hanging beneath it, and she lifted the candle to see what it was.

A bough of mistletoe. Angel had put it there; she knew that in an

instant. This was the explanation of that mysterious parcel which it

had been so difficult to pack and bring; whose contents he would not

explain to her, saying that time would soon show her the purpose

thereof. In his zest and his gaiety he had hung it there. How

foolish and inopportune that mistletoe looked now.

Having nothing more to fear, having scarce anything to hope, for that

he would relent there seemed no promise whatever, she lay down dully.

When sorrow ceases to be speculative, sleep sees her opportunity.

Among so many happier moods which forbid repose this was a mood which

welcomed it, and in a few minutes the lonely Tess forgot existence,

surrounded by the aromatic stillness of the chamber that had once,

possibly, been the bride-chamber of her own ancestry.

Later on that night Clare also retraced his steps to the house.

Entering softly to the sitting-room he obtained a light, and with the

manner of one who had considered his course he spread his rugs upon

the old horse-hair sofa which stood there, and roughly shaped it to

a sleeping-couch. Before lying down he crept shoeless upstairs, and

listened at the door of her apartment. Her measured breathing told

that she was sleeping profoundly.

"Thank God!" murmured Clare; and yet he was conscious of a pang of

bitterness at the thought--approximately true, though not wholly

so--that having shifted the burden of her life to his shoulders, she

was now reposing without care.

He turned away to descend; then, irresolute, faced round to her

door again. In the act he caught sight of one of the d'Urberville

dames, whose portrait was immediately over the entrance to Tess's

bedchamber. In the candlelight the painting was more than

unpleasant. Sinister design lurked in the woman's features, a

concentrated purpose of revenge on the other sex--so it seemed to

him then. The Caroline bodice of the portrait was low--precisely as

Tess's had been when he tucked it in to show the necklace; and again

he experienced the distressing sensation of a resemblance between

them.

The check was sufficient. He resumed his retreat and descended.

His air remained calm and cold, his small compressed mouth indexing

his powers of self-control; his face wearing still that terrible

sterile expression which had spread thereon since her disclosure.

It was the face of a man who was no longer passion's slave, yet who

found no advantage in his enfranchisement. He was simply regarding

the harrowing contingencies of human experience, the unexpectedness

of things. Nothing so pure, so sweet, so virginal as Tess had seemed

possible all the long while that he had adored her, up to an hour

ago; but

The little less, and what worlds away!

He argued erroneously when he said to himself that her heart was not

indexed in the honest freshness of her face; but Tess had no advocate

to set him right. Could it be possible, he continued, that eyes

which as they gazed never expressed any divergence from what the

tongue was telling, were yet ever seeing another world behind her

ostensible one, discordant and contrasting?

He reclined on his couch in the sitting-room, and extinguished the

light. The night came in, and took up its place there, unconcerned

and indifferent; the night which had already swallowed up his

happiness, and was now digesting it listlessly; and was ready to

swallow up the happiness of a thousand other people with as little

disturbance or change of mien.

XXXVI

Clare arose in the light of a dawn that was ashy and furtive, as

though associated with crime. The fireplace confronted him with its

extinct embers; the spread supper-table, whereon stood the two full

glasses of untasted wine, now flat and filmy; her vacated seat and

his own; the other articles of furniture, with their eternal look of

not being able to help it, their intolerable inquiry what was to be

done? From above there was no sound; but in a few minutes there came

a knock at the door. He remembered that it would be the neighbouring

cottager's wife, who was to minister to their wants while they

remained here.

The presence of a third person in the house would be extremely

awkward just now, and, being already dressed, he opened the window

and informed her that they could manage to shift for themselves that

morning. She had a milk-can in her hand, which he told her to leave

at the door. When the dame had gone away he searched in the back

quarters of the house for fuel, and speedily lit a fire. There was

plenty of eggs, butter, bread, and so on in the larder, and Clare

soon had breakfast laid, his experiences at the dairy having rendered

him facile in domestic preparations. The smoke of the kindled wood

rose from the chimney without like a lotus-headed column; local

people who were passing by saw it, and thought of the newly-married

couple, and envied their happiness.

Angel cast a final glance round, and then going to the foot of the

stairs, called in a conventional voice--

"Breakfast is ready!"

He opened the front door, and took a few steps in the morning air.

When, after a short space, he came back she was already in the

sitting-room mechanically readjusting the breakfast things. As she

was fully attired, and the interval since his calling her had been

but two or three minutes, she must have been dressed or nearly so

before he went to summon her. Her hair was twisted up in a large

round mass at the back of her head, and she had put on one of the

new frocks--a pale blue woollen garment with neck-frillings of

white. Her hands and face appeared to be cold, and she had possibly

been sitting dressed in the bedroom a long time without any fire.

The marked civility of Clare's tone in calling her seemed to have

inspired her, for the moment, with a new glimmer of hope. But it

soon died when she looked at him.

The pair were, in truth, but the ashes of their former fires. To the

hot sorrow of the previous night had succeeded heaviness; it seemed

as if nothing could kindle either of them to fervour of sensation any

more.

He spoke gently to her, and she replied with a like

undemonstrativeness. At last she came up to him, looking in his

sharply-defined face as one who had no consciousness that her own

formed a visible object also.

"Angel!" she said, and paused, touching him with her fingers lightly

as a breeze, as though she could hardly believe to be there in the

flesh the man who was once her lover. Her eyes were bright, her pale

cheek still showed its wonted roundness, though half-dried tears had

left glistening traces thereon; and the usually ripe red mouth was

almost as pale as her cheek. Throbbingly alive as she was still,

under the stress of her mental grief the life beat so brokenly that

a little further pull upon it would cause real illness, dull her

characteristic eyes, and make her mouth thin.

She looked absolutely pure. Nature, in her fantastic trickery, had

set such a seal of maidenhood upon Tess's countenance that he gazed

at her with a stupefied air.

"Tess! Say it is not true! No, it is not true!"

"It is true."

"Every word?"

"Every word."

He looked at her imploringly, as if he would willingly have taken a

lie from her lips, knowing it to be one, and have made of it, by some

sort of sophistry, a valid denial. However, she only repeated--

"It is true."

"Is he living?" Angel then asked.

"The baby died."

"But the man?"

"He is alive."

A last despair passed over Clare's face.

"Is he in England?"

"Yes."

He took a few vague steps.

"My position--is this," he said abruptly. "I thought--any man would

have thought--that by giving up all ambition to win a wife with

social standing, with fortune, with knowledge of the world, I should

secure rustic innocence as surely as I should secure pink cheeks;

but--However, I am no man to reproach you, and I will not."

Tess felt his position so entirely that the remainder had not been

needed. Therein lay just the distress of it; she saw that he had

lost all round.

"Angel--I should not have let it go on to marriage with you if I had

not known that, after all, there was a last way out of it for you;

though I hoped you would never--"

Her voice grew husky.

"A last way?"

"I mean, to get rid of me. You CAN get rid of me."

"How?"

"By divorcing me."

"Good heavens--how can you be so simple! How can I divorce you?"

"Can't you--now I have told you? I thought my confession would give

you grounds for that."

"O Tess--you are too, too--childish--unformed--crude, I suppose! I

don't know what you are. You don't understand the law--you don't

understand!"

"What--you cannot?"

"Indeed I cannot."

A quick shame mixed with the misery upon his listener's face.

"I thought--I thought," she whispered. "O, now I see how wicked I

seem to you! Believe me--believe me, on my soul, I never thought but

that you could! I hoped you would not; yet I believed, without a

doubt, that you could cast me off if you were determined, and didn't

love me at--at--all!"

"You were mistaken," he said.

"O, then I ought to have done it, to have done it last night! But I

hadn't the courage. That's just like me!"

"The courage to do what?"

As she did not answer he took her by the hand.

"What were you thinking of doing?" he inquired.

"Of putting an end to myself."

"When?"

She writhed under this inquisitorial manner of his. "Last night,"

she answered.

"Where?"

"Under your mistletoe."

"My good--! How?" he asked sternly.

"I'll tell you, if you won't be angry with me!" she said, shrinking.

"It was with the cord of my box. But I could not--do the last thing!

I was afraid that it might cause a scandal to your name."

The unexpected quality of this confession, wrung from her, and not

volunteered, shook him perceptibly. But he still held her, and,

letting his glance fall from her face downwards, he said, "Now,

listen to this. You must not dare to think of such a horrible thing!

How could you! You will promise me as your husband to attempt that

no more."

"I am ready to promise. I saw how wicked it was."

"Wicked! The idea was unworthy of you beyond description."

"But, Angel," she pleaded, enlarging her eyes in calm unconcern upon

him, "it was thought of entirely on your account--to set you free

without the scandal of the divorce that I thought you would have to

get. I should never have dreamt of doing it on mine. However, to

do it with my own hand is too good for me, after all. It is you, my

ruined husband, who ought to strike the blow. I think I should love

you more, if that were possible, if you could bring yourself to do

it, since there's no other way of escape for 'ee. I feel I am so

utterly worthless! So very greatly in the way!"

"Ssh!"

"Well, since you say no, I won't. I have no wish opposed to yours."

He knew this to be true enough. Since the desperation of the night

her activities had dropped to zero, and there was no further rashness

to be feared.

Tess tried to busy herself again over the breakfast-table with more

or less success, and they sat down both on the same side, so that

their glances did not meet. There was at first something awkward

in hearing each other eat and drink, but this could not be escaped;

moreover, the amount of eating done was small on both sides.

Breakfast over, he rose, and telling her the hour at which he might

be expected to dinner, went off to the miller's in a mechanical

pursuance of the plan of studying that business, which had been his

only practical reason for coming here.

When he was gone Tess stood at the window, and presently saw his form

crossing the great stone bridge which conducted to the mill premises.

He sank behind it, crossed the railway beyond, and disappeared.

Then, without a sigh, she turned her attention to the room, and began

clearing the table and setting it in order.

The charwoman soon came. Her presence was at first a strain upon

Tess, but afterwards an alleviation. At half-past twelve she

left her assistant alone in the kitchen, and, returning to the

sitting-room, waited for the reappearance of Angel's form behind the

bridge.

About one he showed himself. Her face flushed, although he was a

quarter of a mile off. She ran to the kitchen to get the dinner

served by the time he should enter. He went first to the room where

they had washed their hands together the day before, and as he

entered the sitting-room the dish-covers rose from the dishes as if

by his own motion.

"How punctual!" he said.

"Yes. I saw you coming over the bridge," said she.

The meal was passed in commonplace talk of what he had been doing

during the morning at the Abbey Mill, of the methods of bolting and

the old-fashioned machinery, which he feared would not enlighten him

greatly on modern improved methods, some of it seeming to have been

in use ever since the days it ground for the monks in the adjoining

conventual buildings--now a heap of ruins. He left the house again

in the course of an hour, coming home at dusk, and occupying himself

through the evening with his papers. She feared she was in the way

and, when the old woman was gone, retired to the kitchen, where she

made herself busy as well as she could for more than an hour.

Clare's shape appeared at the door. "You must not work like this," he

said. "You are not my servant; you are my wife."

She raised her eyes, and brightened somewhat. "I may think myself

that--indeed?" she murmured, in piteous raillery. "You mean in name!

Well, I don't want to be anything more."

"You MAY think so, Tess! You are. What do you mean?"

"I don't know," she said hastily, with tears in her accents. "I

thought I--because I am not respectable, I mean. I told you I

thought I was not respectable enough long ago--and on that account

I didn't want to marry you, only--only you urged me!"

She broke into sobs, and turned her back to him. It would almost

have won round any man but Angel Clare. Within the remote depths of

his constitution, so gentle and affectionate as he was in general,

there lay hidden a hard logical deposit, like a vein of metal in a

soft loam, which turned the edge of everything that attempted to

traverse it. It had blocked his acceptance of the Church; it blocked

his acceptance of Tess. Moreover, his affection itself was less fire

than radiance, and, with regard to the other sex, when he ceased

to believe he ceased to follow: contrasting in this with many

impressionable natures, who remain sensuously infatuated with what

they intellectually despise. He waited till her sobbing ceased.

"I wish half the women in England were as respectable as you," he

said, in an ebullition of bitterness against womankind in general.

"It isn't a question of respectability, but one of principle!"

He spoke such things as these and more of a kindred sort to her,

being still swayed by the antipathetic wave which warps direct souls

with such persistence when once their vision finds itself mocked by

appearances. There was, it is true, underneath, a back current of

sympathy through which a woman of the world might have conquered him.

But Tess did not think of this; she took everything as her deserts,

and hardly opened her mouth. The firmness of her devotion to him was

indeed almost pitiful; quick-tempered as she naturally was, nothing

that he could say made her unseemly; she sought not her own; was not

provoked; thought no evil of his treatment of her. She might just

now have been Apostolic Charity herself returned to a self-seeking

modern world.

This evening, night, and morning were passed precisely as the

preceding ones had been passed. On one, and only one, occasion did

she--the formerly free and independent Tess--venture to make any

advances. It was on the third occasion of his starting after a meal

to go out to the flour-mill. As he was leaving the table he said

"Goodbye," and she replied in the same words, at the same time

inclining her mouth in the way of his. He did not avail himself of

the invitation, saying, as he turned hastily aside--

"I shall be home punctually."

Tess shrank into herself as if she had been struck. Often enough had

he tried to reach those lips against her consent--often had he said

gaily that her mouth and breath tasted of the butter and eggs and

milk and honey on which she mainly lived, that he drew sustenance

from them, and other follies of that sort. But he did not care for

them now. He observed her sudden shrinking, and said gently--

"You know, I have to think of a course. It was imperative that we

should stay together a little while, to avoid the scandal to you that

would have resulted from our immediate parting. But you must see it

is only for form's sake."

"Yes," said Tess absently.

He went out, and on his way to the mill stood still, and wished for a

moment that he had responded yet more kindly, and kissed her once at

least.

Thus they lived through this despairing day or two; in the same

house, truly; but more widely apart than before they were lovers. It

was evident to her that he was, as he had said, living with paralyzed

activities in his endeavour to think of a plan of procedure. She

was awe-stricken to discover such determination under such apparent

flexibility. His consistency was, indeed, too cruel. She no longer

expected forgiveness now. More than once she thought of going away

from him during his absence at the mill; but she feared that this,

instead of benefiting him, might be the means of hampering and

humiliating him yet more if it should become known.

Meanwhile Clare was meditating, verily. His thought had been

unsuspended; he was becoming ill with thinking; eaten out with

thinking, withered by thinking; scourged out of all his former

pulsating, flexuous domesticity. He walked about saying to himself,

"What's to be done--what's to be done?" and by chance she overheard

him. It caused her to break the reserve about their future which had

hitherto prevailed.

"I suppose--you are not going to live with me--long, are you, Angel?"

she asked, the sunk corners of her mouth betraying how purely

mechanical were the means by which she retained that expression of

chastened calm upon her face.

"I cannot" he said, "without despising myself, and what is worse,

perhaps, despising you. I mean, of course, cannot live with you

in the ordinary sense. At present, whatever I feel, I do not

despise you. And, let me speak plainly, or you may not see all my

difficulties. How can we live together while that man lives?--he

being your husband in nature, and not I. If he were dead it might

be different... Besides, that's not all the difficulty; it lies in

another consideration--one bearing upon the future of other people

than ourselves. Think of years to come, and children being born to

us, and this past matter getting known--for it must get known. There

is not an uttermost part of the earth but somebody comes from it or

goes to it from elsewhere. Well, think of wretches of our flesh and

blood growing up under a taunt which they will gradually get to feel

the full force of with their expanding years. What an awakening

for them! What a prospect! Can you honestly say 'Remain' after

contemplating this contingency? Don't you think we had better

endure the ills we have than fly to others?"

Her eyelids, weighted with trouble, continued drooping as before.

"I cannot say 'Remain,'" she answered, "I cannot; I had not thought

so far."

Tess's feminine hope--shall we confess it?--had been so obstinately

recuperative as to revive in her surreptitious visions of a

domiciliary intimacy continued long enough to break down his coldness

even against his judgement. Though unsophisticated in the usual

sense, she was not incomplete; and it would have denoted deficiency

of womanhood if she had not instinctively known what an argument lies

in propinquity. Nothing else would serve her, she knew, if this

failed. It was wrong to hope in what was of the nature of strategy,

she said to herself: yet that sort of hope she could not extinguish.

His last representation had now been made, and it was, as she said,

a new view. She had truly never thought so far as that, and his

lucid picture of possible offspring who would scorn her was one that

brought deadly convictions to an honest heart which was humanitarian

to its centre. Sheer experience had already taught her that in some

circumstances there was one thing better than to lead a good life,

and that was to be saved from leading any life whatever. Like all

who have been previsioned by suffering, she could, in the words of

M. Sully-Prudhomme, hear a penal sentence in the fiat, "You shall be

born," particularly if addressed to potential issue of hers.

Yet such is the vulpine slyness of Dame Nature, that, till now, Tess

had been hoodwinked by her love for Clare into forgetting it might

result in vitalizations that would inflict upon others what she had

bewailed as misfortune to herself.

She therefore could not withstand his argument. But with the

self-combating proclivity of the supersensitive, an answer thereto

arose in Clare's own mind, and he almost feared it. It was based

on her exceptional physical nature; and she might have used it

promisingly. She might have added besides: "On an Australian upland

or Texan plain, who is to know or care about my misfortunes, or to

reproach me or you?" Yet, like the majority of women, she accepted

the momentary presentment as if it were the inevitable. And she

may have been right. The intuitive heart of woman knoweth not only

its own bitterness, but its husband's, and even if these assumed

reproaches were not likely to be addressed to him or to his by

strangers, they might have reached his ears from his own fastidious

brain.

It was the third day of the estrangement. Some might risk the odd

paradox that with more animalism he would have been the nobler man.

We do not say it. Yet Clare's love was doubtless ethereal to a

fault, imaginative to impracticability. With these natures, corporal

presence is something less appealing than corporal absence; the

latter creating an ideal presence that conveniently drops the defects

of the real. She found that her personality did not plead her cause

so forcibly as she had anticipated. The figurative phrase was true:

she was another woman than the one who had excited his desire.

"I have thought over what you say," she remarked to him, moving her

forefinger over the tablecloth, her other hand, which bore the ring

that mocked them both, supporting her forehead. "It is quite true,

all of it; it must be. You must go away from me."

"But what can you do?"

"I can go home."

Clare had not thought of that.

"Are you sure?" he inquired.

"Quite sure. We ought to part, and we may as well get it past and

done. You once said that I was apt to win men against their better

judgement; and if I am constantly before your eyes I may cause you

to change your plans in opposition to your reason and wish; and

afterwards your repentance and my sorrow will be terrible."

"And you would like to go home?" he asked.

"I want to leave you, and go home."

"Then it shall be so."

Though she did not look up at him, she started. There was a

difference between the proposition and the covenant, which she had

felt only too quickly.

"I feared it would come to this," she murmured, her countenance

meekly fixed. "I don't complain, Angel, I--I think it best. What

you said has quite convinced me. Yes, though nobody else should

reproach me if we should stay together, yet somewhen, years hence,

you might get angry with me for any ordinary matter, and knowing what

you do of my bygones, you yourself might be tempted to say words, and

they might be overheard, perhaps by my own children. O, what only

hurts me now would torture and kill me then! I will go--to-morrow."

"And I shall not stay here. Though I didn't like to initiate it, I

have seen that it was advisable we should part--at least for a while,

till I can better see the shape that things have taken, and can write

to you."

Tess stole a glance at her husband. He was pale, even tremulous;

but, as before, she was appalled by the determination revealed in the

depths of this gentle being she had married--the will to subdue the

grosser to the subtler emotion, the substance to the conception, the

flesh to the spirit. Propensities, tendencies, habits, were as dead

leaves upon the tyrannous wind of his imaginative ascendency.

He may have observed her look, for he explained--

"I think of people more kindly when I am away from them"; adding

cynically, "God knows; perhaps we will shake down together some day,

for weariness; thousands have done it!"

That day he began to pack up, and she went upstairs and began to pack

also. Both knew that it was in their two minds that they might part

the next morning for ever, despite the gloss of assuaging conjectures

thrown over their proceeding because they were of the sort to whom

any parting which has an air of finality is a torture. He knew,

and she knew, that, though the fascination which each had exercised

over the other--on her part independently of accomplishments--would

probably in the first days of their separation be even more potent

than ever, time must attenuate that effect; the practical arguments

against accepting her as a housemate might pronounce themselves more

strongly in the boreal light of a remoter view. Moreover, when two

people are once parted--have abandoned a common domicile and a common

environment--new growths insensibly bud upward to fill each vacated

place; unforeseen accidents hinder intentions, and old plans are

forgotten.

XXXVII

Midnight came and passed silently, for there was nothing to announce

it in the Valley of the Froom.

Not long after one o'clock there was a slight creak in the darkened

farmhouse once the mansion of the d'Urbervilles. Tess, who used the

upper chamber, heard it and awoke. It had come from the corner step

of the staircase, which, as usual, was loosely nailed. She saw the

door of her bedroom open, and the figure of her husband crossed the

stream of moonlight with a curiously careful tread. He was in his

shirt and trousers only, and her first flush of joy died when she

perceived that his eyes were fixed in an unnatural stare on vacancy.

When he reached the middle of the room he stood still and murmured in

tones of indescribable sadness--

"Dead! dead! dead!"

Under the influence of any strongly-disturbing force, Clare would

occasionally walk in his sleep, and even perform strange feats, such

as he had done on the night of their return from market just before

their marriage, when he re-enacted in his bedroom his combat with the

man who had insulted her. Tess saw that continued mental distress

had wrought him into that somnambulistic state now.

Her loyal confidence in him lay so deep down in her heart, that,

awake or asleep, he inspired her with no sort of personal fear. If

he had entered with a pistol in his hand he would scarcely have

disturbed her trust in his protectiveness.

Clare came close, and bent over her. "Dead, dead, dead!" he murmured.

After fixedly regarding her for some moments with the same gaze of

unmeasurable woe, he bent lower, enclosed her in his arms, and rolled

her in the sheet as in a shroud. Then lifting her from the bed with

as much respect as one would show to a dead body, he carried her

across the room, murmuring--

"My poor, poor Tess--my dearest, darling Tess! So sweet, so good, so

true!"

The words of endearment, withheld so severely in his waking hours,

were inexpressibly sweet to her forlorn and hungry heart. If it had

been to save her weary life she would not, by moving or struggling,

have put an end to the position she found herself in. Thus she lay

in absolute stillness, scarcely venturing to breathe, and, wondering

what he was going to do with her, suffered herself to be borne out

upon the landing.

"My wife--dead, dead!" he said.

He paused in his labours for a moment to lean with her against the

banister. Was he going to throw her down? Self-solicitude was near

extinction in her, and in the knowledge that he had planned to depart

on the morrow, possibly for always, she lay in his arms in this

precarious position with a sense rather of luxury than of terror. If

they could only fall together, and both be dashed to pieces, how fit,

how desirable.

However, he did not let her fall, but took advantage of the support

of the handrail to imprint a kiss upon her lips--lips in the day-time

scorned. Then he clasped her with a renewed firmness of hold, and

descended the staircase. The creak of the loose stair did not awaken

him, and they reached the ground-floor safely. Freeing one of his

hands from his grasp of her for a moment, he slid back the door-bar

and passed out, slightly striking his stockinged toe against the edge

of the door. But this he seemed not to mind, and, having room for

extension in the open air, he lifted her against his shoulder, so

that he could carry her with ease, the absence of clothes taking much

from his burden. Thus he bore her off the premises in the direction

of the river a few yards distant.

His ultimate intention, if he had any, she had not yet divined; and

she found herself conjecturing on the matter as a third person might

have done. So easefully had she delivered her whole being up to him

that it pleased her to think he was regarding her as his absolute

possession, to dispose of as he should choose. It was consoling,

under the hovering terror of to-morrow's separation, to feel that he

really recognized her now as his wife Tess, and did not cast her off,

even if in that recognition he went so far as to arrogate to himself

the right of harming her.

Ah! now she knew what he was dreaming of--that Sunday morning when he

had borne her along through the water with the other dairymaids, who

had loved him nearly as much as she, if that were possible, which

Tess could hardly admit. Clare did not cross the bridge with her,

but proceeding several paces on the same side towards the adjoining

mill, at length stood still on the brink of the river.

Its waters, in creeping down these miles of meadowland, frequently

divided, serpentining in purposeless curves, looping themselves

around little islands that had no name, returning and re-embodying

themselves as a broad main stream further on. Opposite the spot to

which he had brought her was such a general confluence, and the river

was proportionately voluminous and deep. Across it was a narrow

foot-bridge; but now the autumn flood had washed the handrail away,

leaving the bare plank only, which, lying a few inches above the

speeding current, formed a giddy pathway for even steady heads; and

Tess had noticed from the window of the house in the day-time young

men walking across upon it as a feat in balancing. Her husband had

possibly observed the same performance; anyhow, he now mounted the

plank, and, sliding one foot forward, advanced along it.

Was he going to drown her? Probably he was. The spot was lonely,

the river deep and wide enough to make such a purpose easy of

accomplishment. He might drown her if he would; it would be better

than parting to-morrow to lead severed lives.

The swift stream raced and gyrated under them, tossing, distorting,

and splitting the moon's reflected face. Spots of froth travelled

past, and intercepted weeds waved behind the piles. If they could

both fall together into the current now, their arms would be so

tightly clasped together that they could not be saved; they would

go out of the world almost painlessly, and there would be no more

reproach to her, or to him for marrying her. His last half-hour with

her would have been a loving one, while if they lived till he awoke,

his day-time aversion would return, and this hour would remain to be

contemplated only as a transient dream.

The impulse stirred in her, yet she dared not indulge it, to make a

movement that would have precipitated them both into the gulf. How

she valued her own life had been proved; but his--she had no right to

tamper with it. He reached the other side with her in safety.

Here they were within a plantation which formed the Abbey grounds,

and taking a new hold of her he went onward a few steps till they

reached the ruined choir of the Abbey-church. Against the north wall

was the empty stone coffin of an abbot, in which every tourist with

a turn for grim humour was accustomed to stretch himself. In this

Clare carefully laid Tess. Having kissed her lips a second time he

breathed deeply, as if a greatly desired end were attained. Clare

then lay down on the ground alongside, when he immediately fell into

the deep dead slumber of exhaustion, and remained motionless as a

log. The spurt of mental excitement which had produced the effort

was now over.

Tess sat up in the coffin. The night, though dry and mild for the

season, was more than sufficiently cold to make it dangerous for him

to remain here long, in his half-clothed state. If he were left to

himself he would in all probability stay there till the morning, and

be chilled to certain death. She had heard of such deaths after

sleep-walking. But how could she dare to awaken him, and let him

know what he had been doing, when it would mortify him to discover

his folly in respect of her? Tess, however, stepping out of her

stone confine, shook him slightly, but was unable to arouse him

without being violent. It was indispensable to do something, for she

was beginning to shiver, the sheet being but a poor protection. Her

excitement had in a measure kept her warm during the few minutes'

adventure; but that beatific interval was over.

It suddenly occurred to her to try persuasion; and accordingly she

whispered in his ear, with as much firmness and decision as she could

summon--

"Let us walk on, darling," at the same time taking him suggestively

by the arm. To her relief, he unresistingly acquiesced; her words

had apparently thrown him back into his dream, which thenceforward

seemed to enter on a new phase, wherein he fancied she had risen as a

spirit, and was leading him to Heaven. Thus she conducted him by the

arm to the stone bridge in front of their residence, crossing which

they stood at the manor-house door. Tess's feet were quite bare, and

the stones hurt her, and chilled her to the bone; but Clare was in

his woollen stockings, and appeared to feel no discomfort.

There was no further difficulty. She induced him to lie down on his

own sofa bed, and covered him up warmly, lighting a temporary fire of

wood, to dry any dampness out of him. The noise of these attentions

she thought might awaken him, and secretly wished that they might.

But the exhaustion of his mind and body was such that he remained

undisturbed.

As soon as they met the next morning Tess divined that Angel knew

little or nothing of how far she had been concerned in the night's

excursion, though, as regarded himself, he may have been aware that

he had not lain still. In truth, he had awakened that morning from

a sleep deep as annihilation; and during those first few moments

in which the brain, like a Samson shaking himself, is trying its

strength, he had some dim notion of an unusual nocturnal proceeding.

But the realities of his situation soon displaced conjecture on the

other subject.

He waited in expectancy to discern some mental pointing; he knew that

if any intention of his, concluded over-night, did not vanish in the

light of morning, it stood on a basis approximating to one of pure

reason, even if initiated by impulse of feeling; that it was so

far, therefore, to be trusted. He thus beheld in the pale morning

light the resolve to separate from her; not as a hot and indignant

instinct, but denuded of the passionateness which had made it scorch

and burn; standing in its bones; nothing but a skeleton, but none the

less there. Clare no longer hesitated.

At breakfast, and while they were packing the few remaining articles,

he showed his weariness from the night's effort so unmistakeably that

Tess was on the point of revealing all that had happened; but the

reflection that it would anger him, grieve him, stultify him, to know

that he had instinctively manifested a fondness for her of which his

common-sense did not approve, that his inclination had compromised

his dignity when reason slept, again deterred her. It was too much

like laughing at a man when sober for his erratic deeds during

intoxication.

It just crossed her mind, too, that he might have a faint

recollection of his tender vagary, and was disinclined to allude to

it from a conviction that she would take amatory advantage of the

opportunity it gave her of appealing to him anew not to go.

He had ordered by letter a vehicle from the nearest town, and

soon after breakfast it arrived. She saw in it the beginning of

the end--the temporary end, at least, for the revelation of his

tenderness by the incident of the night raised dreams of a possible

future with him. The luggage was put on the top, and the man drove

them off, the miller and the old waiting-woman expressing some

surprise at their precipitate departure, which Clare attributed to

his discovery that the mill-work was not of the modern kind which he

wished to investigate, a statement that was true so far as it went.

Beyond this there was nothing in the manner of their leaving to

suggest a fiasco, or that they were not going together to visit

friends.

Their route lay near the dairy from which they had started with such

solemn joy in each other a few days back, and as Clare wished to wind

up his business with Mr Crick, Tess could hardly avoid paying Mrs

Crick a call at the same time, unless she would excite suspicion of

their unhappy state.

To make the call as unobtrusive as possible, they left the carriage

by the wicket leading down from the high road to the dairy-house, and

descended the track on foot, side by side. The withy-bed had been

cut, and they could see over the stumps the spot to which Clare had

followed her when he pressed her to be his wife; to the left the

enclosure in which she had been fascinated by his harp; and far away

behind the cow-stalls the mead which had been the scene of their

first embrace. The gold of the summer picture was now gray, the

colours mean, the rich soil mud, and the river cold.

Over the barton-gate the dairyman saw them, and came forward,

throwing into his face the kind of jocularity deemed appropriate

in Talbothays and its vicinity on the re-appearance of the

newly-married. Then Mrs Crick emerged from the house, and several

others of their old acquaintance, though Marian and Retty did not

seem to be there.

Tess valiantly bore their sly attacks and friendly humours, which

affected her far otherwise than they supposed. In the tacit

agreement of husband and wife to keep their estrangement a secret

they behaved as would have been ordinary. And then, although she

would rather there had been no word spoken on the subject, Tess had

to hear in detail the story of Marian and Retty. The later had gone

home to her father's, and Marian had left to look for employment

elsewhere. They feared she would come to no good.

To dissipate the sadness of this recital Tess went and bade all her

favourite cows goodbye, touching each of them with her hand, and as

she and Clare stood side by side at leaving, as if united body and

soul, there would have been something peculiarly sorry in their

aspect to one who should have seen it truly; two limbs of one life,

as they outwardly were, his arm touching hers, her skirts touching

him, facing one way, as against all the dairy facing the other,

speaking in their adieux as "we", and yet sundered like the poles.

Perhaps something unusually stiff and embarrassed in their attitude,

some awkwardness in acting up to their profession of unity, different

from the natural shyness of young couples, may have been apparent,

for when they were gone Mrs Crick said to her husband--

"How onnatural the brightness of her eyes did seem, and how they

stood like waxen images and talked as if they were in a dream!

Didn't it strike 'ee that 'twas so? Tess had always sommat strange

in her, and she's not now quite like the proud young bride of a

well-be-doing man."

They re-entered the vehicle, and were driven along the roads towards

Weatherbury and Stagfoot Lane, till they reached the Lane inn, where

Clare dismissed the fly and man. They rested here a while, and

entering the Vale were next driven onward towards her home by a

stranger who did not know their relations. At a midway point, when

Nuttlebury had been passed, and where there were cross-roads, Clare

stopped the conveyance and said to Tess that if she meant to return

to her mother's house it was here that he would leave her. As they

could not talk with freedom in the driver's presence he asked her to

accompany him for a few steps on foot along one of the branch roads;

she assented, and directing the man to wait a few minutes they

strolled away.

"Now, let us understand each other," he said gently. "There is no

anger between us, though there is that which I cannot endure at

present. I will try to bring myself to endure it. I will let you

know where I go to as soon as I know myself. And if I can bring

myself to bear it--if it is desirable, possible--I will come to you.

But until I come to you it will be better that you should not try to

come to me."

The severity of the decree seemed deadly to Tess; she saw his view of

her clearly enough; he could regard her in no other light than that

of one who had practised gross deceit upon him. Yet could a woman

who had done even what she had done deserve all this? But she could

contest the point with him no further. She simply repeated after him

his own words.

"Until you come to me I must not try to come to you?"

"Just so."

"May I write to you?"

"O yes--if you are ill, or want anything at all. I hope that will

not be the case; so that it may happen that I write first to you."

"I agree to the conditions, Angel; because you know best what my

punishment ought to be; only--only--don't make it more than I can

bear!"

That was all she said on the matter. If Tess had been artful, had

she made a scene, fainted, wept hysterically, in that lonely lane,

notwithstanding the fury of fastidiousness with which he was

possessed, he would probably not have withstood her. But her mood

of long-suffering made his way easy for him, and she herself was

his best advocate. Pride, too, entered into her submission--which

perhaps was a symptom of that reckless acquiescence in chance too

apparent in the whole d'Urberville family--and the many effective

chords which she could have stirred by an appeal were left untouched.

The remainder of their discourse was on practical matters only. He

now handed her a packet containing a fairly good sum of money, which

he had obtained from his bankers for the purpose. The brilliants,

the interest in which seemed to be Tess's for her life only (if he

understood the wording of the will), he advised her to let him send

to a bank for safety; and to this she readily agreed.

These things arranged, he walked with Tess back to the carriage,

and handed her in. The coachman was paid and told where to drive

her. Taking next his own bag and umbrella--the sole articles he had

brought with him hitherwards--he bade her goodbye; and they parted

there and then.

The fly moved creepingly up a hill, and Clare watched it go with an

unpremeditated hope that Tess would look out of the window for one

moment. But that she never thought of doing, would not have ventured

to do, lying in a half-dead faint inside. Thus he beheld her recede,

and in the anguish of his heart quoted a line from a poet, with

peculiar emendations of his own--

God's NOT in his heaven:

All's WRONG with the world!

When Tess had passed over the crest of the hill he turned to go his

own way, and hardly knew that he loved her still.

XXXVIII

As she drove on through Blackmoor Vale, and the landscape of her

youth began to open around her, Tess aroused herself from her stupor.

Her first thought was how would she be able to face her parents?

She reached a turnpike-gate which stood upon the highway to the

village. It was thrown open by a stranger, not by the old man who

had kept it for many years, and to whom she had been known; he had

probably left on New Year's Day, the date when such changes were

made. Having received no intelligence lately from her home, she

asked the turnpike-keeper for news.

"Oh--nothing, miss," he answered. "Marlott is Marlott still. Folks

have died and that. John Durbeyfield, too, hev had a daughter

married this week to a gentleman-farmer; not from John's own house,

you know; they was married elsewhere; the gentleman being of that

high standing that John's own folk was not considered well-be-doing

enough to have any part in it, the bridegroom seeming not to know

how't have been discovered that John is a old and ancient nobleman

himself by blood, with family skillentons in their own vaults to

this day, but done out of his property in the time o' the Romans.

However, Sir John, as we call 'n now, kept up the wedding-day as well

as he could, and stood treat to everybody in the parish; and John's

wife sung songs at The Pure Drop till past eleven o'clock."

Hearing this, Tess felt so sick at heart that she could not decide

to go home publicly in the fly with her luggage and belongings. She

asked the turnpike-keeper if she might deposit her things at his

house for a while, and, on his offering no objection, she dismissed

her carriage, and went on to the village alone by a back lane.

At sight of her father's chimney she asked herself how she could

possibly enter the house? Inside that cottage her relations were

calmly supposing her far away on a wedding-tour with a comparatively

rich man, who was to conduct her to bouncing prosperity; while here

she was, friendless, creeping up to the old door quite by herself,

with no better place to go to in the world.

She did not reach the house unobserved. Just by the garden-hedge she

was met by a girl who knew her--one of the two or three with whom she

had been intimate at school. After making a few inquiries as to how

Tess came there, her friend, unheeding her tragic look, interrupted

with--

"But where's thy gentleman, Tess?"

Tess hastily explained that he had been called away on business, and,

leaving her interlocutor, clambered over the garden-hedge, and thus

made her way to the house.

As she went up the garden-path she heard her mother singing by the

back door, coming in sight of which she perceived Mrs Durbeyfield on

the doorstep in the act of wringing a sheet. Having performed this

without observing Tess, she went indoors, and her daughter followed

her.

The washing-tub stood in the same old place on the same old

quarter-hogshead, and her mother, having thrown the sheet aside, was

about to plunge her arms in anew.

"Why--Tess!--my chil'--I thought you was married!--married really and

truly this time--we sent the cider--"

"Yes, mother; so I am."

"Going to be?"

"No--I am married."

"Married! Then where's thy husband?"

"Oh, he's gone away for a time."

"Gone away! When was you married, then? The day you said?"

"Yes, Tuesday, mother."

"And now 'tis on'y Saturday, and he gone away?"

"Yes, he's gone."

"What's the meaning o' that? 'Nation seize such husbands as you seem

to get, say I!"

"Mother!" Tess went across to Joan Durbeyfield, laid her face upon

the matron's bosom, and burst into sobs. "I don't know how to tell

'ee, mother! You said to me, and wrote to me, that I was not to tell

him. But I did tell him--I couldn't help it--and he went away!"

"O you little fool--you little fool!" burst out Mrs Durbeyfield,

splashing Tess and herself in her agitation. "My good God! that ever

I should ha' lived to say it, but I say it again, you little fool!"

Tess was convulsed with weeping, the tension of so many days having

relaxed at last.

"I know it--I know--I know!" she gasped through her sobs. "But,

O my mother, I could not help it! He was so good--and I felt

the wickedness of trying to blind him as to what had happened!

If--if--it were to be done again--I should do the same. I could

not--I dared not--so sin--against him!"

"But you sinned enough to marry him first!"

"Yes, yes; that's where my misery do lie! But I thought he could get

rid o' me by law if he were determined not to overlook it. And O, if

you knew--if you could only half know how I loved him--how anxious I

was to have him--and how wrung I was between caring so much for him

and my wish to be fair to him!"

Tess was so shaken that she could get no further, and sank, a

helpless thing, into a chair.

"Well, well; what's done can't be undone! I'm sure I don't know why

children o' my bringing forth should all be bigger simpletons than

other people's--not to know better than to blab such a thing as

that, when he couldn't ha' found it out till too late!" Here Mrs

Durbeyfield began shedding tears on her own account as a mother to

be pitied. "What your father will say I don't know," she continued;

"for he's been talking about the wedding up at Rolliver's and The

Pure Drop every day since, and about his family getting back to their

rightful position through you--poor silly man!--and now you've made

this mess of it! The Lord-a-Lord!"

As if to bring matters to a focus, Tess's father was heard

approaching at that moment. He did not, however, enter immediately,

and Mrs Durbeyfield said that she would break the bad news to him

herself, Tess keeping out of sight for the present. After her first

burst of disappointment Joan began to take the mishap as she had

taken Tess's original trouble, as she would have taken a wet holiday

or failure in the potato-crop; as a thing which had come upon them

irrespective of desert or folly; a chance external impingement to be

borne with; not a lesson.

Tess retreated upstairs and beheld casually that the beds had been

shifted, and new arrangements made. Her old bed had been adapted for

two younger children. There was no place here for her now.

The room below being unceiled she could hear most of what went on

there. Presently her father entered, apparently carrying in a live

hen. He was a foot-haggler now, having been obliged to sell his

second horse, and he travelled with his basket on his arm. The hen

had been carried about this morning as it was often carried, to show

people that he was in his work, though it had lain, with its legs

tied, under the table at Rolliver's for more than an hour.

"We've just had up a story about--" Durbeyfield began, and thereupon

related in detail to his wife a discussion which had arisen at the

inn about the clergy, originated by the fact of his daughter having

married into a clerical family. "They was formerly styled 'sir',

like my own ancestry," he said, "though nowadays their true style,

strictly speaking, is 'clerk' only." As Tess had wished that no

great publicity should be given to the event, he had mentioned no

particulars. He hoped she would remove that prohibition soon. He

proposed that the couple should take Tess's own name, d'Urberville,

as uncorrupted. It was better than her husbands's. He asked if any

letter had come from her that day.

Then Mrs Durbeyfield informed him that no letter had come, but Tess

unfortunately had come herself.

When at length the collapse was explained to him, a sullen

mortification, not usual with Durbeyfield, overpowered the influence

of the cheering glass. Yet the intrinsic quality of the event moved

his touchy sensitiveness less than its conjectured effect upon the

minds of others.

"To think, now, that this was to be the end o't!" said Sir John.

"And I with a family vault under that there church of Kingsbere as

big as Squire Jollard's ale-cellar, and my folk lying there in sixes

and sevens, as genuine county bones and marrow as any recorded in

history. And now to be sure what they fellers at Rolliver's and The

Pure Drop will say to me! How they'll squint and glane, and say,

'This is yer mighty match is it; this is yer getting back to the true

level of yer forefathers in King Norman's time!' I feel this is too

much, Joan; I shall put an end to myself, title and all--I can bear

it no longer! ... But she can make him keep her if he's married

her?"

"Why, yes. But she won't think o' doing that."

"D'ye think he really have married her?--or is it like the first--"

Poor Tess, who had heard as far as this, could not bear to hear more.

The perception that her word could be doubted even here, in her own

parental house, set her mind against the spot as nothing else could

have done. How unexpected were the attacks of destiny! And if her

father doubted her a little, would not neighbours and acquaintance

doubt her much? O, she could not live long at home!

A few days, accordingly, were all that she allowed herself here, at

the end of which time she received a short note from Clare, informing

her that he had gone to the North of England to look at a farm. In

her craving for the lustre of her true position as his wife, and to

hide from her parents the vast extent of the division between them,

she made use of this letter as her reason for again departing,

leaving them under the impression that she was setting out to join

him. Still further to screen her husband from any imputation of

unkindness to her, she took twenty-five of the fifty pounds Clare

had given her, and handed the sum over to her mother, as if the wife

of a man like Angel Clare could well afford it, saying that it was a

slight return for the trouble and humiliation she had brought upon

them in years past. With this assertion of her dignity she bade them

farewell; and after that there were lively doings in the Durbeyfield

household for some time on the strength of Tess's bounty, her mother

saying, and, indeed, believing, that the rupture which had arisen

between the young husband and wife had adjusted itself under their

strong feeling that they could not live apart from each other.

XXXIX

It was three weeks after the marriage that Clare found himself

descending the hill which led to the well-known parsonage of his

father. With his downward course the tower of the church rose into

the evening sky in a manner of inquiry as to why he had come; and no

living person in the twilighted town seemed to notice him, still less

to expect him. He was arriving like a ghost, and the sound of his

own footsteps was almost an encumbrance to be got rid of.

The picture of life had changed for him. Before this time he had

known it but speculatively; now he thought he knew it as a practical

man; though perhaps he did not, even yet. Nevertheless humanity

stood before him no longer in the pensive sweetness of Italian art,

but in the staring and ghastly attitudes of a Wiertz Museum, and with

the leer of a study by Van Beers.

His conduct during these first weeks had been desultory beyond

description. After mechanically attempting to pursue his

agricultural plans as though nothing unusual had happened, in

the manner recommended by the great and wise men of all ages, he

concluded that very few of those great and wise men had ever gone so

far outside themselves as to test the feasibility of their counsel.

"This is the chief thing: be not perturbed," said the Pagan moralist.

That was just Clare's own opinion. But he was perturbed. "Let not

your heart be troubled, neither let it be afraid," said the Nazarene.

Clare chimed in cordially; but his heart was troubled all the same.

How he would have liked to confront those two great thinkers, and

earnestly appeal to them as fellow-man to fellow-men, and ask them

to tell him their method!

His mood transmuted itself into a dogged indifference till at length

he fancied he was looking on his own existence with the passive

interest of an outsider.

He was embittered by the conviction that all this desolation had been

brought about by the accident of her being a d'Urberville. When he

found that Tess came of that exhausted ancient line, and was not of

the new tribes from below, as he had fondly dreamed, why had he not

stoically abandoned her in fidelity to his principles? This was what

he had got by apostasy, and his punishment was deserved.

Then he became weary and anxious, and his anxiety increased. He

wondered if he had treated her unfairly. He ate without knowing that

he ate, and drank without tasting. As the hours dropped past, as the

motive of each act in the long series of bygone days presented itself

to his view, he perceived how intimately the notion of having Tess as

a dear possession was mixed up with all his schemes and words and

ways.

In going hither and thither he observed in the outskirts of a small

town a red-and-blue placard setting forth the great advantages of

the Empire of Brazil as a field for the emigrating agriculturist.

Land was offered there on exceptionally advantageous terms. Brazil

somewhat attracted him as a new idea. Tess could eventually join him

there, and perhaps in that country of contrasting scenes and notions

and habits the conventions would not be so operative which made life

with her seem impracticable to him here. In brief he was strongly

inclined to try Brazil, especially as the season for going thither

was just at hand.

With this view he was returning to Emminster to disclose his plan

to his parents, and to make the best explanation he could make of

arriving without Tess, short of revealing what had actually separated

them. As he reached the door the new moon shone upon his face, just

as the old one had done in the small hours of that morning when he

had carried his wife in his arms across the river to the graveyard

of the monks; but his face was thinner now.

Clare had given his parents no warning of his visit, and his arrival

stirred the atmosphere of the Vicarage as the dive of the kingfisher

stirs a quiet pool. His father and mother were both in the

drawing-room, but neither of his brothers was now at home. Angel

entered, and closed the door quietly behind him.

"But--where's your wife, dear Angel?" cried his mother. "How you

surprise us!"

"She is at her mother's--temporarily. I have come home rather in a

hurry because I've decided to go to Brazil."

"Brazil! Why they are all Roman Catholics there surely!"

"Are they? I hadn't thought of that."

But even the novelty and painfulness of his going to a Papistical

land could not displace for long Mr and Mrs Clare's natural interest

in their son's marriage.

"We had your brief note three weeks ago announcing that it had taken

place," said Mrs Clare, "and your father sent your godmother's gift

to her, as you know. Of course it was best that none of us should be

present, especially as you preferred to marry her from the dairy, and

not at her home, wherever that may be. It would have embarrassed

you, and given us no pleasure. Your bothers felt that very strongly.

Now it is done we do not complain, particularly if she suits you for

the business you have chosen to follow instead of the ministry of the

Gospel. ... Yet I wish I could have seen her first, Angel, or have

known a little more about her. We sent her no present of our own,

not knowing what would best give her pleasure, but you must suppose

it only delayed. Angel, there is no irritation in my mind or your

father's against you for this marriage; but we have thought it much

better to reserve our liking for your wife till we could see her.

And now you have not brought her. It seems strange. What has

happened?"

He replied that it had been thought best by them that she should to

go her parents' home for the present, whilst he came there.

"I don't mind telling you, dear mother," he said, "that I always

meant to keep her away from this house till I should feel she could

some with credit to you. But this idea of Brazil is quite a recent

one. If I do go it will be unadvisable for me to take her on this my

first journey. She will remain at her mother's till I come back."

"And I shall not see her before you start?"

He was afraid they would not. His original plan had been, as he had

said, to refrain from bringing her there for some little while--not

to wound their prejudices--feelings--in any way; and for other

reasons he had adhered to it. He would have to visit home in the

course of a year, if he went out at once; and it would be possible

for them to see her before he started a second time--with her.

A hastily prepared supper was brought in, and Clare made further

exposition of his plans. His mother's disappointment at not seeing

the bride still remained with her. Clare's late enthusiasm for Tess

had infected her through her maternal sympathies, till she had almost

fancied that a good thing could come out of Nazareth--a charming

woman out of Talbothays Dairy. She watched her son as he ate.

"Cannot you describe her? I am sure she is very pretty, Angel."

"Of that there can be no question!" he said, with a zest which

covered its bitterness.

"And that she is pure and virtuous goes without question?"

"Pure and virtuous, of course, she is."

"I can see her quite distinctly. You said the other day that she was

fine in figure; roundly built; had deep red lips like Cupid's bow;

dark eyelashes and brows, an immense rope of hair like a ship's

cable; and large eyes violety-bluey-blackish."

"I did, mother."

"I quite see her. And living in such seclusion she naturally had

scarce ever seen any young man from the world without till she saw

you."

"Scarcely."

"You were her first love?"

"Of course."

"There are worse wives than these simple, rosy-mouthed, robust girls

of the farm. Certainly I could have wished--well, since my son is to

be an agriculturist, it is perhaps but proper that his wife should

have been accustomed to an outdoor life."

His father was less inquisitive; but when the time came for the

chapter from the Bible which was always read before evening prayers,

the Vicar observed to Mrs Clare--

"I think, since Angel has come, that it will be more appropriate to

read the thirty-first of Proverbs than the chapter which we should

have had in the usual course of our reading?"

"Yes, certainly," said Mrs Clare. "The words of King Lemuel" (she

could cite chapter and verse as well as her husband). "My dear son,

your father has decided to read us the chapter in Proverbs in praise

of a virtuous wife. We shall not need to be reminded to apply the

words to the absent one. May Heaven shield her in all her ways!"

A lump rose in Clare's throat. The portable lectern was taken out

from the corner and set in the middle of the fireplace, the two old

servants came in, and Angel's father began to read at the tenth verse

of the aforesaid chapter--

"Who can find a virtuous woman? for her price is far

above rubies. She riseth while it is yet night, and

giveth meat to her household. She girdeth her loins

with strength and strengtheneth her arms. She

perceiveth that her merchandise is good; her candle

goeth not out by night. She looketh well to the ways

of her household, and eateth not the bread of idleness.

Her children arise up and call her blessed; her husband

also, and he praiseth her. Many daughters have done

virtuously, but thou excellest them all."

When prayers were over, his mother said--

"I could not help thinking how very aptly that chapter your dear

father read applied, in some of its particulars, to the woman you

have chosen. The perfect woman, you see, was a working woman; not an

idler; not a fine lady; but one who used her hands and her head and

her heart for the good of others. 'Her children arise up and call

her blessed; her husband also, and he praiseth her. Many daughters

have done virtuously, but she excelleth them all.' Well, I wish I

could have seen her, Angel. Since she is pure and chaste, she would

have been refined enough for me."

Clare could bear this no longer. His eyes were full of tears, which

seemed like drops of molten lead. He bade a quick good night to

these sincere and simple souls whom he loved so well; who knew

neither the world, the flesh, nor the devil in their own hearts, only

as something vague and external to themselves. He went to his own

chamber.

His mother followed him, and tapped at his door. Clare opened it to

discover her standing without, with anxious eyes.

"Angel," she asked, "is there something wrong that you go away so

soon? I am quite sure you are not yourself."

"I am not, quite, mother," said he.

"About her? Now, my son, I know it is that--I know it is about her!

Have you quarrelled in these three weeks?"

"We have not exactly quarrelled," he said. "But we have had a

difference--"

"Angel--is she a young woman whose history will bear investigation?"

With a mother's instinct Mrs Clare had put her finger on the kind of

trouble that would cause such a disquiet as seemed to agitate her

son.

"She is spotless!" he replied; and felt that if it had sent him to

eternal hell there and then he would have told that lie.

"Then never mind the rest. After all, there are few purer things in

nature then an unsullied country maid. Any crudeness of manner which

may offend your more educated sense at first, will, I am sure,

disappear under the influence or your companionship and tuition."

Such terrible sarcasm of blind magnanimity brought home to Clare the

secondary perception that he had utterly wrecked his career by this

marriage, which had not been among his early thoughts after the

disclosure. True, on his own account he cared very little about his

career; but he had wished to make it at least a respectable one on

account of his parents and brothers. And now as he looked into the

candle its flame dumbly expressed to him that it was made to shine on

sensible people, and that it abhorred lighting the face of a dupe and

a failure.

When his agitation had cooled he would be at moments incensed with

his poor wife for causing a situation in which he was obliged to

practise deception on his parents. He almost talked to her in his

anger, as if she had been in the room. And then her cooing voice,

plaintive in expostulation, disturbed the darkness, the velvet touch

of her lips passed over his brow, and he could distinguish in the air

the warmth of her breath.

This night the woman of his belittling deprecations was thinking how

great and good her husband was. But over them both there hung a

deeper shade than the shade which Angel Clare perceived, namely, the

shade of his own limitations. With all his attempted independence of

judgement this advanced and well-meaning young man, a sample product

of the last five-and-twenty years, was yet the slave to custom and

conventionality when surprised back into his early teachings. No

prophet had told him, and he was not prophet enough to tell himself,

that essentially this young wife of his was as deserving of the

praise of King Lemuel as any other woman endowed with the same

dislike of evil, her moral value having to be reckoned not by

achievement but by tendency. Moreover, the figure near at hand

suffers on such occasion, because it shows up its sorriness without

shade; while vague figures afar off are honoured, in that their

distance makes artistic virtues of their stains. In considering

what Tess was not, he overlooked what she was, and forgot that the

defective can be more than the entire.

XL

At breakfast Brazil was the topic, and all endeavoured to take a

hopeful view of Clare's proposed experiment with that country's soil,

notwithstanding the discouraging reports of some farm-labourers who

had emigrated thither and returned home within the twelve months.

After breakfast Clare went into the little town to wind up such

trifling matters as he was concerned with there, and to get from

the local bank all the money he possessed. On his way back he

encountered Miss Mercy Chant by the church, from whose walls she

seemed to be a sort of emanation. She was carrying an armful of

Bibles for her class, and such was her view of life that events which

produced heartache in others wrought beatific smiles upon her--an

enviable result, although, in the opinion of Angel, it was obtained

by a curiously unnatural sacrifice of humanity to mysticism.

She had learnt that he was about to leave England, and observed what

an excellent and promising scheme it seemed to be.

"Yes; it is a likely scheme enough in a commercial sense, no doubt,"

he replied. "But, my dear Mercy, it snaps the continuity of

existence. Perhaps a cloister would be preferable."

"A cloister! O, Angel Clare!"

"Well?"

"Why, you wicked man, a cloister implies a monk, and a monk Roman

Catholicism."

"And Roman Catholicism sin, and sin damnation. Thou art in a parlous

state, Angel Clare."

"_I_ glory in my Protestantism!" she said severely.

Then Clare, thrown by sheer misery into one of the demoniacal moods

in which a man does despite to his true principles, called her close

to him, and fiendishly whispered in her ear the most heterodox ideas

he could think of. His momentary laughter at the horror which

appeared on her fair face ceased when it merged in pain and anxiety

for his welfare.

"Dear Mercy," he said, "you must forgive me. I think I am going

crazy!"

She thought that he was; and thus the interview ended, and Clare

re-entered the Vicarage. With the local banker he deposited the

jewels till happier days should arise. He also paid into the bank

thirty pounds--to be sent to Tess in a few months, as she might

require; and wrote to her at her parents' home in Blackmoor Vale to

inform her of what he had done. This amount, with the sum he had

already placed in her hands--about fifty pounds--he hoped would be

amply sufficient for her wants just at present, particularly as in

an emergency she had been directed to apply to his father.

He deemed it best not to put his parents into communication with her

by informing them of her address; and, being unaware of what had

really happened to estrange the two, neither his father nor his

mother suggested that he should do so. During the day he left the

parsonage, for what he had to complete he wished to get done quickly.

As the last duty before leaving this part of England it was necessary

for him to call at the Wellbridge farmhouse, in which he had spent

with Tess the first three days of their marriage, the trifle of rent

having to be paid, the key given up of the rooms they had occupied,

and two or three small articles fetched away that they had left

behind. It was under this roof that the deepest shadow ever thrown

upon his life had stretched its gloom over him. Yet when he had

unlocked the door of the sitting-room and looked into it, the memory

which returned first upon him was that of their happy arrival on a

similar afternoon, the first fresh sense of sharing a habitation

conjointly, the first meal together, the chatting by the fire with

joined hands.

The farmer and his wife were in the field at the moment of his visit,

and Clare was in the rooms alone for some time. Inwardly swollen

with a renewal of sentiment that he had not quite reckoned with, he

went upstairs to her chamber, which had never been his. The bed

was smooth as she had made it with her own hands on the morning of

leaving. The mistletoe hung under the tester just as he had placed

it. Having been there three or four weeks it was turning colour, and

the leaves and berries were wrinkled. Angel took it down and crushed

it into the grate. Standing there, he for the first time doubted

whether his course in this conjecture had been a wise, much less

a generous, one. But had he not been cruelly blinded? In the

incoherent multitude of his emotions he knelt down at the bedside

wet-eyed. "O Tess! If you had only told me sooner, I would have

forgiven you!" he mourned.

Hearing a footstep below, he rose and went to the top of the stairs.

At the bottom of the flight he saw a woman standing, and on her

turning up her face recognized the pale, dark-eyed Izz Huett.

"Mr Clare," she said, "I've called to see you and Mrs Clare, and to

inquire if ye be well. I thought you might be back here again."

This was a girl whose secret he had guessed, but who had not yet

guessed his; an honest girl who loved him--one who would have made as

good, or nearly as good, a practical farmer's wife as Tess.

"I am here alone," he said; "we are not living here now." Explaining

why he had come, he asked, "Which way are you going home, Izz?"

"I have no home at Talbothays Dairy now, sir," she said.

"Why is that?"

Izz looked down.

"It was so dismal there that I left! I am staying out this way."

She pointed in a contrary direction, the direction in which he was

journeying.

"Well--are you going there now? I can take you if you

wish for a lift."

Her olive complexion grew richer in hue.

"Thank 'ee, Mr Clare," she said.

He soon found the farmer, and settled the account for his rent and

the few other items which had to be considered by reason of the

sudden abandonment of the lodgings. On Clare's return to his horse

and gig, Izz jumped up beside him.

"I am going to leave England, Izz," he said, as they drove on.

"Going to Brazil."

"And do Mrs Clare like the notion of such a journey?" she asked.

"She is not going at present--say for a year or so. I am going out

to reconnoitre--to see what life there is like."

They sped along eastward for some considerable distance, Izz making

no observation.

"How are the others?" he inquired. "How is Retty?"

"She was in a sort of nervous state when I zid her last; and so thin

and hollow-cheeked that 'a do seem in a decline. Nobody will ever

fall in love wi' her any more," said Izz absently.

"And Marian?"

Izz lowered her voice.

"Marian drinks."

"Indeed!"

"Yes. The dairyman has got rid of her."

"And you!"

"I don't drink, and I bain't in a decline. But--I am no great things

at singing afore breakfast now!"

"How is that? Do you remember how neatly you used to turn ''Twas

down in Cupid's Gardens' and 'The Tailor's Breeches' at morning

milking?"

"Ah, yes! When you first came, sir, that was. Not when you had been

there a bit."

"Why was that falling-off?"

Her black eyes flashed up to his face for one moment by way of

answer.

"Izz!--how weak of you--for such as I!" he said, and fell into

reverie. "Then--suppose I had asked YOU to marry me?"

"If you had I should have said 'Yes', and you would have married a

woman who loved 'ee!"

"Really!"

"Down to the ground!" she whispered vehemently. "O my God! did you

never guess it till now!"

By-and-by they reached a branch road to a village.

"I must get down. I live out there," said Izz abruptly, never having

spoken since her avowal.

Clare slowed the horse. He was incensed against his fate, bitterly

disposed towards social ordinances; for they had cooped him up in a

corner, out of which there was no legitimate pathway. Why not be

revenged on society by shaping his future domesticities loosely,

instead of kissing the pedagogic rod of convention in this ensnaring

manner?

"I am going to Brazil alone, Izz," said he. "I have separated from

my wife for personal, not voyaging, reasons. I may never live with

her again. I may not be able to love you; but--will you go with me

instead of her?"

"You truly wish me to go?"

"I do. I have been badly used enough to wish for relief. And you at

least love me disinterestedly."

"Yes--I will go," said Izz, after a pause.

"You will? You know what it means, Izz?"

"It means that I shall live with you for the time you are over

there--that's good enough for me."

"Remember, you are not to trust me in morals now. But I ought

to remind you that it will be wrong-doing in the eyes of

civilization--Western civilization, that is to say."

"I don't mind that; no woman do when it comes to agony-point, and

there's no other way!"

"Then don't get down, but sit where you are."

He drove past the cross-roads, one mile, two miles, without showing

any signs of affection.

"You love me very, very much, Izz?" he suddenly asked.

"I do--I have said I do! I loved you all the time we was at the

dairy together!"

"More than Tess?"

She shook her head.

"No," she murmured, "not more than she."

"How's that?"

"Because nobody could love 'ee more than Tess did! ... She would

have laid down her life for 'ee. I could do no more."

Like the prophet on the top of Peor, Izz Huett would fain have spoken

perversely at such a moment, but the fascination exercised over her

rougher nature by Tess's character compelled her to grace.

Clare was silent; his heart had risen at these straightforward words

from such an unexpected unimpeachable quarter. In his throat was

something as if a sob had solidified there. His ears repeated, "SHE

WOULD HAVE LAID DOWN HER LIFE FOR 'EE. I COULD DO NO MORE!"

"Forget our idle talk, Izz," he said, turning the horse's head

suddenly. "I don't know what I've been saying! I will now drive

you back to where your lane branches off."

"So much for honesty towards 'ee! O--how can I bear it--how can

I--how can I!"

Izz Huett burst into wild tears, and beat her forehead as she saw

what she had done.

"Do you regret that poor little act of justice to an absent one?

O, Izz, don't spoil it by regret!"

She stilled herself by degrees.

"Very well, sir. Perhaps I didn't know what I was saying, either,

wh--when I agreed to go! I wish--what cannot be!"

"Because I have a loving wife already."

"Yes, yes! You have!"

They reached the corner of the lane which they had passed half an

hour earlier, and she hopped down.

"Izz--please, please forget my momentary levity!" he cried. "It was

so ill-considered, so ill-advised!"

"Forget it? Never, never! O, it was no levity to me!"

He felt how richly he deserved the reproach that the wounded cry

conveyed, and, in a sorrow that was inexpressible, leapt down and

took her hand.

"Well, but, Izz, we'll part friends, anyhow? You don't know what

I've had to bear!"

She was a really generous girl, and allowed no further bitterness to

mar their adieux.

"I forgive 'ee, sir!" she said.

"Now, Izz," he said, while she stood beside him there, forcing

himself to the mentor's part he was far from feeling; "I want you to

tell Marian when you see her that she is to be a good woman, and not

to give way to folly. Promise that, and tell Retty that there are

more worthy men than I in the world, that for my sake she is to act

wisely and well--remember the words--wisely and well--for my sake.

I send this message to them as a dying man to the dying; for I shall

never see them again. And you, Izzy, you have saved me by your

honest words about my wife from an incredible impulse towards folly

and treachery. Women may be bad, but they are not so bad as men in

these things! On that one account I can never forget you. Be always

the good and sincere girl you have hitherto been; and think of me as

a worthless lover, but a faithful friend. Promise."

She gave the promise.

"Heaven bless and keep you, sir. Goodbye!"

He drove on; but no sooner had Izz turned into the lane, and Clare

was out of sight, than she flung herself down on the bank in a fit of

racking anguish; and it was with a strained unnatural face that she

entered her mother's cottage late that night. Nobody ever was told

how Izz spent the dark hours that intervened between Angel Clare's

parting from her and her arrival home.

Clare, too, after bidding the girl farewell, was wrought to aching

thoughts and quivering lips. But his sorrow was not for Izz. That

evening he was within a feather-weight's turn of abandoning his road

to the nearest station, and driving across that elevated dorsal line

of South Wessex which divided him from his Tess's home. It was

neither a contempt for her nature, nor the probable state of her

heart, which deterred him.

No; it was a sense that, despite her love, as corroborated by Izz's

admission, the facts had not changed. If he was right at first,

he was right now. And the momentum of the course on which he

had embarked tended to keep him going in it, unless diverted by

a stronger, more sustained force than had played upon him this

afternoon. He could soon come back to her. He took the train that

night for London, and five days after shook hands in farewell of his

brothers at the port of embarkation.

XLI

From the foregoing events of the winter-time let us press on to

an October day, more than eight months subsequent to the parting

of Clare and Tess. We discover the latter in changed conditions;

instead of a bride with boxes and trunks which others bore, we see

her a lonely woman with a basket and a bundle in her own porterage,

as at an earlier time when she was no bride; instead of the ample

means that were projected by her husband for her comfort through

this probationary period, she can produce only a flattened purse.

After again leaving Marlott, her home, she had got through the

spring and summer without any great stress upon her physical powers,

the time being mainly spent in rendering light irregular service

at dairy-work near Port-Bredy to the west of the Blackmoor Valley,

equally remote from her native place and from Talbothays. She

preferred this to living on his allowance. Mentally she remained in

utter stagnation, a condition which the mechanical occupation rather

fostered than checked. Her consciousness was at that other dairy,

at that other season, in the presence of the tender lover who had

confronted her there--he who, the moment she had grasped him to keep

for her own, had disappeared like a shape in a vision.

The dairy-work lasted only till the milk began to lessen, for she

had not met with a second regular engagement as at Talbothays, but

had done duty as a supernumerary only. However, as harvest was now

beginning, she had simply to remove from the pasture to the stubble

to find plenty of further occupation, and this continued till harvest

was done.

Of the five-and-twenty pounds which had remained to her of Clare's

allowance, after deducting the other half of the fifty as a

contribution to her parents for the trouble and expense to which

she had put them, she had as yet spent but little. But there now

followed an unfortunate interval of wet weather, during which she was

obliged to fall back upon her sovereigns.

She could not bear to let them go. Angel had put them into her hand,

had obtained them bright and new from his bank for her; his touch had

consecrated them to souvenirs of himself--they appeared to have had

as yet no other history than such as was created by his and her own

experiences--and to disperse them was like giving away relics. But

she had to do it, and one by one they left her hands.

She had been compelled to send her mother her address from time to

time, but she concealed her circumstances. When her money had almost

gone a letter from her mother reached her. Joan stated that they

were in dreadful difficulty; the autumn rains had gone through the

thatch of the house, which required entire renewal; but this could

not be done because the previous thatching had never been paid for.

New rafters and a new ceiling upstairs also were required, which,

with the previous bill, would amount to a sum of twenty pounds. As

her husband was a man of means, and had doubtless returned by this

time, could she not send them the money?

Tess had thirty pounds coming to her almost immediately from Angel's

bankers, and, the case being so deplorable, as soon as the sum was

received she sent the twenty as requested. Part of the remainder

she was obliged to expend in winter clothing, leaving only a nominal

sum for the whole inclement season at hand. When the last pound

had gone, a remark of Angel's that whenever she required further

resources she was to apply to his father, remained to be considered.

But the more Tess thought of the step, the more reluctant was she to

take it. The same delicacy, pride, false shame, whatever it may be

called, on Clare's account, which had led her to hide from her own

parents the prolongation of the estrangement, hindered her owning to

his that she was in want after the fair allowance he had left her.

They probably despised her already; how much more they would despise

her in the character of a mendicant! The consequence was that by no

effort could the parson's daughter-in-law bring herself to let him

know her state.

Her reluctance to communicate with her husband's parents might,

she thought, lessen with the lapse of time; but with her own the

reverse obtained. On her leaving their house after the short visit

subsequent to her marriage they were under the impression that she

was ultimately going to join her husband; and from that time to the

present she had done nothing to disturb their belief that she was

awaiting his return in comfort, hoping against hope that his journey

to Brazil would result in a short stay only, after which he would

come to fetch her, or that he would write for her to join him; in any

case that they would soon present a united front to their families

and the world. This hope she still fostered. To let her parents

know that she was a deserted wife, dependent, now that she had

relieved their necessities, on her own hands for a living, after the

_clat_ of a marriage which was to nullify the collapse of the first

attempt, would be too much indeed.

The set of brilliants returned to her mind. Where Clare had

deposited them she did not know, and it mattered little, if it were

true that she could only use and not sell them. Even were they

absolutely hers it would be passing mean to enrich herself by a legal

title to them which was not essentially hers at all.

Meanwhile her husband's days had been by no means free from trial.

At this moment he was lying ill of fever in the clay lands near

Curitiba in Brazil, having been drenched with thunder-storms and

persecuted by other hardships, in common with all the English farmers

and farm-labourers who, just at this time, were deluded into going

thither by the promises of the Brazilian Government, and by the

baseless assumption that those frames which, ploughing and sowing on

English uplands, had resisted all the weathers to whose moods they

had been born, could resist equally well all the weathers by which

they were surprised on Brazilian plains.

To return. Thus it happened that when the last of Tess's sovereigns

had been spent she was unprovided with others to take their place,

while on account of the season she found it increasingly difficult

to get employment. Not being aware of the rarity of intelligence,

energy, health, and willingness in any sphere of life, she refrained

from seeking an indoor occupation; fearing towns, large houses,

people of means and social sophistication, and of manners other

than rural. From that direction of gentility Black Care had come.

Society might be better than she supposed from her slight experience

of it. But she had no proof of this, and her instinct in the

circumstances was to avoid its purlieus.

The small dairies to the west, beyond Port-Bredy, in which she

had served as supernumerary milkmaid during the spring and summer

required no further aid. Room would probably have been made for her

at Talbothays, if only out of sheer compassion; but comfortable as

her life had been there, she could not go back. The anti-climax

would be too intolerable; and her return might bring reproach upon

her idolized husband. She could not have borne their pity, and their

whispered remarks to one another upon her strange situation; though

she would almost have faced a knowledge of her circumstances by every

individual there, so long as her story had remained isolated in the

mind of each. It was the interchange of ideas about her that made

her sensitiveness wince. Tess could not account for this

distinction; she simply knew that she felt it.

She was now on her way to an upland farm in the centre of the county,

to which she had been recommended by a wandering letter which had

reached her from Marian. Marian had somehow heard that Tess was

separated from her husband--probably through Izz Huett--and the

good-natured and now tippling girl, deeming Tess in trouble, had

hastened to notify to her former friend that she herself had gone to

this upland spot after leaving the dairy, and would like to see her

there, where there was room for other hands, if it was really true

that she worked again as of old.

With the shortening of the days all hope of obtaining her husband's

forgiveness began to leave her; and there was something of the

habitude of the wild animal in the unreflecting instinct with which

she rambled on--disconnecting herself by littles from her eventful

past at every step, obliterating her identity, giving no thought to

accidents or contingencies which might make a quick discovery of her

whereabouts by others of importance to her own happiness, if not to

theirs.

Among the difficulties of her lonely position not the least was

the attention she excited by her appearance, a certain bearing of

distinction, which she had caught from Clare, being superadded to her

natural attractiveness. Whilst the clothes lasted which had been

prepared for her marriage, these casual glances of interest caused

her no inconvenience, but as soon as she was compelled to don the

wrapper of a fieldwoman, rude words were addressed to her more than

once; but nothing occurred to cause her bodily fear till a particular

November afternoon.

She had preferred the country west of the River Brit to the upland

farm for which she was now bound, because, for one thing, it was

nearer to the home of her husband's father; and to hover about that

region unrecognized, with the notion that she might decide to call at

the Vicarage some day, gave her pleasure. But having once decided to

try the higher and drier levels, she pressed back eastward, marching

afoot towards the village of Chalk-Newton, where she meant to pass

the night.

The lane was long and unvaried, and, owing to the rapid shortening of

the days, dusk came upon her before she was aware. She had reached

the top of a hill down which the lane stretched its serpentine length

in glimpses, when she heard footsteps behind her back, and in a few

moments she was overtaken by a man. He stepped up alongside Tess and

said--

"Good night, my pretty maid": to which she civilly replied.

The light still remaining in the sky lit up her face, though the

landscape was nearly dark. The man turned and stared hard at her.

"Why, surely, it is the young wench who was at Trantridge awhile--

young Squire d'Urberville's friend? I was there at that time, though

I don't live there now."

She recognized in him the well-to-do boor whom Angel had knocked down

at the inn for addressing her coarsely. A spasm of anguish shot

through her, and she returned him no answer.

"Be honest enough to own it, and that what I said in the town was

true, though your fancy-man was so up about it--hey, my sly one? You

ought to beg my pardon for that blow of his, considering."

Still no answer came from Tess. There seemed only one escape for her

hunted soul. She suddenly took to her heels with the speed of the

wind, and, without looking behind her, ran along the road till she

came to a gate which opened directly into a plantation. Into this

she plunged, and did not pause till she was deep enough in its shade

to be safe against any possibility of discovery.

Under foot the leaves were dry, and the foliage of some holly bushes

which grew among the deciduous trees was dense enough to keep off

draughts. She scraped together the dead leaves till she had formed

them into a large heap, making a sort of nest in the middle. Into

this Tess crept.

Such sleep as she got was naturally fitful; she fancied she heard

strange noises, but persuaded herself that they were caused by the

breeze. She thought of her husband in some vague warm clime on the

other side of the globe, while she was here in the cold. Was there

another such a wretched being as she in the world? Tess asked

herself; and, thinking of her wasted life, said, "All is vanity."

She repeated the words mechanically, till she reflected that this

was a most inadequate thought for modern days. Solomon had thought

as far as that more than two thousand years ago; she herself,

though not in the van of thinkers, had got much further. If all

were only vanity, who would mind it? All was, alas, worse than

vanity--injustice, punishment, exaction, death. The wife of Angel

Clare put her hand to her brow, and felt its curve, and the edges of

her eye-sockets perceptible under the soft skin, and thought as she

did so that a time would come when that bone would be bare. "I wish

it were now," she said.

In the midst of these whimsical fancies she heard a new strange sound

among the leaves. It might be the wind; yet there was scarcely any

wind. Sometimes it was a palpitation, sometimes a flutter; sometimes

it was a sort of gasp or gurgle. Soon she was certain that the

noises came from wild creatures of some kind, the more so when,

originating in the boughs overhead, they were followed by the fall

of a heavy body upon the ground. Had she been ensconced here under

other and more pleasant conditions she would have become alarmed;

but, outside humanity, she had at present no fear.

Day at length broke in the sky. When it had been day aloft for some

little while it became day in the wood.

Directly the assuring and prosaic light of the world's active hours

had grown strong, she crept from under her hillock of leaves, and

looked around boldly. Then she perceived what had been going on to

disturb her. The plantation wherein she had taken shelter ran down

at this spot into a peak, which ended it hitherward, outside the

hedge being arable ground. Under the trees several pheasants lay

about, their rich plumage dabbled with blood; some were dead, some

feebly twitching a wing, some staring up at the sky, some pulsating

quickly, some contorted, some stretched out--all of them writhing in

agony, except the fortunate ones whose tortures had ended during the

night by the inability of nature to bear more.

Tess guessed at once the meaning of this. The birds had been driven

down into this corner the day before by some shooting-party; and

while those that had dropped dead under the shot, or had died before

nightfall, had been searched for and carried off, many badly wounded

birds had escaped and hidden themselves away, or risen among the

thick boughs, where they had maintained their position till they grew

weaker with loss of blood in the night-time, when they had fallen one

by one as she had heard them.

She had occasionally caught glimpses of these men in girlhood,

looking over hedges, or peeping through bushes, and pointing their

guns, strangely accoutred, a bloodthirsty light in their eyes. She

had been told that, rough and brutal as they seemed just then, they

were not like this all the year round, but were, in fact, quite civil

persons save during certain weeks of autumn and winter, when, like

the inhabitants of the Malay Peninsula, they ran amuck, and made

it their purpose to destroy life--in this case harmless feathered

creatures, brought into being by artificial means solely to gratify

these propensities--at once so unmannerly and so unchivalrous towards

their weaker fellows in Nature's teeming family.

With the impulse of a soul who could feel for kindred sufferers as

much as for herself, Tess's first thought was to put the still living

birds out of their torture, and to this end with her own hands she

broke the necks of as many as she could find, leaving them to lie

where she had found them till the game-keepers should come--as they

probably would come--to look for them a second time.

"Poor darlings--to suppose myself the most miserable being on earth

in the sight o' such misery as yours!" she exclaimed, her tears

running down as she killed the birds tenderly. "And not a twinge of

bodily pain about me! I be not mangled, and I be not bleeding, and

I have two hands to feed and clothe me." She was ashamed of herself

for her gloom of the night, based on nothing more tangible than a

sense of condemnation under an arbitrary law of society which had no

foundation in Nature.

XLII

It was now broad day, and she started again, emerging cautiously upon

the highway. But there was no need for caution; not a soul was at

hand, and Tess went onward with fortitude, her recollection of the

birds' silent endurance of their night of agony impressing upon her

the relativity of sorrows and the tolerable nature of her own, if she

could once rise high enough to despise opinion. But that she could

not do so long as it was held by Clare.

She reached Chalk-Newton, and breakfasted at an inn, where several

young men were troublesomely complimentary to her good looks.

Somehow she felt hopeful, for was it not possible that her husband

also might say these same things to her even yet? She was bound to

take care of herself on the chance of it, and keep off these casual

lovers. To this end Tess resolved to run no further risks from her

appearance. As soon as she got out of the village she entered a

thicket and took from her basket one of the oldest field-gowns, which

she had never put on even at the dairy--never since she had worked

among the stubble at Marlott. She also, by a felicitous thought,

took a handkerchief from her bundle and tied it round her face under

her bonnet, covering her chin and half her cheeks and temples, as if

she were suffering from toothache. Then with her little scissors,

by the aid of a pocket looking-glass, she mercilessly nipped her

eyebrows off, and thus insured against aggressive admiration, she

went on her uneven way.

"What a mommet of a maid!" said the next man who met her to a

companion.

Tears came into her eyes for very pity of herself as she heard him.

"But I don't care!" she said. "O no--I don't care! I'll always be

ugly now, because Angel is not here, and I have nobody to take care

of me. My husband that was is gone away, and never will love me any

more; but I love him just the same, and hate all other men, and like

to make 'em think scornfully of me!"

Thus Tess walks on; a figure which is part of the landscape; a

fieldwoman pure and simple, in winter guise; a gray serge cape, a

red woollen cravat, a stuff skirt covered by a whitey-brown rough

wrapper, and buff-leather gloves. Every thread of that old attire

has become faded and thin under the stroke of raindrops, the burn of

sunbeams, and the stress of winds. There is no sign of young passion

in her now--

The maiden's mouth is cold

. . .

Fold over simple fold

Binding her head.

Inside this exterior, over which the eye might have roved as over a

thing scarcely percipient, almost inorganic, there was the record of

a pulsing life which had learnt too well, for its years, of the dust

and ashes of things, of the cruelty of lust and the fragility of

love.

Next day the weather was bad, but she trudged on, the honesty,

directness, and impartiality of elemental enmity disconcerting her

but little. Her object being a winter's occupation and a winter's

home, there was no time to lose. Her experience of short hirings

had been such that she was determined to accept no more.

Thus she went forward from farm to farm in the direction of the place

whence Marian had written to her, which she determined to make use of

as a last shift only, its rumoured stringencies being the reverse of

tempting. First she inquired for the lighter kinds of employment,

and, as acceptance in any variety of these grew hopeless, applied

next for the less light, till, beginning with the dairy and poultry

tendance that she liked best, she ended with the heavy and course

pursuits which she liked least--work on arable land: work of such

roughness, indeed, as she would never have deliberately voluteered

for.

Towards the second evening she reached the irregular chalk table-land

or plateau, bosomed with semi-globular tumuli--as if Cybele the

Many-breasted were supinely extended there--which stretched between

the valley of her birth and the valley of her love.

Here the air was dry and cold, and the long cart-roads were blown

white and dusty within a few hours after rain. There were few trees,

or none, those that would have grown in the hedges being mercilessly

plashed down with the quickset by the tenant-farmers, the natural

enemies of tree, bush, and brake. In the middle distance ahead of

her she could see the summits of Bulbarrow and of Nettlecombe Tout,

and they seemed friendly. They had a low and unassuming aspect from

this upland, though as approached on the other side from Blackmoor

in her childhood they were as lofty bastions against the sky.

Southerly, at many miles' distance, and over the hills and ridges

coastward, she could discern a surface like polished steel: it was

the English Channel at a point far out towards France.

Before her, in a slight depression, were the remains of a village.

She had, in fact, reached Flintcomb-Ash, the place of Marian's

sojourn. There seemed to be no help for it; hither she was doomed to

come. The stubborn soil around her showed plainly enough that the

kind of labour in demand here was of the roughest kind; but it was

time to rest from searching, and she resolved to stay, particularly

as it began to rain. At the entrance to the village was a cottage

whose gable jutted into the road, and before applying for a lodging

she stood under its shelter, and watched the evening close in.

"Who would think I was Mrs Angel Clare!" she said.

The wall felt warm to her back and shoulders, and she found that

immediately within the gable was the cottage fireplace, the heat of

which came through the bricks. She warmed her hands upon them, and

also put her cheek--red and moist with the drizzle--against their

comforting surface. The wall seemed to be the only friend she had.

She had so little wish to leave it that she could have stayed there

all night.

Tess could hear the occupants of the cottage--gathered together after

their day's labour--talking to each other within, and the rattle of

their supper-plates was also audible. But in the village-street she

had seen no soul as yet. The solitude was at last broken by the

approach of one feminine figure, who, though the evening was cold,

wore the print gown and the tilt-bonnet of summer time. Tess

instinctively thought it might be Marian, and when she came near

enough to be distinguishable in the gloom, surely enough it was

she. Marian was even stouter and redder in the face than formerly,

and decidedly shabbier in attire. At any previous period of her

existence Tess would hardly have cared to renew the acquaintance in

such conditions; but her loneliness was excessive, and she responded

readily to Marian's greeting.

Marian was quite respectful in her inquiries, but seemed much moved

by the fact that Tess should still continue in no better condition

than at first; though she had dimly heard of the separation.

"Tess--Mrs Clare--the dear wife of dear he! And is it really so bad

as this, my child? Why is your cwomely face tied up in such a way?

Anybody been beating 'ee? Not HE?"

"No, no, no! I merely did it not to be clipsed or colled, Marian."

She pulled off in disgust a bandage which could suggest such wild

thoughts.

"And you've got no collar on" (Tess had been accustomed to wear a

little white collar at the dairy).

"I know it, Marian."

"You've lost it travelling."

"I've not lost it. The truth is, I don't care anything about my

looks; and so I didn't put it on."

"And you don't wear your wedding-ring?"

"Yes, I do; but not in public. I wear it round my neck on a ribbon.

I don't wish people to think who I am by marriage, or that I am

married at all; it would be so awkward while I lead my present life."

Marian paused.

"But you BE a gentleman's wife; and it seems hardly fair that you

should live like this!"

"O yes it is, quite fair; though I am very unhappy."

"Well, well. HE married you--and you can be unhappy!"

"Wives are unhappy sometimes; from no fault of their husbands--from

their own."

"You've no faults, deary; that I'm sure of. And he's none. So it

must be something outside ye both."

"Marian, dear Marian, will you do me a good turn without asking

questions? My husband has gone abroad, and somehow I have overrun my

allowance, so that I have to fall back upon my old work for a time.

Do not call me Mrs Clare, but Tess, as before. Do they want a hand

here?"

"O yes; they'll take one always, because few care to come. 'Tis a

starve-acre place. Corn and swedes are all they grow. Though I be

here myself, I feel 'tis a pity for such as you to come."

"But you used to be as good a dairywoman as I."

"Yes; but I've got out o' that since I took to drink. Lord, that's

the only comfort I've got now! If you engage, you'll be set

swede-hacking. That's what I be doing; but you won't like it."

"O--anything! Will you speak for me?"

"You will do better by speaking for yourself."

"Very well. Now, Marian, remember--nothing about HIM if I get the

place. I don't wish to bring his name down to the dirt."

Marian, who was really a trustworthy girl though of coarser grain

than Tess, promised anything she asked.

"This is pay-night," she said, "and if you were to come with me you

would know at once. I be real sorry that you are not happy; but 'tis

because he's away, I know. You couldn't be unhappy if he were here,

even if he gie'd ye no money--even if he used you like a drudge."

"That's true; I could not!"

They walked on together and soon reached the farmhouse, which was

almost sublime in its dreariness. There was not a tree within sight;

there was not, at this season, a green pasture--nothing but fallow

and turnips everywhere, in large fields divided by hedges plashed to

unrelieved levels.

Tess waited outside the door of the farmhouse till the group of

workfolk had received their wages, and then Marian introduced her.

The farmer himself, it appeared, was not at home, but his wife, who

represented him this evening, made no objection to hiring Tess, on

her agreeing to remain till Old Lady-Day. Female field-labour was

seldom offered now, and its cheapness made it profitable for tasks

which women could perform as readily as men.

Having signed the agreement, there was nothing more for Tess to do

at present than to get a lodging, and she found one in the house at

whose gable-wall she had warmed herself. It was a poor subsistence

that she had ensured, but it would afford a shelter for the winter

at any rate.

That night she wrote to inform her parents of her new address, in

case a letter should arrive at Marlott from her husband. But she

did not tell them of the sorriness of her situation: it might have

brought reproach upon him.

XLIII

There was no exaggeration in Marian's definition of Flintcomb-Ash

farm as a starve-acre place. The single fat thing on the soil was

Marian herself; and she was an importation. Of the three classes of

village, the village cared for by its lord, the village cared for by

itself, and the village uncared for either by itself or by its lord

(in other words, the village of a resident squires's tenantry, the

village of free- or copy-holders, and the absentee-owner's village,

farmed with the land) this place, Flintcomb-Ash, was the third.

But Tess set to work. Patience, that blending of moral courage with

physical timidity, was now no longer a minor feature in Mrs Angel

Clare; and it sustained her.

The swede-field in which she and her companion were set hacking was

a stretch of a hundred odd acres in one patch, on the highest ground

of the farm, rising above stony lanchets or lynchets--the outcrop of

siliceous veins in the chalk formation, composed of myriads of loose

white flints in bulbous, cusped, and phallic shapes. The upper half

of each turnip had been eaten off by the live-stock, and it was the

business of the two women to grub up the lower or earthy half of the

root with a hooked fork called a hacker, that it might be eaten also.

Every leaf of the vegetable having already been consumed, the whole

field was in colour a desolate drab; it was a complexion without

features, as if a face, from chin to brow, should be only an expanse

of skin. The sky wore, in another colour, the same likeness; a white

vacuity of countenance with the lineaments gone. So these two upper

and nether visages confronted each other all day long, the white face

looking down on the brown face, and the brown face looking up at the

white face, without anything standing between them but the two girls

crawling over the surface of the former like flies.

Nobody came near them, and their movements showed a mechanical

regularity; their forms standing enshrouded in Hessian "wroppers"--

sleeved brown pinafores, tied behind to the bottom, to keep their

gowns from blowing about--scant skirts revealing boots that reached

high up the ankles, and yellow sheepskin gloves with gauntlets. The

pensive character which the curtained hood lent to their bent heads

would have reminded the observer of some early Italian conception of

the two Marys.

They worked on hour after hour, unconscious of the forlorn aspect

they bore in the landscape, not thinking of the justice or injustice

of their lot. Even in such a position as theirs it was possible

to exist in a dream. In the afternoon the rain came on again, and

Marian said that they need not work any more. But if they did not

work they would not be paid; so they worked on. It was so high a

situation, this field, that the rain had no occasion to fall, but

raced along horizontally upon the yelling wind, sticking into them

like glass splinters till they were wet through. Tess had not

known till now what was really meant by that. There are degrees of

dampness, and a very little is called being wet through in common

talk. But to stand working slowly in a field, and feel the creep of

rain-water, first in legs and shoulders, then on hips and head, then

at back, front, and sides, and yet to work on till the leaden light

diminishes and marks that the sun is down, demands a distinct modicum

of stoicism, even of valour.

Yet they did not feel the wetness so much as might be supposed. They

were both young, and they were talking of the time when they lived

and loved together at Talbothays Dairy, that happy green tract of

land where summer had been liberal in her gifts; in substance to

all, emotionally to these. Tess would fain not have conversed with

Marian of the man who was legally, if not actually, her husband;

but the irresistible fascination of the subject betrayed her into

reciprocating Marian's remarks. And thus, as has been said, though

the damp curtains of their bonnets flapped smartly into their faces,

and their wrappers clung about them to wearisomeness, they lived all

this afternoon in memories of green, sunny, romantic Talbothays.

"You can see a gleam of a hill within a few miles o' Froom Valley

from here when 'tis fine," said Marian.

"Ah! Can you?" said Tess, awake to the new value of this locality.

So the two forces were at work here as everywhere, the inherent will

to enjoy, and the circumstantial will against enjoyment. Marian's

will had a method of assisting itself by taking from her pocket as

the afternoon wore on a pint bottle corked with white rag, from which

she invited Tess to drink. Tess's unassisted power of dreaming,

however, being enough for her sublimation at present, she declined

except the merest sip, and then Marian took a pull from the spirits.

"I've got used to it," she said, "and can't leave it off now. 'Tis

my only comfort--You see I lost him: you didn't; and you can do

without it perhaps."

Tess thought her loss as great as Marian's, but upheld by the dignity

of being Angel's wife, in the letter at least, she accepted Marian's

differentiation.

Amid this scene Tess slaved in the morning frosts and in

the afternoon rains. When it was not swede-grubbing it was

swede-trimming, in which process they sliced off the earth and the

fibres with a bill-hook before storing the roots for future use. At

this occupation they could shelter themselves by a thatched hurdle if

it rained; but if it was frosty even their thick leather gloves could

not prevent the frozen masses they handled from biting their fingers.

Still Tess hoped. She had a conviction that sooner or later the

magnanimity which she persisted in reckoning as a chief ingredient

of Clare's character would lead him to rejoin her.

Marian, primed to a humorous mood, would discover the queer-shaped

flints aforesaid, and shriek with laughter, Tess remaining severely

obtuse. They often looked across the country to where the Var or

Froom was know to stretch, even though they might not be able to see

it; and, fixing their eyes on the cloaking gray mist, imagined the

old times they had spent out there.

"Ah," said Marian, "how I should like another or two of our old set

to come here! Then we could bring up Talbothays every day here

afield, and talk of he, and of what nice times we had there, and o'

the old things we used to know, and make it all come back a'most, in

seeming!" Marian's eyes softened, and her voice grew vague as the

visions returned. "I'll write to Izz Huett," she said. "She's

biding at home doing nothing now, I know, and I'll tell her we be

here, and ask her to come; and perhaps Retty is well enough now."

Tess had nothing to say against the proposal, and the next she heard

of this plan for importing old Talbothays' joys was two or three days

later, when Marian informed her that Izz had replied to her inquiry,

and had promised to come if she could.

There had not been such a winter for years. It came on in stealthy

and measured glides, like the moves of a chess-player. One morning

the few lonely trees and the thorns of the hedgerows appeared as if

they had put off a vegetable for an animal integument. Every twig

was covered with a white nap as of fur grown from the rind during the

night, giving it four times its usual stoutness; the whole bush or

tree forming a staring sketch in white lines on the mournful gray

of the sky and horizon. Cobwebs revealed their presence on sheds

and walls where none had ever been observed till brought out into

visibility by the crystallizing atmosphere, hanging like loops of

white worsted from salient points of the out-houses, posts, and

gates.

After this season of congealed dampness came a spell of dry frost,

when strange birds from behind the North Pole began to arrive

silently on the upland of Flintcomb-Ash; gaunt spectral creatures

with tragical eyes--eyes which had witnessed scenes of cataclysmal

horror in inaccessible polar regions of a magnitude such as no human

being had ever conceived, in curdling temperatures that no man could

endure; which had beheld the crash of icebergs and the slide of

snow-hills by the shooting light of the Aurora; been half blinded

by the whirl of colossal storms and terraqueous distortions; and

retained the expression of feature that such scenes had engendered.

These nameless birds came quite near to Tess and Marian, but of

all they had seen which humanity would never see, they brought no

account. The traveller's ambition to tell was not theirs, and, with

dumb impassivity, they dismissed experiences which they did not

value for the immediate incidents of this homely upland--the trivial

movements of the two girls in disturbing the clods with their hackers

so as to uncover something or other that these visitants relished as

food.

Then one day a peculiar quality invaded the air of this open country.

There came a moisture which was not of rain, and a cold which was not

of frost. It chilled the eyeballs of the twain, made their brows

ache, penetrated to their skeletons, affecting the surface of the

body less than its core. They knew that it meant snow, and in the

night the snow came. Tess, who continued to live at the cottage with

the warm gable that cheered any lonely pedestrian who paused beside

it, awoke in the night, and heard above the thatch noises which

seemed to signify that the roof had turned itself into a gymnasium

of all the winds. When she lit her lamp to get up in the morning

she found that the snow had blown through a chink in the casement,

forming a white cone of the finest powder against the inside, and had

also come down the chimney, so that it lay sole-deep upon the floor,

on which her shoes left tracks when she moved about. Without, the

storm drove so fast as to create a snow-mist in the kitchen; but as

yet it was too dark out-of-doors to see anything.

Tess knew that it was impossible to go on with the swedes; and by

the time she had finished breakfast beside the solitary little lamp,

Marian arrived to tell her that they were to join the rest of the

women at reed-drawing in the barn till the weather changed. As soon,

therefore, as the uniform cloak of darkness without began to turn

to a disordered medley of grays, they blew out the lamp, wrapped

themselves up in their thickest pinners, tied their woollen cravats

round their necks and across their chests, and started for the barn.

The snow had followed the birds from the polar basin as a white

pillar of a cloud, and individual flakes could not be seen. The

blast smelt of icebergs, arctic seas, whales, and white bears,

carrying the snow so that it licked the land but did not deepen on

it. They trudged onwards with slanted bodies through the flossy

fields, keeping as well as they could in the shelter of hedges,

which, however, acted as strainers rather than screens. The air,

afflicted to pallor with the hoary multitudes that infested it,

twisted and spun them eccentrically, suggesting an achromatic chaos

of things. But both the young women were fairly cheerful; such

weather on a dry upland is not in itself dispiriting.

"Ha-ha! the cunning northern birds knew this was coming," said

Marian. "Depend upon't, they keep just in front o't all the way from

the North Star. Your husband, my dear, is, I make no doubt, having

scorching weather all this time. Lord, if he could only see his

pretty wife now! Not that this weather hurts your beauty at all--in

fact, it rather does it good."

"You mustn't talk about him to me, Marian," said Tess severely.

"Well, but--surely you care for'n! Do you?"

Instead of answering, Tess, with tears in her eyes, impulsively faced

in the direction in which she imagined South America to lie, and,

putting up her lips, blew out a passionate kiss upon the snowy wind.

"Well, well, I know you do. But 'pon my body, it is a rum life for

a married couple! There--I won't say another word! Well, as for

the weather, it won't hurt us in the wheat-barn; but reed-drawing is

fearful hard work--worse than swede-hacking. I can stand it because

I'm stout; but you be slimmer than I. I can't think why maister

should have set 'ee at it."

They reached the wheat-barn and entered it. One end of the long

structure was full of corn; the middle was where the reed-drawing was

carried on, and there had already been placed in the reed-press the

evening before as many sheaves of wheat as would be sufficient for

the women to draw from during the day.

"Why, here's Izz!" said Marian.

Izz it was, and she came forward. She had walked all the way from

her mother's home on the previous afternoon, and, not deeming the

distance so great, had been belated, arriving, however, just before

the snow began, and sleeping at the alehouse. The farmer had agreed

with her mother at market to take her on if she came to-day, and she

had been afraid to disappoint him by delay.

In addition to Tess, Marian, and Izz, there were two women from a

neighbouring village; two Amazonian sisters, whom Tess with a start

remembered as Dark Car, the Queen of Spades, and her junior, the

Queen of Diamonds--those who had tried to fight with her in the

midnight quarrel at Trantridge. They showed no recognition of her,

and possibly had none, for they had been under the influence of

liquor on that occasion, and were only temporary sojourners there

as here. They did all kinds of men's work by preference, including

well-sinking, hedging, ditching, and excavating, without any sense of

fatigue. Noted reed-drawers were they too, and looked round upon the

other three with some superciliousness.

Putting on their gloves, all set to work in a row in front of the

press, an erection formed of two posts connected by a cross-beam,

under which the sheaves to be drawn from were laid ears outward, the

beam being pegged down by pins in the uprights, and lowered as the

sheaves diminished.

The day hardened in colour, the light coming in at the barndoors

upwards from the snow instead of downwards from the sky. The girls

pulled handful after handful from the press; but by reason of the

presence of the strange women, who were recounting scandals, Marian

and Izz could not at first talk of old times as they wished to do.

Presently they heard the muffled tread of a horse, and the farmer

rode up to the barndoor. When he had dismounted he came close to

Tess, and remained looking musingly at the side of her face. She had

not turned at first, but his fixed attitude led her to look round,

when she perceived that her employer was the native of Trantridge

from whom she had taken flight on the high-road because of his

allusion to her history.

He waited till she had carried the drawn bundles to the pile outside,

when he said, "So you be the young woman who took my civility in such

ill part? Be drowned if I didn't think you might be as soon as I

heard of your being hired! Well, you thought you had got the better

of me the first time at the inn with your fancy-man, and the second

time on the road, when you bolted; but now I think I've got the

better you." He concluded with a hard laugh.

Tess, between the Amazons and the farmer, like a bird caught in a

clap-net, returned no answer, continuing to pull the straw. She

could read character sufficiently well to know by this time that she

had nothing to fear from her employer's gallantry; it was rather the

tyranny induced by his mortification at Clare's treatment of him.

Upon the whole she preferred that sentiment in man and felt brave

enough to endure it.

"You thought I was in love with 'ee I suppose? Some women are such

fools, to take every look as serious earnest. But there's nothing

like a winter afield for taking that nonsense out o' young wenches'

heads; and you've signed and agreed till Lady-Day. Now, are you

going to beg my pardon?"

"I think you ought to beg mine."

"Very well--as you like. But we'll see which is master here. Be

they all the sheaves you've done to-day?"

"Yes, sir."

"'Tis a very poor show. Just see what they've done over there"

(pointing to the two stalwart women). "The rest, too, have done

better than you."

"They've all practised it before, and I have not. And I thought it

made no difference to you as it is task work, and we are only paid

for what we do."

"Oh, but it does. I want the barn cleared."

"I am going to work all the afternoon instead of leaving at two as

the others will do."

He looked sullenly at her and went away. Tess felt that she could

not have come to a much worse place; but anything was better than

gallantry. When two o'clock arrived the professional reed-drawers

tossed off the last half-pint in their flagon, put down their hooks,

tied their last sheaves, and went away. Marian and Izz would have

done likewise, but on hearing that Tess meant to stay, to make up

by longer hours for her lack of skill, they would not leave her.

Looking out at the snow, which still fell, Marian exclaimed, "Now,

we've got it all to ourselves." And so at last the conversation

turned to their old experiences at the dairy; and, of course, the

incidents of their affection for Angel Clare.

"Izz and Marian," said Mrs Angel Clare, with a dignity which was

extremely touching, seeing how very little of a wife she was: "I

can't join in talk with you now, as I used to do, about Mr Clare; you

will see that I cannot; because, although he is gone away from me for

the present, he is my husband."

Izz was by nature the sauciest and most caustic of all the four girls

who had loved Clare. "He was a very splendid lover, no doubt," she

said; "but I don't think he is a too fond husband to go away from you

so soon."

"He had to go--he was obliged to go, to see about the land over

there!" pleaded Tess.

"He might have tided 'ee over the winter."

"Ah--that's owing to an accident--a misunderstanding; and we won't

argue it," Tess answered, with tearfulness in her words. "Perhaps

there's a good deal to be said for him! He did not go away, like

some husbands, without telling me; and I can always find out where

he is."

After this they continued for some long time in a reverie, as they

went on seizing the ears of corn, drawing out the straw, gathering

it under their arms, and cutting off the ears with their bill-hooks,

nothing sounding in the barn but the swish of the straw and the

crunch of the hook. Then Tess suddenly flagged, and sank down upon

the heap of wheat-ears at her feet.

"I knew you wouldn't be able to stand it!" cried Marian. "It wants

harder flesh than yours for this work."

Just then the farmer entered. "Oh, that's how you get on when I am

away," he said to her.

"But it is my own loss," she pleaded. "Not yours."

"I want it finished," he said doggedly, as he crossed the barn and

went out at the other door.

"Don't 'ee mind him, there's a dear," said Marian. "I've worked here

before. Now you go and lie down there, and Izz and I will make up

your number."

"I don't like to let you do that. I'm taller than you, too."

However, she was so overcome that she consented to lie down awhile,

and reclined on a heap of pull-tails--the refuse after the straight

straw had been drawn--thrown up at the further side of the barn. Her

succumbing had been as largely owning to agitation at the re-opening

the subject of her separation from her husband as to the hard work.

She lay in a state of percipience without volition, and the rustle of

the straw and the cutting of the ears by the others had the weight of

bodily touches.

She could hear from her corner, in addition to these noises, the

murmur of their voices. She felt certain that they were continuing

the subject already broached, but their voices were so low that she

could not catch the words. At last Tess grew more and more anxious

to know what they were saying, and, persuading herself that she felt

better, she got up and resumed work.

Then Izz Huett broke down. She had walked more than a dozen miles

the previous evening, had gone to bed at midnight, and had risen

again at five o'clock. Marian alone, thanks to her bottle of liquor

and her stoutness of build, stood the strain upon back and arms

without suffering. Tess urged Izz to leave off, agreeing, as she

felt better, to finish the day without her, and make equal division

of the number of sheaves.

Izz accepted the offer gratefully, and disappeared through the great

door into the snowy track to her lodging. Marian, as was the case

every afternoon at this time on account of the bottle, began to feel

in a romantic vein.

"I should not have thought it of him--never!" she said in a dreamy

tone. "And I loved him so! I didn't mind his having YOU. But this

about Izz is too bad!"

Tess, in her start at the words, narrowly missed cutting off a finger

with the bill-hook.

"Is it about my husband?" she stammered.

"Well, yes. Izz said, 'Don't 'ee tell her'; but I am sure I can't

help it! It was what he wanted Izz to do. He wanted her to go off

to Brazil with him."

Tess's face faded as white as the scene without, and its curves

straightened. "And did Izz refuse to go?" she asked.

"I don't know. Anyhow he changed his mind."

"Pooh--then he didn't mean it! 'Twas just a man's jest!"

"Yes he did; for he drove her a good-ways towards the station."

"He didn't take her!"

They pulled on in silence till Tess, without any premonitory

symptoms, burst out crying.

"There!" said Marian. "Now I wish I hadn't told 'ee!"

"No. It is a very good thing that you have done! I have been living

on in a thirtover, lackaday way, and have not seen what it may lead

to! I ought to have sent him a letter oftener. He said I could not

go to him, but he didn't say I was not to write as often as I liked.

I won't dally like this any longer! I have been very wrong and

neglectful in leaving everything to be done by him!"

The dim light in the barn grew dimmer, and they could see to work no

longer. When Tess had reached home that evening, and had entered

into the privacy of her little white-washed chamber, she began

impetuously writing a letter to Clare. But falling into doubt, she

could not finish it. Afterwards she took the ring from the ribbon on

which she wore it next her heart, and retained it on her finger all

night, as if to fortify herself in the sensation that she was really

the wife of this elusive lover of hers, who could propose that Izz

should go with him abroad, so shortly after he had left her. Knowing

that, how could she write entreaties to him, or show that she cared

for him any more?

XLIV

By the disclosure in the barn her thoughts were led anew in the

direction which they had taken more than once of late--to the distant

Emminster Vicarage. It was through her husband's parents that she

had been charged to send a letter to Clare if she desired; and to

write to them direct if in difficulty. But that sense of her having

morally no claim upon him had always led Tess to suspend her impulse

to send these notes; and to the family at the Vicarage, therefore,

as to her own parents since her marriage, she was virtually

non-existent. This self-effacement in both directions had been quite

in consonance with her independent character of desiring nothing

by way of favour or pity to which she was not entitled on a fair

consideration of her deserts. She had set herself to stand or fall

by her qualities, and to waive such merely technical claims upon a

strange family as had been established for her by the flimsy fact of

a member of that family, in a season of impulse, writing his name in

a church-book beside hers.

But now that she was stung to a fever by Izz's tale, there was a

limit to her powers of renunciation. Why had her husband not written

to her? He had distinctly implied that he would at least let her

know of the locality to which he had journeyed; but he had not sent a

line to notify his address. Was he really indifferent? But was he

ill? Was it for her to make some advance? Surely she might summon

the courage of solicitude, call at the Vicarage for intelligence, and

express her grief at his silence. If Angel's father were the good

man she had heard him represented to be, he would be able to enter

into her heart-starved situation. Her social hardships she could

conceal.

To leave the farm on a week-day was not in her power; Sunday was

the only possible opportunity. Flintcomb-Ash being in the middle

of the cretaceous tableland over which no railway had climbed as

yet, it would be necessary to walk. And the distance being fifteen

miles each way she would have to allow herself a long day for the

undertaking by rising early.

A fortnight later, when the snow had gone, and had been followed by

a hard black frost, she took advantage of the state of the roads to

try the experiment. At four o'clock that Sunday morning she came

downstairs and stepped out into the starlight. The weather was still

favourable, the ground ringing under her feet like an anvil.

Marian and Izz were much interested in her excursion, knowing that

the journey concerned her husband. Their lodgings were in a cottage

a little further along the lane, but they came and assisted Tess

in her departure, and argued that she should dress up in her very

prettiest guise to captivate the hearts of her parents-in-law; though

she, knowing of the austere and Calvinistic tenets of old Mr Clare,

was indifferent, and even doubtful. A year had now elapsed since

her sad marriage, but she had preserved sufficient draperies from

the wreck of her then full wardrobe to clothe her very charmingly as

a simple country girl with no pretensions to recent fashion; a soft

gray woollen gown, with white crape quilling against the pink skin of

her face and neck, and a black velvet jacket and hat.

"'Tis a thousand pities your husband can't see 'ee now--you do look

a real beauty!" said Izz Huett, regarding Tess as she stood on

the threshold between the steely starlight without and the yellow

candlelight within. Izz spoke with a magnanimous abandonment of

herself to the situation; she could not be--no woman with a heart

bigger than a hazel-nut could be--antagonistic to Tess in her

presence, the influence which she exercised over those of her own sex

being of a warmth and strength quite unusual, curiously overpowering

the less worthy feminine feelings of spite and rivalry.

With a final tug and touch here, and a slight brush there, they let

her go; and she was absorbed into the pearly air of the fore-dawn.

They heard her footsteps tap along the hard road as she stepped out

to her full pace. Even Izz hoped she would win, and, though without

any particular respect for her own virtue, felt glad that she had

been prevented wronging her friend when momentarily tempted by Clare.

It was a year ago, all but a day, that Clare had married Tess, and

only a few days less than a year that he had been absent from her.

Still, to start on a brisk walk, and on such an errand as hers, on a

dry clear wintry morning, through the rarefied air of these chalky

hogs'-backs, was not depressing; and there is no doubt that her dream

at starting was to win the heart of her mother-in-law, tell her whole

history to that lady, enlist her on her side, and so gain back the

truant.

In time she reached the edge of the vast escarpment below which

stretched the loamy Vale of Blackmoor, now lying misty and still

in the dawn. Instead of the colourless air of the uplands, the

atmosphere down there was a deep blue. Instead of the great

enclosures of a hundred acres in which she was now accustomed to

toil, there were little fields below her of less than half-a-dozen

acres, so numerous that they looked from this height like the meshes

of a net. Here the landscape was whitey-brown; down there, as in

Froom Valley, it was always green. Yet it was in that vale that her

sorrow had taken shape, and she did not love it as formerly. Beauty

to her, as to all who have felt, lay not in the thing, but in what

the thing symbolized.

Keeping the Vale on her right, she steered steadily westward; passing

above the Hintocks, crossing at right-angles the high-road from

Sherton-Abbas to Casterbridge, and skirting Dogbury Hill and

High-Stoy, with the dell between them called "The Devil's Kitchen".

Still following the elevated way she reached Cross-in-Hand, where

the stone pillar stands desolate and silent, to mark the site of a

miracle, or murder, or both. Three miles further she cut across the

straight and deserted Roman road called Long-Ash Lane; leaving which

as soon as she reached it she dipped down a hill by a transverse lane

into the small town or village of Evershead, being now about halfway

over the distance. She made a halt here, and breakfasted a second

time, heartily enough--not at the Sow-and-Acorn, for she avoided

inns, but at a cottage by the church.

The second half of her journey was through a more gentle country, by

way of Benvill Lane. But as the mileage lessened between her and the

spot of her pilgrimage, so did Tess's confidence decrease, and her

enterprise loom out more formidably. She saw her purpose in such

staring lines, and the landscape so faintly, that she was sometimes

in danger of losing her way. However, about noon she paused by a

gate on the edge of the basin in which Emminster and its Vicarage

lay.

The square tower, beneath which she knew that at that moment the

Vicar and his congregation were gathered, had a severe look in

her eyes. She wished that she had somehow contrived to come on a

week-day. Such a good man might be prejudiced against a woman who

had chosen Sunday, never realizing the necessities of her case.

But it was incumbent upon her to go on now. She took off the thick

boots in which she had walked thus far, put on her pretty thin ones

of patent leather, and, stuffing the former into the hedge by the

gatepost where she might readily find them again, descended the hill;

the freshness of colour she had derived from the keen air thinning

away in spite of her as she drew near the parsonage.

Tess hoped for some accident that might favour her, but nothing

favoured her. The shrubs on the Vicarage lawn rustled uncomfortably

in the frosty breeze; she could not feel by any stretch of

imagination, dressed to her highest as she was, that the house was

the residence of near relations; and yet nothing essential, in nature

or emotion, divided her from them: in pains, pleasures, thoughts,

birth, death, and after-death, they were the same.

She nerved herself by an effort, entered the swing-gate, and rang

the door-bell. The thing was done; there could be no retreat. No;

the thing was not done. Nobody answered to her ringing. The effort

had to be risen to and made again. She rang a second time, and the

agitation of the act, coupled with her weariness after the fifteen

miles' walk, led her support herself while she waited by resting her

hand on her hip, and her elbow against the wall of the porch. The

wind was so nipping that the ivy-leaves had become wizened and gray,

each tapping incessantly upon its neighbour with a disquieting stir

of her nerves. A piece of blood-stained paper, caught up from some

meat-buyer's dust-heap, beat up and down the road without the gate;

too flimsy to rest, too heavy to fly away; and a few straws kept it

company.

The second peal had been louder, and still nobody came. Then she

walked out of the porch, opened the gate, and passed through. And

though she looked dubiously at the house-front as if inclined to

return, it was with a breath of relied that she closed the gate. A

feeling haunted her that she might have been recognized (though how

she could not tell), and orders been given not to admit her.

Tess went as far as the corner. She had done all she could do; but

determined not to escape present trepidation at the expense of future

distress, she walked back again quite past the house, looking up at

all the windows.

Ah--the explanation was that they were all at church, every one. She

remembered her husband saying that his father always insisted upon

the household, servants included, going to morning-service, and,

as a consequence, eating cold food when they came home. It was,

therefore, only necessary to wait till the service was over. She

would not make herself conspicuous by waiting on the spot, and she

started to get past the church into the lane. But as she reached the

churchyard-gate the people began pouring out, and Tess found herself

in the midst of them.

The Emminster congregation looked at her as only a congregation of

small country-townsfolk walking home at its leisure can look at a

woman out of the common whom it perceives to be a stranger. She

quickened her pace, and ascended the the road by which she had come,

to find a retreat between its hedges till the Vicar's family should

have lunched, and it might be convenient for them to receive her.

She soon distanced the churchgoers, except two youngish men, who,

linked arm-in-arm, were beating up behind her at a quick step.

As they drew nearer she could hear their voices engaged in earnest

discourse, and, with the natural quickness of a woman in her

situation, did not fail to recognize in those noises the quality

of her husband's tones. The pedestrians were his two brothers.

Forgetting all her plans, Tess's one dread was lest they should

overtake her now, in her disorganized condition, before she was

prepared to confront them; for though she felt that they could not

identify her, she instinctively dreaded their scrutiny. The more

briskly they walked, the more briskly walked she. They were plainly

bent upon taking a short quick stroll before going indoors to lunch

or dinner, to restore warmth to limbs chilled with sitting through a

long service.

Only one person had preceded Tess up the hill--a ladylike young

woman, somewhat interesting, though, perhaps, a trifle _guinde_

and prudish. Tess had nearly overtaken her when the speed of her

brothers-in-law brought them so nearly behind her back that she could

hear every word of their conversation. They said nothing, however,

which particularly interested her till, observing the young lady

still further in front, one of them remarked, "There is Mercy Chant.

Let us overtake her."

Tess knew the name. It was the woman who had been destined for

Angel's life-companion by his and her parents, and whom he probably

would have married but for her intrusive self. She would have known

as much without previous information if she had waited a moment, for

one of the brothers proceeded to say: "Ah! poor Angel, poor Angel!

I never see that nice girl without more and more regretting his

precipitancy in throwing himself away upon a dairymaid, or whatever

she may be. It is a queer business, apparently. Whether she has

joined him yet or not I don't know; but she had not done so some

months ago when I heard from him."

"I can't say. He never tells me anything nowadays. His

ill-considered marriage seems to have completed that estrangement

from me which was begun by his extraordinary opinions."

Tess beat up the long hill still faster; but she could not outwalk

them without exciting notice. At last they outsped her altogether,

and passed her by. The young lady still further ahead heard their

footsteps and turned. Then there was a greeting and a shaking of

hands, and the three went on together.

They soon reached the summit of the hill, and, evidently intending

this point to be the limit of their promenade, slackened pace and

turned all three aside to the gate whereat Tess had paused an hour

before that time to reconnoitre the town before descending into it.

During their discourse one of the clerical brothers probed the hedge

carefully with his umbrella, and dragged something to light.

"Here's a pair of old boots," he said. "Thrown away, I suppose, by

some tramp or other."

"Some imposter who wished to come into the town barefoot, perhaps,

and so excite our sympathies," said Miss Chant. "Yes, it must have

been, for they are excellent walking-boots--by no means worn out.

What a wicked thing to do! I'll carry them home for some poor

person."

Cuthbert Clare, who had been the one to find them, picked them up for

her with the crook of his stick; and Tess's boots were appropriated.

She, who had heard this, walked past under the screen of her woollen

veil till, presently looking back, she perceived that the church

party had left the gate with her boots and retreated down the hill.

Thereupon our heroine resumed her walk. Tears, blinding tears, were

running down her face. She knew that it was all sentiment, all

baseless impressibility, which had caused her to read the scene as

her own condemnation; nevertheless she could not get over it; she

could not contravene in her own defenceless person all those untoward

omens. It was impossible to think of returning to the Vicarage.

Angel's wife felt almost as if she had been hounded up that hill like

a scorned thing by those--to her--superfine clerics. Innocently

as the slight had been inflicted, it was somewhat unfortunate that

she had encountered the sons and not the father, who, despite his

narrowness, was far less starched and ironed than they, and had to

the full the gift of charity. As she again thought of her dusty

boots she almost pitied those habiliments for the quizzing to which

they had been subjected, and felt how hopeless life was for their

owner.

"Ah!" she said, still sighing in pity of herself, "THEY didn't know

that I wore those over the roughest part of the road to save these

pretty ones HE bought for me--no--they did not know it! And they

didn't think that HE chose the colour o' my pretty frock--no--how

could they? If they had known perhaps they would not have cared,

for they don't care much for him, poor thing!"

Then she grieved for the beloved man whose conventional standard of

judgement had caused her all these latter sorrows; and she went her

way without knowing that the greatest misfortune of her life was this

feminine loss of courage at the last and critical moment through her

estimating her father-in-law by his sons. Her present condition was

precisely one which would have enlisted the sympathies of old Mr and

Mrs Clare. Their hearts went out of them at a bound towards extreme

cases, when the subtle mental troubles of the less desperate among

mankind failed to win their interest or regard. In jumping at

Publicans and Sinners they would forget that a word might be said for

the worries of Scribes and Pharisees; and this defect or limitation

might have recommended their own daughter-in-law to them at this

moment as a fairly choice sort of lost person for their love.

Thereupon she began to plod back along the road by which she had come

not altogether full of hope, but full of a conviction that a crisis

in her life was approaching. No crisis, apparently, had supervened;

and there was nothing left for her to do but to continue upon that

starve-acre farm till she could again summon courage to face the

Vicarage. She did, indeed, take sufficient interest in herself to

throw up her veil on this return journey, as if to let the world see

that she could at least exhibit a face such as Mercy Chant could

not show. But it was done with a sorry shake of the head. "It is

nothing--it is nothing!" she said. "Nobody loves it; nobody sees it.

Who cares about the looks of a castaway like me!"

Her journey back was rather a meander than a march. It had no

sprightliness, no purpose; only a tendency. Along the tedious length

of Benvill Lane she began to grow tired, and she leant upon gates and

paused by milestones.

She did not enter any house till, at the seventh or eighth mile, she

descended the steep long hill below which lay the village or townlet

of Evershead, where in the morning she had breakfasted with such

contrasting expectations. The cottage by the church, in which she

again sat down, was almost the first at that end of the village, and

while the woman fetched her some milk from the pantry, Tess, looking

down the street, perceived that the place seemed quite deserted.

"The people are gone to afternoon service, I suppose?" she said.

"No, my dear," said the old woman. "'Tis too soon for that; the

bells hain't strook out yet. They be all gone to hear the preaching

in yonder barn. A ranter preaches there between the services--an

excellent, fiery, Christian man, they say. But, Lord, I don't go to

hear'n! What comes in the regular way over the pulpit is hot enough

for I."

Tess soon went onward into the village, her footsteps echoing against

the houses as though it were a place of the dead. Nearing the

central part, her echoes were intruded on by other sounds; and seeing

the barn not far off the road, she guessed these to be the utterances

of the preacher.

His voice became so distinct in the still clear air that she could

soon catch his sentences, though she was on the closed side of

the barn. The sermon, as might be expected, was of the extremest

antinomian type; on justification by faith, as expounded in the

theology of St Paul. This fixed idea of the rhapsodist was delivered

with animated enthusiasm, in a manner entirely declamatory, for he

had plainly no skill as a dialectician. Although Tess had not heard

the beginning of the address, she learnt what the text had been from

its constant iteration--

"O foolish galatians, who hath bewitched you, that ye

should not obey the truth, before whose eyes Jesus Christ

hath been evidently set forth, crucified among you?"

Tess was all the more interested, as she stood listening behind, in

finding that the preacher's doctrine was a vehement form of the view

of Angel's father, and her interest intensified when the speaker

began to detail his own spiritual experiences of how he had come by

those views. He had, he said, been the greatest of sinners. He had

scoffed; he had wantonly associated with the reckless and the lewd.

But a day of awakening had come, and, in a human sense, it had been

brought about mainly by the influence of a certain clergyman, whom he

had at first grossly insulted; but whose parting words had sunk into

his heart, and had remained there, till by the grace of Heaven they

had worked this change in him, and made him what they saw him.

But more startling to Tess than the doctrine had been the voice,

which, impossible as it seemed, was precisely that of Alec

d'Urberville. Her face fixed in painful suspense, she came round

to the front of the barn, and passed before it. The low winter sun

beamed directly upon the great double-doored entrance on this side;

one of the doors being open, so that the rays stretched far in over

the threshing-floor to the preacher and his audience, all snugly

sheltered from the northern breeze. The listeners were entirely

villagers, among them being the man whom she had seen carrying the

red paint-pot on a former memorable occasion. But her attention

was given to the central figure, who stood upon some sacks of corn,

facing the people and the door. The three o'clock sun shone full

upon him, and the strange enervating conviction that her seducer

confronted her, which had been gaining ground in Tess ever since she

had heard his words distinctly, was at last established as a fact

indeed.

END OF PHASE THE FIFTH

Phase the Sixth: The Convert

XLV

Till this moment she had never seen or heard from d'Urberville since

her departure from Trantridge.

The rencounter came at a heavy moment, one of all moments calculated

to permit its impact with the least emotional shock. But such was

unreasoning memory that, though he stood there openly and palpably a

converted man, who was sorrowing for his past irregularities, a fear

overcame her, paralyzing her movement so that she neither retreated

nor advanced.

To think of what emanated from that countenance when she saw it last,

and to behold it now! ... There was the same handsome unpleasantness

of mien, but now he wore neatly trimmed, old-fashioned whiskers, the

sable moustache having disappeared; and his dress was half-clerical,

a modification which had changed his expression sufficiently to

abstract the dandyism from his features, and to hinder for a second

her belief in his identity.

To Tess's sense there was, just at first, a ghastly _bizarrerie_,

a grim incongruity, in the march of these solemn words of Scripture

out of such a mouth. This too familiar intonation, less than four

years earlier, had brought to her ears expressions of such divergent

purpose that her heart became quite sick at the irony of the

contrast.

It was less a reform than a transfiguration. The former curves of

sensuousness were now modulated to lines of devotional passion.

The lip-shapes that had meant seductiveness were now made to

express supplication; the glow on the cheek that yesterday could be

translated as riotousness was evangelized to-day into the splendour

of pious rhetoric; animalism had become fanaticism; Paganism,

Paulinism; the bold rolling eye that had flashed upon her form in

the old time with such mastery now beamed with the rude energy of a

theolatry that was almost ferocious. Those black angularities which

his face had used to put on when his wishes were thwarted now did

duty in picturing the incorrigible backslider who would insist upon

turning again to his wallowing in the mire.

The lineaments, as such, seemed to complain. They had been diverted

from their hereditary connotation to signify impressions for which

Nature did not intend them. Strange that their very elevation was a

misapplication, that to raise seemed to falsify.

Yet could it be so? She would admit the ungenerous sentiment no

longer. D'Urberville was not the first wicked man who had turned

away from his wickedness to save his soul alive, and why should she

deem it unnatural in him? It was but the usage of thought which had

been jarred in her at hearing good new words in bad old notes. The

greater the sinner, the greater the saint; it was not necessary to

dive far into Christian history to discover that.

Such impressions as these moved her vaguely, and without strict

definiteness. As soon as the nerveless pause of her surprise would

allow her to stir, her impulse was to pass on out of his sight. He

had obviously not discerned her yet in her position against the sun.

But the moment that she moved again he recognized her. The effect

upon her old lover was electric, far stronger than the effect of his

presence upon her. His fire, the tumultuous ring of his eloquence,

seemed to go out of him. His lip struggled and trembled under the

words that lay upon it; but deliver them it could not as long as she

faced him. His eyes, after their first glance upon her face, hung

confusedly in every other direction but hers, but came back in a

desperate leap every few seconds. This paralysis lasted, however,

but a short time; for Tess's energies returned with the atrophy of

his, and she walked as fast as she was able past the barn and onward.

As soon as she could reflect, it appalled her, this change in their

relative platforms. He who had wrought her undoing was now on the

side of the Spirit, while she remained unregenerate. And, as in the

legend, it had resulted that her Cyprian image had suddenly appeared

upon his altar, whereby the fire of the priest had been well nigh

extinguished.

She went on without turning her head. Her back seemed to be endowed

with a sensitiveness to ocular beams--even her clothing--so alive

was she to a fancied gaze which might be resting upon her from the

outside of that barn. All the way along to this point her heart

had been heavy with an inactive sorrow; now there was a change in

the quality of its trouble. That hunger for affection too long

withheld was for the time displaced by an almost physical sense

of an implacable past which still engirdled her. It intensified

her consciousness of error to a practical despair; the break of

continuity between her earlier and present existence, which she had

hoped for, had not, after all, taken place. Bygones would never be

complete bygones till she was a bygone herself.

Thus absorbed, she recrossed the northern part of Long-Ash Lane at

right angles, and presently saw before her the road ascending whitely

to the upland along whose margin the remainder of her journey lay.

Its dry pale surface stretched severely onward, unbroken by a single

figure, vehicle, or mark, save some occasional brown horse-droppings

which dotted its cold aridity here and there. While slowly breasting

this ascent Tess became conscious of footsteps behind her, and

turning she saw approaching that well-known form--so strangely

accoutred as the Methodist--the one personage in all the world she

wished not to encounter alone on this side of the grave.

There was not much time, however, for thought or elusion, and she

yielded as calmly as she could to the necessity of letting him

overtake her. She saw that he was excited, less by the speed of his

walk than by the feelings within him.

"Tess!" he said.

She slackened speed without looking round.

"Tess!" he repeated. "It is I--Alec d'Urberville."

She then looked back at him, and he came up.

"I see it is," she answered coldly.

"Well--is that all? Yet I deserve no more! Of course," he added,

with a slight laugh, "there is something of the ridiculous to your

eyes in seeing me like this. But--I must put up with that. ... I

heard you had gone away; nobody knew where. Tess, you wonder why I

have followed you?"

"I do, rather; and I would that you had not, with all my heart!"

"Yes--you may well say it," he returned grimly, as they moved onward

together, she with unwilling tread. "But don't mistake me; I beg

this because you may have been led to do so in noticing--if you did

notice it--how your sudden appearance unnerved me down there. It was

but a momentary faltering; and considering what you have been to me,

it was natural enough. But will helped me through it--though perhaps

you think me a humbug for saying it--and immediately afterwards I

felt that of all persons in the world whom it was my duty and desire

to save from the wrath to come--sneer if you like--the woman whom I

had so grievously wronged was that person. I have come with that

sole purpose in view--nothing more."

There was the smallest vein of scorn in her words of rejoinder: "Have

you saved yourself? Charity begins at home, they say."

"_I_ have done nothing!" said he indifferently. "Heaven, as I have

been telling my hearers, has done all. No amount of contempt that

you can pour upon me, Tess, will equal what I have poured upon

myself--the old Adam of my former years! Well, it is a strange

story; believe it or not; but I can tell you the means by which my

conversion was brought about, and I hope you will be interested

enough at least to listen. Have you ever heard the name of the

parson of Emminster--you must have done do?--old Mr Clare; one of the

most earnest of his school; one of the few intense men left in the

Church; not so intense as the extreme wing of Christian believers

with which I have thrown in my lot, but quite an exception among the

Established clergy, the younger of whom are gradually attenuating the

true doctrines by their sophistries, till they are but the shadow of

what they were. I only differ from him on the question of Church and

State--the interpretation of the text, 'Come out from among them and

be ye separate, saith the Lord'--that's all. He is one who, I firmly

believe, has been the humble means of saving more souls in this

country than any other man you can name. You have heard of him?"

"I have," she said.

"He came to Trantridge two or three years ago to preach on behalf of

some missionary society; and I, wretched fellow that I was, insulted

him when, in his disinterestedness, he tried to reason with me and

show me the way. He did not resent my conduct, he simply said that

some day I should receive the first-fruits of the Spirit--that those

who came to scoff sometimes remained to pray. There was a strange

magic in his words. They sank into my mind. But the loss of my

mother hit me most; and by degrees I was brought to see daylight.

Since then my one desire has been to hand on the true view to others,

and that is what I was trying to do to-day; though it is only lately

that I have preached hereabout. The first months of my ministry have

been spent in the North of England among strangers, where I preferred

to make my earliest clumsy attempts, so as to acquire courage before

undergoing that severest of all tests of one's sincerity, addressing

those who have known one, and have been one's companions in the days

of darkness. If you could only know, Tess, the pleasure of having a

good slap at yourself, I am sure--"

"Don't go on with it!" she cried passionately, as she turned away

from him to a stile by the wayside, on which she bent herself. "I

can't believe in such sudden things! I feel indignant with you for

talking to me like this, when you know--when you know what harm

you've done me! You, and those like you, take your fill of pleasure

on earth by making the life of such as me bitter and black with

sorrow; and then it is a fine thing, when you have had enough of

that, to think of securing your pleasure in heaven by becoming

converted! Out upon such--I don't believe in you--I hate it!"

"Tess," he insisted; "don't speak so! It came to me like a jolly new

idea! And you don't believe me? What don't you believe?"

"Your conversion. Your scheme of religion."

"Why?"

She dropped her voice. "Because a better man than you does not

believe in such."

"What a woman's reason! Who is this better man?"

"I cannot tell you."

"Well," he declared, a resentment beneath his words seeming ready to

spring out at a moment's notice, "God forbid that I should say I am

a good man--and you know I don't say any such thing. I am new to

goodness, truly; but newcomers see furthest sometimes."

"Yes," she replied sadly. "But I cannot believe in your conversion

to a new spirit. Such flashes as you feel, Alec, I fear don't last!"

Thus speaking she turned from the stile over which she had been

leaning, and faced him; whereupon his eyes, falling casually upon

the familiar countenance and form, remained contemplating her. The

inferior man was quiet in him now; but it was surely not extracted,

nor even entirely subdued.

"Don't look at me like that!" he said abruptly.

Tess, who had been quite unconscious of her action and mien,

instantly withdrew the large dark gaze of her eyes, stammering with

a flush, "I beg your pardon!" And there was revived in her the

wretched sentiment which had often come to her before, that in

inhabiting the fleshly tabernacle with which Nature had endowed her

she was somehow doing wrong.

"No, no! Don't beg my pardon. But since you wear a veil to hide

your good looks, why don't you keep it down?"

She pulled down the veil, saying hastily, "It was mostly to keep off

the wind."

"It may seem harsh of me to dictate like this," he went on; "but

it is better that I should not look too often on you. It might be

dangerous."

"Ssh!" said Tess.

"Well, women's faces have had too much power over me already for me

not to fear them! An evangelist has nothing to do with such as they;

and it reminds me of the old times that I would forget!"

After this their conversation dwindled to a casual remark now and

then as they rambled onward, Tess inwardly wondering how far he was

going with her, and not liking to send him back by positive mandate.

Frequently when they came to a gate or stile they found painted

thereon in red or blue letters some text of Scripture, and she

asked him if he knew who had been at the pains to blazon these

announcements. He told her that the man was employed by himself and

others who were working with him in that district, to paint these

reminders that no means might be left untried which might move the

hearts of a wicked generation.

At length the road touched the spot called "Cross-in-Hand." Of all

spots on the bleached and desolate upland this was the most forlorn.

It was so far removed from the charm which is sought in landscape by

artists and view-lovers as to reach a new kind of beauty, a negative

beauty of tragic tone. The place took its name from a stone pillar

which stood there, a strange rude monolith, from a stratum unknown

in any local quarry, on which was roughly carved a human hand.

Differing accounts were given of its history and purport. Some

authorities stated that a devotional cross had once formed the

complete erection thereon, of which the present relic was but the

stump; others that the stone as it stood was entire, and that it had

been fixed there to mark a boundary or place of meeting. Anyhow,

whatever the origin of the relic, there was and is something

sinister, or solemn, according to mood, in the scene amid which it

stands; something tending to impress the most phlegmatic passer-by.

"I think I must leave you now," he remarked, as they drew near to

this spot. "I have to preach at Abbot's-Cernel at six this evening,

and my way lies across to the right from here. And you upset me

somewhat too, Tessy--I cannot, will not, say why. I must go away and

get strength. ... How is it that you speak so fluently now? Who has

taught you such good English?"

"I have learnt things in my troubles," she said evasively.

"What troubles have you had?"

She told him of the first one--the only one that related to him.

D'Urberville was struck mute. "I knew nothing of this till now!"

he next murmured. "Why didn't you write to me when you felt your

trouble coming on?"

She did not reply; and he broke the silence by adding: "Well--you

will see me again."

"No," she answered. "Do not again come near me!"

"I will think. But before we part come here." He stepped up to the

pillar. "This was once a Holy Cross. Relics are not in my creed; but

I fear you at moments--far more than you need fear me at present; and

to lessen my fear, put your hand upon that stone hand, and swear that

you will never tempt me--by your charms or ways."

"Good God--how can you ask what is so unnecessary! All that is

furthest from my thought!"

"Yes--but swear it."

Tess, half frightened, gave way to his importunity; placed her hand

upon the stone and swore.

"I am sorry you are not a believer," he continued; "that some

unbeliever should have got hold of you and unsettled your mind. But

no more now. At home at least I can pray for you; and I will; and

who knows what may not happen? I'm off. Goodbye!"

He turned to a hunting-gate in the hedge and, without letting his

eyes again rest upon her, leapt over and struck out across the down

in the direction of Abbot's-Cernel. As he walked his pace showed

perturbation, and by-and-by, as if instigated by a former thought,

he drew from his pocket a small book, between the leaves of which

was folded a letter, worn and soiled, as from much re-reading.

D'Urberville opened the letter. It was dated several months before

this time, and was signed by Parson Clare.

The letter began by expressing the writer's unfeigned joy at

d'Urberville's conversion, and thanked him for his kindness in

communicating with the parson on the subject. It expressed Mr

Clare's warm assurance of forgiveness for d'Urberville's former

conduct and his interest in the young man's plans for the future.

He, Mr Clare, would much have liked to see d'Urberville in the Church

to whose ministry he had devoted so many years of his own life, and

would have helped him to enter a theological college to that end; but

since his correspondent had possibly not cared to do this on account

of the delay it would have entailed, he was not the man to insist

upon its paramount importance. Every man must work as he could best

work, and in the method towards which he felt impelled by the Spirit.

D'Urberville read and re-read this letter, and seemed to quiz himself

cynically. He also read some passages from memoranda as he walked

till his face assumed a calm, and apparently the image of Tess no

longer troubled his mind.

She meanwhile had kept along the edge of the hill by which lay her

nearest way home. Within the distance of a mile she met a solitary

shepherd.

"What is the meaning of that old stone I have passed?" she asked of

him. "Was it ever a Holy Cross?"

"Cross--no; 'twer not a cross! 'Tis a thing of ill-omen, Miss. It

was put up in wuld times by the relations of a malefactor who was

tortured there by nailing his hand to a post and afterwards hung.

The bones lie underneath. They say he sold his soul to the devil,

and that he walks at times."

She felt the _petite mort_ at this unexpectedly gruesome information,

and left the solitary man behind her. It was dusk when she drew near

to Flintcomb-Ash, and in the lane at the entrance to the hamlet she

approached a girl and her lover without their observing her. They

were talking no secrets, and the clear unconcerned voice of the young

woman, in response to the warmer accents of the man, spread into the

chilly air as the one soothing thing within the dusky horizon, full

of a stagnant obscurity upon which nothing else intruded. For a

moment the voices cheered the heart of Tess, till she reasoned that

this interview had its origin, on one side or the other, in the same

attraction which had been the prelude to her own tribulation. When

she came close, the girl turned serenely and recognized her, the

young man walking off in embarrassment. The woman was Izz Huett,

whose interest in Tess's excursion immediately superseded her own

proceedings. Tess did not explain very clearly its results, and Izz,

who was a girl of tact, began to speak of her own little affair, a

phase of which Tess had just witnessed.

"He is Amby Seedling, the chap who used to sometimes come and help at

Talbothays," she explained indifferently. "He actually inquired and

found out that I had come here, and has followed me. He says he's

been in love wi' me these two years. But I've hardly answered him."

XLVI

Several days had passed since her futile journey, and Tess was

afield. The dry winter wind still blew, but a screen of thatched

hurdles erected in the eye of the blast kept its force away from her.

On the sheltered side was a turnip-slicing machine, whose bright blue

hue of new paint seemed almost vocal in the otherwise subdued scene.

Opposite its front was a long mound or "grave", in which the roots

had been preserved since early winter. Tess was standing at the

uncovered end, chopping off with a bill-hook the fibres and earth

from each root, and throwing it after the operation into the slicer.

A man was turning the handle of the machine, and from its trough

came the newly-cut swedes, the fresh smell of whose yellow chips

was accompanied by the sounds of the snuffling wind, the smart swish

of the slicing-blades, and the choppings of the hook in Tess's

leather-gloved hand.

The wide acreage of blank agricultural brownness, apparent where

the swedes had been pulled, was beginning to be striped in wales of

darker brown, gradually broadening to ribands. Along the edge of

each of these something crept upon ten legs, moving without haste

and without rest up and down the whole length of the field; it was

two horses and a man, the plough going between them, turning up the

cleared ground for a spring sowing.

For hours nothing relieved the joyless monotony of things. Then, far

beyond the ploughing-teams, a black speck was seen. It had come from

the corner of a fence, where there was a gap, and its tendency was

up the incline, towards the swede-cutters. From the proportions of

a mere point it advanced to the shape of a ninepin, and was soon

perceived to be a man in black, arriving from the direction of

Flintcomb-Ash. The man at the slicer, having nothing else to do with

his eyes, continually observed the comer, but Tess, who was occupied,

did not perceive him till her companion directed her attention to his

approach.

It was not her hard taskmaster, Farmer Groby; it was one in a

semi-clerical costume, who now represented what had once been the

free-and-easy Alec d'Urberville. Not being hot at his preaching

there was less enthusiasm about him now, and the presence of the

grinder seemed to embarrass him. A pale distress was already on

Tess's face, and she pulled her curtained hood further over it.

D'Urberville came up and said quietly--

"I want to speak to you, Tess."

"You have refused my last request, not to come near me!" said she.

"Yes, but I have a good reason."

"Well, tell it."

"It is more serious than you may think."

He glanced round to see if he were overheard. They were at some

distance from the man who turned the slicer, and the movement of the

machine, too, sufficiently prevented Alec's words reaching other

ears. D'Urberville placed himself so as to screen Tess from the

labourer, turning his back to the latter.

"It is this," he continued, with capricious compunction. "In

thinking of your soul and mine when we last met, I neglected to

inquire as to your worldly condition. You were well dressed, and I

did not think of it. But I see now that it is hard--harder than it

used to be when I--knew you--harder than you deserve. Perhaps a good

deal of it is owning to me!"

She did not answer, and he watched her inquiringly, as, with bent

head, her face completely screened by the hood, she resumed her

trimming of the swedes. By going on with her work she felt better

able to keep him outside her emotions.

"Tess," he added, with a sigh of discontent,--"yours was the very

worst case I ever was concerned in! I had no idea of what had

resulted till you told me. Scamp that I was to foul that innocent

life! The whole blame was mine--the whole unconventional business

of our time at Trantridge. You, too, the real blood of which I am

but the base imitation, what a blind young thing you were as to

possibilities! I say in all earnestness that it is a shame for

parents to bring up their girls in such dangerous ignorance of the

gins and nets that the wicked may set for them, whether their motive

be a good one or the result of simple indifference."

Tess still did no more than listen, throwing down one globular root

and taking up another with automatic regularity, the pensive contour

of the mere fieldwoman alone marking her.

"But it is not that I came to say," d'Urberville went on. "My

circumstances are these. I have lost my mother since you were at

Trantridge, and the place is my own. But I intend to sell it, and

devote myself to missionary work in Africa. A devil of a poor hand

I shall make at the trade, no doubt. However, what I want to ask

you is, will you put it in my power to do my duty--to make the only

reparation I can make for the trick played you: that is, will you be

my wife, and go with me? ... I have already obtained this precious

document. It was my old mother's dying wish."

He drew a piece of parchment from his pocket, with a slight fumbling

of embarrassment.

"What is it?" said she.

"A marriage licence."

"O no, sir--no!" she said quickly, starting back.

"You will not? Why is that?"

And as he asked the question a disappointment which was not entirely

the disappointment of thwarted duty crossed d'Urberville's face. It

was unmistakably a symptom that something of his old passion for her

had been revived; duty and desire ran hand-in-hand.

"Surely," he began again, in more impetuous tones, and then looked

round at the labourer who turned the slicer.

Tess, too, felt that the argument could not be ended there.

Informing the man that a gentleman had come to see her, with whom she

wished to walk a little way, she moved off with d'Urberville across

the zebra-striped field. When they reached the first newly-ploughed

section he held out his hand to help her over it; but she stepped

forward on the summits of the earth-rolls as if she did not see him.

"You will not marry me, Tess, and make me a self-respecting man?" he

repeated, as soon as they were over the furrows.

"I cannot."

"But why?"

"You know I have no affection for you."

"But you would get to feel that in time, perhaps--as soon as you

really could forgive me?"

"Never!"

"Why so positive?"

"I love somebody else."

The words seemed to astonish him.

"You do?" he cried. "Somebody else? But has not a sense of what is

morally right and proper any weight with you?"

"No, no, no--don't say that!"

"Anyhow, then, your love for this other man may be only a passing

feeling which you will overcome--"

"No--no."

"Yes, yes! Why not?"

"I cannot tell you."

"You must in honour!"

"Well then ... I have married him."

"Ah!" he exclaimed; and he stopped dead and gazed at

her.

"I did not wish to tell--I did not mean to!" she pleaded. "It is a

secret here, or at any rate but dimly known. So will you, PLEASE

will you, keep from questioning me? You must remember that we are

now strangers."

"Strangers--are we? Strangers!"

For a moment a flash of his old irony marked his face; but he

determinedly chastened it down.

"Is that man your husband?" he asked mechanically, denoting by a sign

the labourer who turned the machine.

"That man!" she said proudly. "I should think not!"

"Who, then?"

"Do not ask what I do not wish to tell!" she begged, and flashed her

appeal to him from her upturned face and lash-shadowed eyes.

D'Urberville was disturbed.

"But I only asked for your sake!" he retorted hotly. "Angels of

heaven!--God forgive me for such an expression--I came here, I swear,

as I thought for your good. Tess--don't look at me so--I cannot

stand your looks! There never were such eyes, surely, before

Christianity or since! There--I won't lose my head; I dare not.

I own that the sight of you had waked up my love for you, which, I

believed, was extinguished with all such feelings. But I thought

that our marriage might be a sanctification for us both. 'The

unbelieving husband is sanctified by the wife, and the unbelieving

wife is sanctified by the husband,' I said to myself. But my plan

is dashed from me; and I must bear the disappointment!"

He moodily reflected with his eyes on the ground.

"Married. Married! ... Well, that being so," he added, quite

calmly, tearing the licence slowly into halves and putting them in

his pocket; "that being prevented, I should like to do some good to

you and your husband, whoever he may be. There are many questions

that I am tempted to ask, but I will not do so, of course, in

opposition to your wishes. Though, if I could know your husband, I

might more easily benefit him and you. Is he on this farm?"

"No," she murmured. "He is far away."

"Far away? From YOU? What sort of husband can he be?"

"O, do not speak against him! It was through you! He found out--"

"Ah, is it so! ... That's sad, Tess!"

"Yes."

"But to stay away from you--to leave you to work like this!"

"He does not leave me to work!" she cried, springing to the defence

of the absent one with all her fervour. "He don't know it! It is by

my own arrangement."

"Then, does he write?"

"I--I cannot tell you. There are things which are private to

ourselves."

"Of course that means that he does not. You are a deserted wife, my

fair Tess--"

In an impulse he turned suddenly to take her hand; the buff-glove was

on it, and he seized only the rough leather fingers which did not

express the life or shape of those within.

"You must not--you must not!" she cried fearfully, slipping her hand

from the glove as from a pocket, and leaving it in his grasp. "O,

will you go away--for the sake of me and my husband--go, in the name

of your own Christianity!"

"Yes, yes; I will," he said abruptly, and thrusting the glove back to

her he turned to leave. Facing round, however, he said, "Tess, as

God is my judge, I meant no humbug in taking your hand!"

A pattering of hoofs on the soil of the field, which they had not

noticed in their preoccupation, ceased close behind them; and a voice

reached her ear:

"What the devil are you doing away from your work at this time o'

day?"

Farmer Groby had espied the two figures from the distance, and had

inquisitively ridden across, to learn what was their business in his

field.

"Don't speak like that to her!" said d'Urberville, his face

blackening with something that was not Christianity.

"Indeed, Mister! And what mid Methodist pa'sons have to do with

she?"

"Who is the fellow?" asked d'Urberville, turning to Tess.

She went close up to him.

"Go--I do beg you!" she said.

"What! And leave you to that tyrant? I can see in his face what a

churl he is."

"He won't hurt me. HE'S not in love with me. I can leave at

Lady-Day."

"Well, I have no right but to obey, I suppose. But--well, goodbye!"

Her defender, whom she dreaded more than her assailant, having

reluctantly disappeared, the farmer continued his reprimand, which

Tess took with the greatest coolness, that sort of attack being

independent of sex. To have as a master this man of stone, who would

have cuffed her if he had dared, was almost a relief after her former

experiences. She silently walked back towards the summit of the

field that was the scene of her labour, so absorbed in the interview

which had just taken place that she was hardly aware that the nose of

Groby's horse almost touched her shoulders.

"If so be you make an agreement to work for me till Lady-Day, I'll

see that you carry it out," he growled. "'Od rot the women--now

'tis one thing, and then 'tis another. But I'll put up with it no

longer!"

Knowing very well that he did not harass the other women of the

farm as he harassed her out of spite for the flooring he had once

received, she did for one moment picture what might have been the

result if she had been free to accept the offer just made her of

being the monied Alec's wife. It would have lifted her completely

out of subjection, not only to her present oppressive employer, but

to a whole world who seemed to despise her. "But no, no!" she said

breathlessly; "I could not have married him now! He is so unpleasant

to me."

That very night she began an appealing letter to Clare, concealing

from him her hardships, and assuring him of her undying affection.

Any one who had been in a position to read between the lines would

have seen that at the back of her great love was some monstrous

fear--almost a desperation--as to some secret contingencies which

were not disclosed. But again she did not finish her effusion; he

had asked Izz to go with him, and perhaps he did not care for her at

all. She put the letter in her box, and wondered if it would ever

reach Angel's hands.

After this her daily tasks were gone through heavily enough, and

brought on the day which was of great import to agriculturists--the

day of the Candlemas Fair. It was at this fair that new engagements

were entered into for the twelve months following the ensuing

Lady-Day, and those of the farming population who thought of changing

their places duly attended at the county-town where the fair was

held. Nearly all the labourers on Flintcomb-Ash farm intended

flight, and early in the morning there was a general exodus in the

direction of the town, which lay at a distance of from ten to a dozen

miles over hilly country. Though Tess also meant to leave at the

quarter-day, she was one of the few who did not go to the fair,

having a vaguely-shaped hope that something would happen to render

another outdoor engagement unnecessary.

It was a peaceful February day, of wonderful softness for the time,

and one would almost have thought that winter was over. She had

hardly finished her dinner when d'Urberville's figure darkened the

window of the cottage wherein she was a lodger, which she had all to

herself to-day.

Tess jumped up, but her visitor had knocked at the door, and she

could hardly in reason run away. D'Urberville's knock, his walk up

to the door, had some indescribable quality of difference from his

air when she last saw him. They seemed to be acts of which the doer

was ashamed. She thought that she would not open the door; but, as

there was no sense in that either, she arose, and having lifted the

latch stepped back quickly. He came in, saw her, and flung himself

down into a chair before speaking.

"Tess--I couldn't help it!" he began desperately, as he wiped his

heated face, which had also a superimposed flush of excitement. "I

felt that I must call at least to ask how you are. I assure you I

had not been thinking of you at all till I saw you that Sunday; now I

cannot get rid of your image, try how I may! It is hard that a good

woman should do harm to a bad man; yet so it is. If you would only

pray for me, Tess!"

The suppressed discontent of his manner was almost pitiable, and yet

Tess did not pity him.

"How can I pray for you," she said, "when I am forbidden to believe

that the great Power who moves the world would alter His plans on my

account?"

"You really think that?"

"Yes. I have been cured of the presumption of thinking otherwise."

"Cured? By whom?"

"By my husband, if I must tell."

"Ah--your husband--your husband! How strange it seems! I remember

you hinted something of the sort the other day. What do you really

believe in these matters, Tess?" he asked. "You seem to have no

religion--perhaps owing to me."

"But I have. Though I don't believe in anything supernatural."

D'Urberville looked at her with misgiving.

"Then do you think that the line I take is all wrong?"

"A good deal of it."

"H'm--and yet I've felt so sure about it," he said uneasily.

"I believe in the SPIRIT of the Sermon on the Mount, and so did my

dear husband... But I don't believe--"

Here she gave her negations.

"The fact is," said d'Urberville drily, "whatever your dear husband

believed you accept, and whatever he rejected you reject, without the

least inquiry or reasoning on your own part. That's just like you

women. Your mind is enslaved to his."

"Ah, because he knew everything!" said she, with a triumphant

simplicity of faith in Angel Clare that the most perfect man could

hardly have deserved, much less her husband.

"Yes, but you should not take negative opinions wholesale from

another person like that. A pretty fellow he must be to teach you

such scepticism!"

"He never forced my judgement! He would never argue on the subject

with me! But I looked at it in this way; what he believed, after

inquiring deep into doctrines, was much more likely to be right than

what I might believe, who hadn't looked into doctrines at all."

"What used he to say? He must have said something?"

She reflected; and with her acute memory for the letter of Angel

Clare's remarks, even when she did not comprehend their spirit, she

recalled a merciless polemical syllogism that she had heard him

use when, as it occasionally happened, he indulged in a species of

thinking aloud with her at his side. In delivering it she gave also

Clare's accent and manner with reverential faithfulness.

"Say that again," asked d'Urberville, who had listened with the

greatest attention.

She repeated the argument, and d'Urberville thoughtfully murmured the

words after her.

"Anything else?" he presently asked.

"He said at another time something like this"; and she gave another,

which might possibly have been paralleled in many a work of the

pedigree ranging from the _Dictionnaire Philosophique_ to Huxley's

_Essays_.

"Ah--ha! How do you remember them?"

"I wanted to believe what he believed, though he didn't wish me to;

and I managed to coax him to tell me a few of his thoughts. I can't

say I quite understand that one; but I know it is right."

"H'm. Fancy your being able to teach me what you don't know

yourself!"

He fell into thought.

"And so I threw in my spiritual lot with his," she resumed. "I

didn't wish it to be different. What's good enough for him is good

enough for me."

"Does he know that you are as big an infidel as he?"

"No--I never told him--if I am an infidel."

"Well--you are better off to-day that I am, Tess, after all! You

don't believe that you ought to preach my doctrine, and, therefore,

do no despite to your conscience in abstaining. I do believe I ought

to preach it, but, like the devils, I believe and tremble, for I

suddenly leave off preaching it, and give way to my passion for you."

"How?"

"Why," he said aridly; "I have come all the way here to see you

to-day! But I started from home to go to Casterbridge Fair, where

I have undertaken to preach the Word from a waggon at half-past two

this afternoon, and where all the brethren are expecting me this

minute. Here's the announcement."

He drew from his breast-pocket a poster whereon was printed the day,

hour, and place of meeting, at which he, d'Urberville, would preach

the Gospel as aforesaid.

"But how can you get there?" said Tess, looking at the clock.

"I cannot get there! I have come here."

"What, you have really arranged to preach, and--"

"I have arranged to preach, and I shall not be there--by reason of my

burning desire to see a woman whom I once despised!--No, by my word

and truth, I never despised you; if I had I should not love you now!

Why I did not despise you was on account of your being unsmirched in

spite of all; you withdrew yourself from me so quickly and resolutely

when you saw the situation; you did not remain at my pleasure; so

there was one petticoat in the world for whom I had no contempt,

and you are she. But you may well despise me now! I thought I

worshipped on the mountains, but I find I still serve in the groves!

Ha! ha!"

"O Alec d'Urberville! what does this mean? What have I done!"

"Done?" he said, with a soulless sneer in the word. "Nothing

intentionally. But you have been the means--the innocent means--of

my backsliding, as they call it. I ask myself, am I, indeed, one of

those 'servants of corruption' who, 'after they have escaped the

pollutions of the world, are again entangled therein and overcome'--

whose latter end is worse than their beginning?" He laid his hand on

her shoulder. "Tess, my girl, I was on the way to, at least, social

salvation till I saw you again!" he said freakishly shaking her, as

if she were a child. "And why then have you tempted me? I was firm

as a man could be till I saw those eyes and that mouth again--surely

there never was such a maddening mouth since Eve's!" His voice sank,

and a hot archness shot from his own black eyes. "You temptress,

Tess; you dear damned witch of Babylon--I could not resist you as

soon as I met you again!"

"I couldn't help your seeing me again!" said Tess, recoiling.

"I know it--I repeat that I do not blame you. But the fact remains.

When I saw you ill-used on the farm that day I was nearly mad to

think that I had no legal right to protect you--that I could not have

it; whilst he who has it seems to neglect you utterly!"

"Don't speak against him--he is absent!" she cried in much

excitement. "Treat him honourably--he has never wronged you! O

leave his wife before any scandal spreads that may do harm to his

honest name!"

"I will--I will," he said, like a man awakening from a luring dream.

"I have broken my engagement to preach to those poor drunken boobies

at the fair--it is the first time I have played such a practical

joke. A month ago I should have been horrified at such a

possibility. I'll go away--to swear--and--ah, can I! to keep away."

Then, suddenly: "One clasp, Tessy--one! Only for old friendship--"

"I am without defence. Alec! A good man's honour is in my keeping--

think--be ashamed!"

"Pooh! Well, yes--yes!"

He clenched his lips, mortified with himself for his weakness. His

eyes were equally barren of worldly and religious faith. The corpses

of those old fitful passions which had lain inanimate amid the lines

of his face ever since his reformation seemed to wake and come

together as in a resurrection. He went out indeterminately.

Though d'Urberville had declared that this breach of his engagement

to-day was the simple backsliding of a believer, Tess's words, as

echoed from Angel Clare, had made a deep impression upon him, and

continued to do so after he had left her. He moved on in silence, as

if his energies were benumbed by the hitherto undreamt-of possibility

that his position was untenable. Reason had had nothing to do with

his whimsical conversion, which was perhaps the mere freak of a

careless man in search of a new sensation, and temporarily impressed

by his mother's death.

The drops of logic Tess had let fall into the sea of his enthusiasm

served to chill its effervescence to stagnation. He said to himself,

as he pondered again and again over the crystallized phrases that she

had handed on to him, "That clever fellow little thought that, by

telling her those things, he might be paving my way back to her!"

XLVII

It is the threshing of the last wheat-rick at Flintcomb-Ash farm. The

dawn of the March morning is singularly inexpressive, and there is

nothing to show where the eastern horizon lies. Against the twilight

rises the trapezoidal top of the stack, which has stood forlornly

here through the washing and bleaching of the wintry weather.

When Izz Huett and Tess arrived at the scene of operations only a

rustling denoted that others had preceded them; to which, as the

light increased, there were presently added the silhouettes of two

men on the summit. They were busily "unhaling" the rick, that

is, stripping off the thatch before beginning to throw down the

sheaves; and while this was in progress Izz and Tess, with the

other women-workers, in their whitey-brown pinners, stood waiting

and shivering, Farmer Groby having insisted upon their being on

the spot thus early to get the job over if possible by the end of

the day. Close under the eaves of the stack, and as yet barely

visible, was the red tyrant that the women had come to serve--a

timber-framed construction, with straps and wheels appertaining--

the threshing-machine which, whilst it was going, kept up a

despotic demand upon the endurance of their muscles and nerves.

A little way off there was another indistinct figure; this one black,

with a sustained hiss that spoke of strength very much in reserve.

The long chimney running up beside an ash-tree, and the warmth which

radiated from the spot, explained without the necessity of much

daylight that here was the engine which was to act as the _primum

mobile_ of this little world. By the engine stood a dark, motionless

being, a sooty and grimy embodiment of tallness, in a sort of trance,

with a heap of coals by his side: it was the engine-man. The

isolation of his manner and colour lent him the appearance of a

creature from Tophet, who had strayed into the pellucid smokelessness

of this region of yellow grain and pale soil, with which he had

nothing in common, to amaze and to discompose its aborigines.

What he looked he felt. He was in the agricultural world, but not of

it. He served fire and smoke; these denizens of the fields served

vegetation, weather, frost, and sun. He travelled with his engine

from farm to farm, from county to county, for as yet the steam

threshing-machine was itinerant in this part of Wessex. He spoke in

a strange northern accent; his thoughts being turned inwards upon

himself, his eye on his iron charge, hardly perceiving the scenes

around him, and caring for them not at all: holding only strictly

necessary intercourse with the natives, as if some ancient doom

compelled him to wander here against his will in the service of his

Plutonic master. The long strap which ran from the driving-wheel of

his engine to the red thresher under the rick was the sole tie-line

between agriculture and him.

While they uncovered the sheaves he stood apathetic beside his

portable repository of force, round whose hot blackness the morning

air quivered. He had nothing to do with preparatory labour. His

fire was waiting incandescent, his steam was at high pressure, in

a few seconds he could make the long strap move at an invisible

velocity. Beyond its extent the environment might be corn, straw,

or chaos; it was all the same to him. If any of the autochthonous

idlers asked him what he called himself, he replied shortly, "an

engineer."

The rick was unhaled by full daylight; the men then took their

places, the women mounted, and the work began. Farmer Groby--or, as

they called him, "he"--had arrived ere this, and by his orders Tess

was placed on the platform of the machine, close to the man who fed

it, her business being to untie every sheaf of corn handed on to her

by Izz Huett, who stood next, but on the rick; so that the feeder

could seize it and spread it over the revolving drum, which whisked

out every grain in one moment.

They were soon in full progress, after a preparatory hitch or two,

which rejoiced the hearts of those who hated machinery. The work

sped on till breakfast time, when the thresher was stopped for half

an hour; and on starting again after the meal the whole supplementary

strength of the farm was thrown into the labour of constructing the

straw-rick, which began to grow beside the stack of corn. A hasty

lunch was eaten as they stood, without leaving their positions, and

then another couple of hours brought them near to dinner-time; the

inexorable wheel continuing to spin, and the penetrating hum of the

thresher to thrill to the very marrow all who were near the revolving

wire-cage.

The old men on the rising straw-rick talked of the past days

when they had been accustomed to thresh with flails on the oaken

barn-floor; when everything, even to winnowing, was effected by

hand-labour, which, to their thinking, though slow, produced better

results. Those, too, on the corn-rick talked a little; but the

perspiring ones at the machine, including Tess, could not lighten

their duties by the exchange of many words. It was the ceaselessness

of the work which tried her so severely, and began to make her

wish that she had never some to Flintcomb-Ash. The women on the

corn-rick--Marian, who was one of them, in particular--could stop to

drink ale or cold tea from the flagon now and then, or to exchange

a few gossiping remarks while they wiped their faces or cleared the

fragments of straw and husk from their clothing; but for Tess there

was no respite; for, as the drum never stopped, the man who fed

it could not stop, and she, who had to supply the man with untied

sheaves, could not stop either, unless Marian changed places with

her, which she sometimes did for half an hour in spite of Groby's

objections that she was too slow-handed for a feeder.

For some probably economical reason it was usually a woman who was

chosen for this particular duty, and Groby gave as his motive in

selecting Tess that she was one of those who best combined strength

with quickness in untying, and both with staying power, and this may

have been true. The hum of the thresher, which prevented speech,

increased to a raving whenever the supply of corn fell short of the

regular quantity. As Tess and the man who fed could never turn their

heads she did not know that just before the dinner-hour a person had

come silently into the field by the gate, and had been standing under

a second rick watching the scene and Tess in particular. He was

dressed in a tweed suit of fashionable pattern, and he twirled a gay

walking-cane.

"Who is that?" said Izz Huett to Marian. She had at first addressed

the inquiry to Tess, but the latter could not hear it.

"Somebody's fancy-man, I s'pose," said Marian laconically.

"I'll lay a guinea he's after Tess."

"O no. 'Tis a ranter pa'son who's been sniffing after her lately;

not a dandy like this."

"Well--this is the same man."

"The same man as the preacher? But he's quite different!"

"He hev left off his black coat and white neckercher, and hev cut off

his whiskers; but he's the same man for all that."

"D'ye really think so? Then I'll tell her," said Marian.

"Don't. She'll see him soon enough, good-now."

"Well, I don't think it at all right for him to join his preaching to

courting a married woman, even though her husband mid be abroad, and

she, in a sense, a widow."

"Oh--he can do her no harm," said Izz drily. "Her mind can no more

be heaved from that one place where it do bide than a stooded waggon

from the hole he's in. Lord love 'ee, neither court-paying, nor

preaching, nor the seven thunders themselves, can wean a woman when

'twould be better for her that she should be weaned."

Dinner-time came, and the whirling ceased; whereupon Tess left her

post, her knees trembling so wretchedly with the shaking of the

machine that she could scarcely walk.

"You ought to het a quart o' drink into 'ee, as I've done," said

Marian. "You wouldn't look so white then. Why, souls above us,

your face is as if you'd been hagrode!"

It occurred to the good-natured Marian that, as Tess was so tired,

her discovery of her visitor's presence might have the bad effect of

taking away her appetite; and Marian was thinking of inducing Tess

to descend by a ladder on the further side of the stack when the

gentleman came forward and looked up.

Tess uttered a short little "Oh!" And a moment after she said,

quickly, "I shall eat my dinner here--right on the rick."

Sometimes, when they were so far from their cottages, they all did

this; but as there was rather a keen wind going to-day, Marian and

the rest descended, and sat under the straw-stack.

The newcomer was, indeed, Alec d'Urberville, the late Evangelist,

despite his changed attire and aspect. It was obvious at a glance

that the original _Weltlust_ had come back; that he had restored

himself, as nearly as a man could do who had grown three or four

years older, to the old jaunty, slapdash guise under which Tess

had first known her admirer, and cousin so-called. Having decided

to remain where she was, Tess sat down among the bundles, out of

sight of the ground, and began her meal; till, by-and-by, she heard

footsteps on the ladder, and immediately after Alec appeared upon the

stack--now an oblong and level platform of sheaves. He strode across

them, and sat down opposite of her without a word.

Tess continued to eat her modest dinner, a slice of thick pancake

which she had brought with her. The other workfolk were by this

time all gathered under the rick, where the loose straw formed a

comfortable retreat.

"I am here again, as you see," said d'Urberville.

"Why do you trouble me so!" she cried, reproach flashing from her

very finger-ends.

"I trouble YOU? I think I may ask, why do you trouble me?"

"Sure, I don't trouble you any-when!"

"You say you don't? But you do! You haunt me. Those very eyes that

you turned upon my with such a bitter flash a moment ago, they come

to me just as you showed them then, in the night and in the day!

Tess, ever since you told me of that child of ours, it is just as if

my feelings, which have been flowing in a strong puritanical stream,

had suddenly found a way open in the direction of you, and had all at

once gushed through. The religious channel is left dry forthwith;

and it is you who have done it!"

She gazed in silence.

"What--you have given up your preaching entirely?" she asked. She

had gathered from Angel sufficient of the incredulity of modern

thought to despise flash enthusiasm; but, as a woman, she was

somewhat appalled.

In affected severity d'Urberville continued--

"Entirely. I have broken every engagement since that afternoon I was

to address the drunkards at Casterbridge Fair. The deuce only knows

what I am thought of by the brethren. Ah-ha! The brethren! No

doubt they pray for me--weep for me; for they are kind people in

their way. But what do I care? How could I go on with the thing

when I had lost my faith in it?--it would have been hypocrisy of

the basest kind! Among them I should have stood like Hymenaeus and

Alexander, who were delivered over to Satan that they might learn

not to blaspheme. What a grand revenge you have taken! I saw you

innocent, and I deceived you. Four years after, you find me a

Christian enthusiast; you then work upon me, perhaps to my complete

perdition! But Tess, my coz, as I used to call you, this is only

my way of talking, and you must not look so horribly concerned.

Of course you have done nothing except retain your pretty face and

shapely figure. I saw it on the rick before you saw me--that tight

pinafore-thing sets it off, and that wing-bonnet--you field-girls

should never wear those bonnets if you wish to keep out of danger."

He regarded her silently for a few moments, and with a short cynical

laugh resumed: "I believe that if the bachelor-apostle, whose deputy

I thought I was, had been tempted by such a pretty face, he would

have let go the plough for her sake as I do!"

Tess attempted to expostulate, but at this juncture all her fluency

failed her, and without heeding he added:

"Well, this paradise that you supply is perhaps as good as any other,

after all. But to speak seriously, Tess." D'Urberville rose and

came nearer, reclining sideways amid the sheaves, and resting upon

his elbow. "Since I last saw you, I have been thinking of what

you said that HE said. I have come to the conclusion that there

does seem rather a want of common-sense in these threadbare old

propositions; how I could have been so fired by poor Parson Clare's

enthusiasm, and have gone so madly to work, transcending even him, I

cannot make out! As for what you said last time, on the strength of

your wonderful husband's intelligence--whose name you have never told

me--about having what they call an ethical system without any dogma,

I don't see my way to that at all."

"Why, you can have the religion of loving-kindness and purity at

least, if you can't have--what do you call it--dogma."

"O no! I'm a different sort of fellow from that! If there's nobody

to say, 'Do this, and it will be a good thing for you after you are

dead; do that, and if will be a bad thing for you,' I can't warm up.

Hang it, I am not going to feel responsible for my deeds and passions

if there's nobody to be responsible to; and if I were you, my dear,

I wouldn't either!"

She tried to argue, and tell him that he had mixed in his dull

brain two matters, theology and morals, which in the primitive days

of mankind had been quite distinct. But owing to Angel Clare's

reticence, to her absolute want of training, and to her being a

vessel of emotions rather than reasons, she could not get on.

"Well, never mind," he resumed. "Here I am, my love, as in the old

times!"

"Not as then--never as then--'tis different!" she entreated. "And

there was never warmth with me! O why didn't you keep your faith,

if the loss of it has brought you to speak to me like this!"

"Because you've knocked it out of me; so the evil be upon your sweet

head! Your husband little thought how his teaching would recoil upon

him! Ha-ha--I'm awfully glad you have made an apostate of me all the

same! Tess, I am more taken with you than ever, and I pity you too.

For all your closeness, I see you are in a bad way--neglected by one

who ought to cherish you."

She could not get her morsels of food down her throat; her lips

were dry, and she was ready to choke. The voices and laughs of the

workfolk eating and drinking under the rick came to her as if they

were a quarter of a mile off.

"It is cruelty to me!" she said. "How--how can you treat me to this

talk, if you care ever so little for me?"

"True, true," he said, wincing a little. "I did not come to reproach

you for my deeds. I came Tess, to say that I don't like you to be

working like this, and I have come on purpose for you. You say you

have a husband who is not I. Well, perhaps you have; but I've never

seen him, and you've not told me his name; and altogether he seems

rather a mythological personage. However, even if you have one, I

think I am nearer to you than he is. I, at any rate, try to help you

out of trouble, but he does not, bless his invisible face! The words

of the stern prophet Hosea that I used to read come back to me.

Don't you know them, Tess?--'And she shall follow after her lover,

but she shall not overtake him; and she shall seek him, but shall

not find him; then shall she say, I will go and return to my first

husband; for then was it better with me than now!' ... Tess, my trap

is waiting just under the hill, and--darling mine, not his!--you know

the rest."

Her face had been rising to a dull crimson fire while he spoke; but

she did not answer.

"You have been the cause of my backsliding," he continued, stretching

his arm towards her waist; "you should be willing to share it, and

leave that mule you call husband for ever."

One of her leather gloves, which she had taken off to eat her

skimmer-cake, lay in her lap, and without the slightest warning she

passionately swung the glove by the gauntlet directly in his face.

It was heavy and thick as a warrior's, and it struck him flat on the

mouth. Fancy might have regarded the act as the recrudescence of

a trick in which her armed progenitors were not unpractised. Alec

fiercely started up from his reclining position. A scarlet oozing

appeared where her blow had alighted, and in a moment the blood began

dropping from his mouth upon the straw. But he soon controlled

himself, calmly drew his handkerchief from his pocket, and mopped

his bleeding lips.

She too had sprung up, but she sank down again. "Now, punish me!" she

said, turning up her eyes to him with the hopeless defiance of the

sparrow's gaze before its captor twists its neck. "Whip me, crush

me; you need not mind those people under the rick! I shall not cry

out. Once victim, always victim--that's the law!"

"O no, no, Tess," he said blandly. "I can make full allowance for

this. Yet you most unjustly forget one thing, that I would have

married you if you had not put it out of my power to do so. Did I

not ask you flatly to be my wife--hey? Answer me."

"You did."

"And you cannot be. But remember one thing!" His voice hardened

as his temper got the better of him with the recollection of his

sincerity in asking her and her present ingratitude, and he stepped

across to her side and held her by the shoulders, so that she shook

under his grasp. "Remember, my lady, I was your master once! I will

be your master again. If you are any man's wife you are mine!"

The threshers now began to stir below.

"So much for our quarrel," he said, letting her go. "Now I shall

leave you, and shall come again for your answer during the afternoon.

You don't know me yet! But I know you."

She had not spoken again, remaining as if stunned. D'Urberville

retreated over the sheaves, and descended the ladder, while the

workers below rose and stretched their arms, and shook down the beer

they had drunk. Then the threshing-machine started afresh; and amid

the renewed rustle of the straw Tess resumed her position by the

buzzing drum as one in a dream, untying sheaf after sheaf in endless

succession.

XLVIII

In the afternoon the farmer made it known that the rick was to be

finished that night, since there was a moon by which they could see

to work, and the man with the engine was engaged for another farm on

the morrow. Hence the twanging and humming and rustling proceeded

with even less intermission than usual.

It was not till "nammet"-time, about three o-clock, that Tess raised

her eyes and gave a momentary glance round. She felt but little

surprise at seeing that Alec d'Urberville had come back, and was

standing under the hedge by the gate. He had seen her lift her

eyes, and waved his hand urbanely to her, while he blew her a kiss.

It meant that their quarrel was over. Tess looked down again, and

carefully abstained from gazing in that direction.

Thus the afternoon dragged on. The wheat-rick shrank lower, and the

straw-rick grew higher, and the corn-sacks were carted away. At six

o'clock the wheat-rick was about shoulder-high from the ground. But

the unthreshed sheaves remaining untouched seemed countless still,

notwithstanding the enormous numbers that had been gulped down by

the insatiable swallower, fed by the man and Tess, through whose two

young hands the greater part of them had passed. And the immense

stack of straw where in the morning there had been nothing, appeared

as the faeces of the same buzzing red glutton. From the west sky

a wrathful shine--all that wild March could afford in the way of

sunset--had burst forth after the cloudy day, flooding the tired and

sticky faces of the threshers, and dyeing them with a coppery light,

as also the flapping garments of the women, which clung to them like

dull flames.

A panting ache ran through the rick. The man who fed was weary, and

Tess could see that the red nape of his neck was encrusted with dirt

and husks. She still stood at her post, her flushed and perspiring

face coated with the corndust, and her white bonnet embrowned by it.

She was the only woman whose place was upon the machine so as to be

shaken bodily by its spinning, and the decrease of the stack now

separated her from Marian and Izz, and prevented their changing

duties with her as they had done. The incessant quivering, in

which every fibre of her frame participated, had thrown her into a

stupefied reverie in which her arms worked on independently of her

consciousness. She hardly knew where she was, and did not hear Izz

Huett tell her from below that her hair was tumbling down.

By degrees the freshest among them began to grow cadaverous and

saucer-eyed. Whenever Tess lifted her head she beheld always the

great upgrown straw-stack, with the men in shirt-sleeves upon it,

against the gray north sky; in front of it the long red elevator

like a Jacob's ladder, on which a perpetual stream of threshed straw

ascended, a yellow river running uphill, and spouting out on the top

of the rick.

She knew that Alec d'Urberville was still on the scene, observing

her from some point or other, though she could not say where. There

was an excuse for his remaining, for when the threshed rick drew

near its final sheaves a little ratting was always done, and men

unconnected with the threshing sometimes dropped in for that

performance--sporting characters of all descriptions, gents with

terriers and facetious pipes, roughs with sticks and stones.

But there was another hour's work before the layer of live rats at

the base of the stack would be reached; and as the evening light in

the direction of the Giant's Hill by Abbot's-Cernel dissolved away,

the white-faced moon of the season arose from the horizon that lay

towards Middleton Abbey and Shottsford on the other side. For the

last hour or two Marian had felt uneasy about Tess, whom she could

not get near enough to speak to, the other women having kept up their

strength by drinking ale, and Tess having done without it through

traditionary dread, owing to its results at her home in childhood.

But Tess still kept going: if she could not fill her part she would

have to leave; and this contingency, which she would have regarded

with equanimity and even with relief a month or two earlier, had

become a terror since d'Urberville had begun to hover round her.

The sheaf-pitchers and feeders had now worked the rick so low that

people on the ground could talk to them. To Tess's surprise Farmer

Groby came up on the machine to her, and said that if she desired to

join her friend he did not wish her to keep on any longer, and would

send somebody else to take her place. The "friend" was d'Urberville,

she knew, and also that this concession had been granted in obedience

to the request of that friend, or enemy. She shook her head and

toiled on.

The time for the rat-catching arrived at last, and the hunt began.

The creatures had crept downwards with the subsidence of the rick

till they were all together at the bottom, and being now uncovered

from their last refuge, they ran across the open ground in all

directions, a loud shriek from the by-this-time half-tipsy Marian

informing her companions that one of the rats had invaded her

person--a terror which the rest of the women had guarded against by

various schemes of skirt-tucking and self-elevation. The rat was

at last dislodged, and, amid the barking of dogs, masculine shouts,

feminine screams, oaths, stampings, and confusion as of Pandemonium,

Tess untied her last sheaf; the drum slowed, the whizzing ceased,

and she stepped from the machine to the ground.

Her lover, who had only looked on at the rat-catching, was promptly

at her side.

"What--after all--my insulting slap, too!" said she in an

underbreath. She was so utterly exhausted that she had not strength

to speak louder.

"I should indeed be foolish to feel offended at anything you say or

do," he answered, in the seductive voice of the Trantridge time.

"How the little limbs tremble! You are as weak as a bled calf, you

know you are; and yet you need have done nothing since I arrived.

How could you be so obstinate? However, I have told the farmer that

he has no right to employ women at steam-threshing. It is not proper

work for them; and on all the better class of farms it has been given

up, as he knows very well. I will walk with you as far as your

home."

"O yes," she answered with a jaded gait. "Walk wi' me if you will!

I do bear in mind that you came to marry me before you knew o' my

state. Perhaps--perhaps you are a little better and kinder than I

have been thinking you were. Whatever is meant as kindness I am

grateful for; whatever is meant in any other way I am angered at.

I cannot sense your meaning sometimes."

"If I cannot legitimize our former relations at least I can assist

you. And I will do it with much more regard for your feelings than

I formerly showed. My religious mania, or whatever it was, is over.

But I retain a little good nature; I hope I do. Now, Tess, by

all that's tender and strong between man and woman, trust me! I

have enough and more than enough to put you out of anxiety, both

for yourself and your parents and sisters. I can make them all

comfortable if you will only show confidence in me."

"Have you seen 'em lately?" she quickly inquired.

"Yes. They didn't know where you were. It was only by chance that I

found you here."

The cold moon looked aslant upon Tess's fagged face between the twigs

of the garden-hedge as she paused outside the cottage which was her

temporary home, d'Urberville pausing beside her.

"Don't mention my little brothers and sisters--don't make me break

down quite!" she said. "If you want to help them--God knows they

need it--do it without telling me. But no, no!" she cried. "I will

take nothing from you, either for them or for me!"

He did not accompany her further, since, as she lived with the

household, all was public indoors. No sooner had she herself

entered, laved herself in a washing-tub, and shared supper with the

family than she fell into thought, and withdrawing to the table under

the wall, by the light of her own little lamp wrote in a passionate

mood--

MY OWN HUSBAND,--

Let me call you so--I must--even if it makes you angry to

think of such an unworthy wife as I. I must cry to you

in my trouble--I have no one else! I am so exposed to

temptation, Angel. I fear to say who it is, and I do not

like to write about it at all. But I cling to you in a way

you cannot think! Can you not come to me now, at once,

before anything terrible happens? O, I know you cannot,

because you are so far away! I think I must die if you do

not come soon, or tell me to come to you. The punishment

you have measured out to me is deserved--I do know that--

well deserved--and you are right and just to be angry with

me. But, Angel, please, please, not to be just--only a

little kind to me, even if I do not deserve it, and come to

me! If you would come, I could die in your arms! I would

be well content to do that if so be you had forgiven me!

Angel, I live entirely for you. I love you too much to

blame you for going away, and I know it was necessary you

should find a farm. Do not think I shall say a word of

sting or bitterness. Only come back to me. I am desolate

without you, my darling, O, so desolate! I do not mind

having to work: but if you will send me one little line,

and say, "I am coming soon," I will bide on, Angel--O, so

cheerfully!

It has been so much my religion ever since we were married

to be faithful to you in every thought and look, that even

when a man speaks a compliment to me before I am aware, it

seems wronging you. Have you never felt one little bit of

what you used to feel when we were at the dairy? If you

have, how can you keep away from me? I am the same women,

Angel, as you fell in love with; yes, the very same!--not

the one you disliked but never saw. What was the past to me

as soon as I met you? It was a dead thing altogether. I

became another woman, filled full of new life from you. How

could I be the early one? Why do you not see this? Dear,

if you would only be a little more conceited, and believe

in yourself so far as to see that you were strong enough to

work this change in me, you would perhaps be in a mind to

come to me, your poor wife.

How silly I was in my happiness when I thought I could trust

you always to love me! I ought to have known that such as

that was not for poor me. But I am sick at heart, not only

for old times, but for the present. Think--think how it do

hurt my heart not to see you ever--ever! Ah, if I could

only make your dear heart ache one little minute of each day

as mine does every day and all day long, it might lead you

to show pity to your poor lonely one.

People still say that I am rather pretty, Angel (handsome is

the word they use, since I wish to be truthful). Perhaps I

am what they say. But I do not value my good looks; I only

like to have them because they belong to you, my dear, and

that there may be at least one thing about me worth your

having. So much have I felt this, that when I met with

annoyance on account of the same, I tied up my face in a

bandage as long as people would believe in it. O Angel, I

tell you all this not from vanity--you will certainly know

I do not--but only that you may come to me!

If you really cannot come to me, will you let me come to

you? I am, as I say, worried, pressed to do what I will

not do. It cannot be that I shall yield one inch, yet I am

in terror as to what an accident might lead to, and I so

defenceless on account of my first error. I cannot say more

about this--it makes me too miserable. But if I break down

by falling into some fearful snare, my last state will be

worse than my first. O God, I cannot think of it! Let me

come at once, or at once come to me!

I would be content, ay, glad, to live with you as your

servant, if I may not as your wife; so that I could only be

near you, and get glimpses of you, and think of you as mine.

The daylight has nothing to show me, since you are not here,

and I don't like to see the rooks and starlings in the

field, because I grieve and grieve to miss you who used to

see them with me. I long for only one thing in heaven or

earth or under the earth, to meet you, my own dear! Come

to me--come to me, and save me from what threatens me!--

Your faithful heartbroken

TESS

XLIX

The appeal duly found its way to the breakfast-table of the quiet

Vicarage to the westward, in that valley where the air is so soft and

the soil so rich that the effort of growth requires but superficial

aid by comparison with the tillage at Flintcomb-Ash, and where to

Tess the human world seemed so different (though it was much the

same). It was purely for security that she had been requested by

Angel to send her communications through his father, whom he kept

pretty well informed of his changing addresses in the country he

had gone to exploit for himself with a heavy heart.

"Now," said old Mr Clare to his wife, when he had read the envelope,

"if Angel proposes leaving Rio for a visit home at the end of next

month, as he told us that he hoped to do, I think this may hasten his

plans; for I believe it to be from his wife." He breathed deeply at

the thought of her; and the letter was redirected to be promptly sent

on to Angel.

"Dear fellow, I hope he will get home safely," murmured Mrs Clare.

"To my dying day I shall feel that he has been ill-used. You should

have sent him to Cambridge in spite of his want of faith and given

him the same chance as the other boys had. He would have grown out

of it under proper influence, and perhaps would have taken Orders

after all. Church or no Church, it would have been fairer to him."

This was the only wail with which Mrs Clare ever disturbed her

husband's peace in respect to their sons. And she did not vent this

often; for she was as considerate as she was devout, and knew that

his mind too was troubled by doubts as to his justice in this matter.

Only too often had she heard him lying awake at night, stifling sighs

for Angel with prayers. But the uncompromising Evangelical did not

even now hold that he would have been justified in giving his son,

an unbeliever, the same academic advantages that he had given to the

two others, when it was possible, if not probable, that those very

advantages might have been used to decry the doctrines which he had

made it his life's mission and desire to propagate, and the mission

of his ordained sons likewise. To put with one hand a pedestal

under the feet of the two faithful ones, and with the other to exalt

the unfaithful by the same artificial means, he deemed to be alike

inconsistent with his convictions, his position, and his hopes.

Nevertheless, he loved his misnamed Angel, and in secret mourned

over this treatment of him as Abraham might have mourned over the

doomed Isaac while they went up the hill together. His silent

self-generated regrets were far bitterer than the reproaches which

his wife rendered audible.

They blamed themselves for this unlucky marriage. If Angel had never

been destined for a farmer he would never have been thrown with

agricultural girls. They did not distinctly know what had separated

him and his wife, nor the date on which the separation had taken

place. At first they had supposed it must be something of the nature

of a serious aversion. But in his later letters he occasionally

alluded to the intention of coming home to fetch her; from which

expressions they hoped the division might not owe its origin to

anything so hopelessly permanent as that. He had told them that she

was with her relatives, and in their doubts they had decided not to

intrude into a situation which they knew no way of bettering.

The eyes for which Tess's letter was intended were gazing at this

time on a limitless expanse of country from the back of a mule which

was bearing him from the interior of the South-American Continent

towards the coast. His experiences of this strange land had been

sad. The severe illness from which he had suffered shortly after

his arrival had never wholly left him, and he had by degrees almost

decided to relinquish his hope of farming here, though, as long as

the bare possibility existed of his remaining, he kept this change

of view a secret from his parents.

The crowds of agricultural labourers who had come out to the country

in his wake, dazzled by representations of easy independence, had

suffered, died, and wasted away. He would see mothers from English

farms trudging along with their infants in their arms, when the child

would be stricken with fever and would die; the mother would pause

to dig a hole in the loose earth with her bare hands, would bury the

babe therein with the same natural grave-tools, shed one tear, and

again trudge on.

Angel's original intention had not been emigration to Brazil but a

northern or eastern farm in his own country. He had come to this

place in a fit of desperation, the Brazil movement among the English

agriculturists having by chance coincided with his desire to escape

from his past existence.

During this time of absence he had mentally aged a dozen years.

What arrested him now as of value in life was less its beauty than

its pathos. Having long discredited the old systems of mysticism,

he now began to discredit the old appraisements of morality. He

thought they wanted readjusting. Who was the moral man? Still more

pertinently, who was the moral woman? The beauty or ugliness of

a character lay not only in its achievements, but in its aims and

impulses; its true history lay, not among things done, but among

things willed.

How, then, about Tess?

Viewing her in these lights, a regret for his hasty judgement began

to oppress him. Did he reject her eternally, or did he not? He

could no longer say that he would always reject her, and not to say

that was in spirit to accept her now.

This growing fondness for her memory coincided in point of time

with her residence at Flintcomb-Ash, but it was before she had felt

herself at liberty to trouble him with a word about her circumstances

or her feelings. He was greatly perplexed; and in his perplexity as

to her motives in withholding intelligence, he did not inquire. Thus

her silence of docility was misinterpreted. How much it really said

if he had understood!--that she adhered with literal exactness to

orders which he had given and forgotten; that despite her natural

fearlessness she asserted no rights, admitted his judgement to be in

every respect the true one, and bent her head dumbly thereto.

In the before-mentioned journey by mules through the interior of the

country, another man rode beside him. Angel's companion was also an

Englishman, bent on the same errand, though he came from another part

of the island. They were both in a state of mental depression, and

they spoke of home affairs. Confidence begat confidence. With that

curious tendency evinced by men, more especially when in distant

lands, to entrust to strangers details of their lives which they

would on no account mention to friends, Angel admitted to this man

as they rode along the sorrowful facts of his marriage.

The stranger had sojourned in many more lands and among many more

peoples than Angel; to his cosmopolitan mind such deviations from the

social norm, so immense to domesticity, were no more than are the

irregularities of vale and mountain-chain to the whole terrestrial

curve. He viewed the matter in quite a different light from Angel;

thought that what Tess had been was of no importance beside what she

would be, and plainly told Clare that he was wrong in coming away

from her.

The next day they were drenched in a thunder-storm. Angel's companion

was struck down with fever, and died by the week's end. Clare waited

a few hours to bury him, and then went on his way.

The cursory remarks of the large-minded stranger, of whom he knew

absolutely nothing beyond a commonplace name, were sublimed by his

death, and influenced Clare more than all the reasoned ethics of the

philosophers. His own parochialism made him ashamed by its contrast.

His inconsistencies rushed upon him in a flood. He had persistently

elevated Hellenic Paganism at the expense of Christianity; yet in

that civilization an illegal surrender was not certain disesteem.

Surely then he might have regarded that abhorrence of the un-intact

state, which he had inherited with the creed of mysticism, as at

least open to correction when the result was due to treachery. A

remorse struck into him. The words of Izz Huett, never quite stilled

in his memory, came back to him. He had asked Izz if she loved him,

and she had replied in the affirmative. Did she love him more than

Tess did? No, she had replied; Tess would lay down her life for him,

and she herself could do no more.

He thought of Tess as she had appeared on the day of the wedding.

How her eyes had lingered upon him; how she had hung upon his words

as if they were a god's! And during the terrible evening over the

hearth, when her simple soul uncovered itself to his, how pitiful her

face had looked by the rays of the fire, in her inability to realize

that his love and protection could possibly be withdrawn.

Thus from being her critic he grew to be her advocate. Cynical

things he had uttered to himself about her; but no man can be always

a cynic and live; and he withdrew them. The mistake of expressing

them had arisen from his allowing himself to be influenced by general

principles to the disregard of the particular instance.

But the reasoning is somewhat musty; lovers and husbands have gone

over the ground before to-day. Clare had been harsh towards her;

there is no doubt of it. Men are too often harsh with women they

love or have loved; women with men. And yet these harshnesses are

tenderness itself when compared with the universal harshness out

of which they grow; the harshness of the position towards the

temperament, of the means towards the aims, of to-day towards

yesterday, of hereafter towards to-day.

The historic interest of her family--that masterful line of

d'Urbervilles--whom he had despised as a spent force, touched his

sentiments now. Why had he not known the difference between the

political value and the imaginative value of these things? In

the latter aspect her d'Urberville descent was a fact of great

dimensions; worthless to economics, it was a most useful ingredient

to the dreamer, to the moralizer on declines and falls. It was a

fact that would soon be forgotten--that bit of distinction in poor

Tess's blood and name, and oblivion would fall upon her hereditary

link with the marble monuments and leaded skeletons at Kingsbere. So

does Time ruthlessly destroy his own romances. In recalling her face

again and again, he thought now that he could see therein a flash of

the dignity which must have graced her grand-dames; and the vision

sent that _aura_ through his veins which he had formerly felt, and

which left behind it a sense of sickness.

Despite her not-inviolate past, what still abode in such a woman as

Tess outvalued the freshness of her fellows. Was not the gleaning

of the grapes of Ephraim better than the vintage of Abiezer?

So spoke love renascent, preparing the way for Tess's devoted

outpouring, which was then just being forwarded to him by his father;

though owing to his distance inland it was to be a long time in

reaching him.

Meanwhile the writer's expectation that Angel would come in response

to the entreaty was alternately great and small. What lessened it

was that the facts of her life which had led to the parting had

not changed--could never change; and that, if her presence had not

attenuated them, her absence could not. Nevertheless she addressed

her mind to the tender question of what she could do to please him

best if he should arrive. Sighs were expended on the wish that she

had taken more notice of the tunes he played on his harp, that she

had inquired more curiously of him which were his favourite ballads

among those the country-girls sang. She indirectly inquired of Amby

Seedling, who had followed Izz from Talbothays, and by chance Amby

remembered that, amongst the snatches of melody in which they had

indulged at the dairyman's, to induce the cows to let down their

milk, Clare had seemed to like "Cupid's Gardens", "I have parks, I

have hounds", and "The break o' the day"; and had seemed not to care

for "The Tailor's Breeches" and "Such a beauty I did grow", excellent

ditties as they were.

To perfect the ballads was now her whimsical desire. She practised

them privately at odd moments, especially "The break o' the day":

Arise, arise, arise!

And pick your love a posy,

All o' the sweetest flowers

That in the garden grow.

The turtle doves and sma' birds

In every bough a-building,

So early in the May-time

At the break o' the day!

It would have melted the heart of a stone to hear her singing these

ditties whenever she worked apart from the rest of the girls in this

cold dry time; the tears running down her cheeks all the while at the

thought that perhaps he would not, after all, come to hear her, and

the simple silly words of the songs resounding in painful mockery of

the aching heart of the singer.

Tess was so wrapt up in this fanciful dream that she seemed not to

know how the season was advancing; that the days had lengthened, that

Lady-Day was at hand, and would soon be followed by Old Lady-Day, the

end of her term here.

But before the quarter-day had quite come, something happened which

made Tess think of far different matters. She was at her lodging as

usual one evening, sitting in the downstairs room with the rest of

the family, when somebody knocked at the door and inquired for Tess.

Through the doorway she saw against the declining light a figure

with the height of a woman and the breadth of a child, a tall, thin,

girlish creature whom she did not recognize in the twilight till the

girl said "Tess!"

"What--is it 'Liza-Lu?" asked Tess, in startled accents. Her sister,

whom a little over a year ago she had left at home as a child, had

sprung up by a sudden shoot to a form of this presentation, of which

as yet Lu seemed herself scarce able to understand the meaning.

Her thin legs, visible below her once-long frock, now short by her

growing, and her uncomfortable hands and arms revealed her youth and

inexperience.

"Yes, I have been traipsing about all day, Tess," said Lu, with

unemotional gravity, "a-trying to find 'ee; and I'm very tired."

"What is the matter at home?"

"Mother is took very bad, and the doctor says she's dying, and as

father is not very well neither, and says 'tis wrong for a man of

such a high family as his to slave and drave at common labouring

work, we don't know what to do."

Tess stood in reverie a long time before she thought of asking

'Liza-Lu to come in and sit down. When she had done so, and 'Liza-Lu

was having some tea, she came to a decision. It was imperative that

she should go home. Her agreement did not end till Old Lady-Day, the

sixth of April, but as the interval thereto was not a long one she

resolved to run the risk of starting at once.

To go that night would be a gain of twelve-hours; but her sister

was too tired to undertake such a distance till the morrow. Tess

ran down to where Marian and Izz lived, informed them of what had

happened, and begged them to make the best of her case to the farmer.

Returning, she got Lu a supper, and after that, having tucked the

younger into her own bed, packed up as many of her belongings as

would go into a withy basket, and started, directing Lu to follow

her next morning.

L

She plunged into the chilly equinoctial darkness as the clock struck

ten, for her fifteen miles' walk under the steely stars. In lonely

districts night is a protection rather than a danger to a noiseless

pedestrian, and knowing this, Tess pursued the nearest course along

by-lanes that she would almost have feared in the day-time; but

marauders were wanting now, and spectral fears were driven out of

her mind by thoughts of her mother. Thus she proceeded mile after

mile, ascending and descending till she came to Bulbarrow, and about

midnight looked from that height into the abyss of chaotic shade

which was all that revealed itself of the vale on whose further side

she was born. Having already traversed about five miles on the

upland, she had now some ten or eleven in the lowland before her

journey would be finished. The winding road downwards became just

visible to her under the wan starlight as she followed it, and

soon she paced a soil so contrasting with that above it that the

difference was perceptible to the tread and to the smell. It was the

heavy clay land of Blackmoor Vale, and a part of the Vale to which

turnpike-roads had never penetrated. Superstitions linger longest on

these heavy soils. Having once been forest, at this shadowy time it

seemed to assert something of its old character, the far and the near

being blended, and every tree and tall hedge making the most of its

presence. The harts that had been hunted here, the witches that had

been pricked and ducked, the green-spangled fairies that "whickered"

at you as you passed;--the place teemed with beliefs in them still,

and they formed an impish multitude now.

At Nuttlebury she passed the village inn, whose sign creaked in

response to the greeting of her footsteps, which not a human soul

heard but herself. Under the thatched roofs her mind's eye beheld

relaxed tendons and flaccid muscles, spread out in the darkness

beneath coverlets made of little purple patchwork squares, and

undergoing a bracing process at the hands of sleep for renewed labour

on the morrow, as soon as a hint of pink nebulosity appeared on

Hambledon Hill.

At three she turned the last corner of the maze of lanes she had

threaded, and entered Marlott, passing the field in which as a

club-girl she had first seen Angel Clare, when he had not danced

with her; the sense of disappointment remained with her yet. In the

direction of her mother's house she saw a light. It came from the

bedroom window, and a branch waved in front of it and made it wink at

her. As soon as she could discern the outline of the house--newly

thatched with her money--it had all its old effect upon Tess's

imagination. Part of her body and life it ever seemed to be; the

slope of its dormers, the finish of its gables, the broken courses of

brick which topped the chimney, all had something in common with her

personal character. A stupefaction had come into these features, to

her regard; it meant the illness of her mother.

She opened the door so softly as to disturb nobody; the lower room

was vacant, but the neighbour who was sitting up with her mother came

to the top of the stairs, and whispered that Mrs Durbeyfield was no

better, though she was sleeping just then. Tess prepared herself a

breakfast, and then took her place as nurse in her mother's chamber.

In the morning, when she contemplated the children, they had all a

curiously elongated look; although she had been away little more than

a year, their growth was astounding; and the necessity of applying

herself heart and soul to their needs took her out of her own cares.

Her father's ill-health was the same indefinite kind, and he sat in

his chair as usual. But the day after her arrival he was unusually

bright. He had a rational scheme for living, and Tess asked him what

it was.

"I'm thinking of sending round to all the old antiqueerians in this

part of England," he said, "asking them to subscribe to a fund to

maintain me. I'm sure they'd see it as a romantical, artistical,

and proper thing to do. They spend lots o' money in keeping up old

ruins, and finding the bones o' things, and such like; and living

remains must be more interesting to 'em still, if they only knowed

of me. Would that somebody would go round and tell 'em what there

is living among 'em, and they thinking nothing of him! If Pa'son

Tringham, who discovered me, had lived, he'd ha' done it, I'm sure."

Tess postponed her arguments on this high project till she had

grappled with pressing matters in hand, which seemed little improved

by her remittances. When indoor necessities had been eased, she

turned her attention to external things. It was now the season for

planting and sowing; many gardens and allotments of the villagers

had already received their spring tillage; but the garden and the

allotment of the Durbeyfields were behindhand. She found, to her

dismay, that this was owing to their having eaten all the seed

potatoes,--that last lapse of the improvident. At the earliest

moment she obtained what others she could procure, and in a few

days her father was well enough to see to the garden, under Tess's

persuasive efforts: while she herself undertook the allotment-plot

which they rented in a field a couple of hundred yards out of the

village.

She liked doing it after the confinement of the sick chamber, where

she was not now required by reason of her mother's improvement.

Violent motion relieved thought. The plot of ground was in a high,

dry, open enclosure, where there were forty or fifty such pieces,

and where labour was at its briskest when the hired labour of the

day had ended. Digging began usually at six o'clock and extended

indefinitely into the dusk or moonlight. Just now heaps of dead

weeds and refuse were burning on many of the plots, the dry weather

favouring their combustion.

One fine day Tess and 'Liza-Lu worked on here with their neighbours

till the last rays of the sun smote flat upon the white pegs that

divided the plots. As soon as twilight succeeded to sunset the flare

of the couch-grass and cabbage-stalk fires began to light up the

allotments fitfully, their outlines appearing and disappearing under

the dense smoke as wafted by the wind. When a fire glowed, banks

of smoke, blown level along the ground, would themselves become

illuminated to an opaque lustre, screening the workpeople from one

another; and the meaning of the "pillar of a cloud", which was a wall

by day and a light by night, could be understood.

As evening thickened, some of the gardening men and women gave over

for the night, but the greater number remained to get their planting

done, Tess being among them, though she sent her sister home. It was

on one of the couch-burning plots that she laboured with her fork,

its four shining prongs resounding against the stones and dry clods

in little clicks. Sometimes she was completely involved in the smoke

of her fire; then it would leave her figure free, irradiated by the

brassy glare from the heap. She was oddly dressed to-night, and

presented a somewhat staring aspect, her attire being a gown bleached

by many washings, with a short black jacket over it, the effect of

the whole being that of a wedding and funeral guest in one. The

women further back wore white aprons, which, with their pale faces,

were all that could be seen of them in the gloom, except when at

moments they caught a flash from the flames.

Westward, the wiry boughs of the bare thorn hedge which formed the

boundary of the field rose against the pale opalescence of the lower

sky. Above, Jupiter hung like a full-blown jonquil, so bright

as almost to throw a shade. A few small nondescript stars were

appearing elsewhere. In the distance a dog barked, and wheels

occasionally rattled along the dry road.

Still the prongs continued to click assiduously, for it was not late;

and though the air was fresh and keen there was a whisper of spring

in it that cheered the workers on. Something in the place, the

hours, the crackling fires, the fantastic mysteries of light and

shade, made others as well as Tess enjoy being there. Nightfall,

which in the frost of winter comes as a fiend and in the warmth of

summer as a lover, came as a tranquillizer on this March day.

Nobody looked at his or her companions. The eyes of all were on the

soil as its turned surface was revealed by the fires. Hence as Tess

stirred the clods and sang her foolish little songs with scarce

now a hope that Clare would ever hear them, she did not for a long

time notice the person who worked nearest to her--a man in a long

smockfrock who, she found, was forking the same plot as herself, and

whom she supposed her father had sent there to advance the work.

She became more conscious of him when the direction of his digging

brought him closer. Sometimes the smoke divided them; then it

swerved, and the two were visible to each other but divided from all

the rest.

Tess did not speak to her fellow-worker, nor did he speak to her.

Nor did she think of him further than to recollect that he had not

been there when it was broad daylight, and that she did not know

him as any one of the Marlott labourers, which was no wonder, her

absences having been so long and frequent of late years. By-and-by

he dug so close to her that the fire-beams were reflected as

distinctly from the steel prongs of his fork as from her own. On

going up to the fire to throw a pitch of dead weeds upon it, she

found that he did the same on the other side. The fire flared up,

and she beheld the face of d'Urberville.

The unexpectedness of his presence, the grotesqueness of his

appearance in a gathered smockfrock, such as was now worn only by the

most old-fashioned of the labourers, had a ghastly comicality that

chilled her as to its bearing. D'Urberville emitted a low, long

laugh.

"If I were inclined to joke, I should say, How much this seems like

Paradise!" he remarked whimsically, looking at her with an inclined

head.

"What do you say?" she weakly asked.

"A jester might say this is just like Paradise. You are Eve, and I

am the old Other One come to tempt you in the disguise of an inferior

animal. I used to be quite up in that scene of Milton's when I was

theological. Some of it goes--

"'Empress, the way is ready, and not long,

Beyond a row of myrtles...

... If thou accept

My conduct, I can bring thee thither soon.'

'Lead then,' said Eve.

"And so on. My dear Tess, I am only putting this to you as a thing

that you might have supposed or said quite untruly, because you think

so badly of me."

"I never said you were Satan, or thought it. I don't think of you in

that way at all. My thoughts of you are quite cold, except when you

affront me. What, did you come digging here entirely because of me?"

"Entirely. To see you; nothing more. The smockfrock, which I

saw hanging for sale as I came along, was an afterthought, that I

mightn't be noticed. I come to protest against your working like

this."

"But I like doing it--it is for my father."

"Your engagement at the other place is ended?"

"Yes."

"Where are you going to next? To join your dear husband?"

She could not bear the humiliating reminder.

"O--I don't know!" she said bitterly. "I have no husband!"

"It is quite true--in the sense you mean. But you have a friend, and

I have determined that you shall be comfortable in spite of yourself.

When you get down to your house you will see what I have sent there

for you."

"O, Alec, I wish you wouldn't give me anything at all! I cannot take

it from you! I don't like--it is not right!"

"It IS right!" he cried lightly. "I am not going to see a woman whom

I feel so tenderly for as I do for you in trouble without trying to

help her."

"But I am very well off! I am only in trouble about--about--not

about living at all!"

She turned, and desperately resumed her digging, tears dripping upon

the fork-handle and upon the clods.

"About the children--your brothers and sisters," he resumed. "I've

been thinking of them."

Tess's heart quivered--he was touching her in a weak place. He had

divined her chief anxiety. Since returning home her soul had gone

out to those children with an affection that was passionate.

"If your mother does not recover, somebody ought to do something for

them; since your father will not be able to do much, I suppose?"

"He can with my assistance. He must!"

"And with mine."

"No, sir!"

"How damned foolish this is!" burst out d'Urberville. "Why, he

thinks we are the same family; and will be quite satisfied!"

"He don't. I've undeceived him."

"The more fool you!"

D'Urberville in anger retreated from her to the hedge, where he

pulled off the long smockfrock which had disguised him; and rolling

it up and pushing it into the couch-fire, went away.

Tess could not get on with her digging after this; she felt restless;

she wondered if he had gone back to her father's house; and taking

the fork in her hand proceeded homewards.

Some twenty yards from the house she was met by one of her sisters.

"O, Tessy--what do you think! 'Liza-Lu is a-crying, and there's a

lot of folk in the house, and mother is a good deal better, but they

think father is dead!"

The child realized the grandeur of the news; but not as yet its

sadness, and stood looking at Tess with round-eyed importance till,

beholding the effect produced upon her, she said--

"What, Tess, shan't we talk to father never no more?"

"But father was only a little bit ill!" exclaimed Tess distractedly.

'Liza-Lu came up.

"He dropped down just now, and the doctor who was there for mother

said there was no chance for him, because his heart was growed in."

Yes; the Durbeyfield couple had changed places; the dying one was

out of danger, and the indisposed one was dead. The news meant even

more than it sounded. Her father's life had a value apart from his

personal achievements, or perhaps it would not have had much. It

was the last of the three lives for whose duration the house and

premises were held under a lease; and it had long been coveted by the

tenant-farmer for his regular labourers, who were stinted in cottage

accommodation. Moreover, "liviers" were disapproved of in villages

almost as much as little freeholders, because of their independence

of manner, and when a lease determined it was never renewed.

Thus the Durbeyfields, once d'Urbervilles, saw descending upon them

the destiny which, no doubt, when they were among the Olympians of

the county, they had caused to descend many a time, and severely

enough, upon the heads of such landless ones as they themselves were

now. So do flux and reflux--the rhythm of change--alternate and

persist in everything under the sky.

LI

At length it was the eve of Old Lady-Day, and the agricultural world

was in a fever of mobility such as only occurs at that particular

date of the year. It is a day of fulfilment; agreements for outdoor

service during the ensuing year, entered into at Candlemas, are to

be now carried out. The labourers--or "work-folk", as they used to

call themselves immemorially till the other word was introduced from

without--who wish to remain no longer in old places are removing to

the new farms.

These annual migrations from farm to farm were on the increase here.

When Tess's mother was a child the majority of the field-folk about

Marlott had remained all their lives on one farm, which had been the

home also of their fathers and grandfathers; but latterly the desire

for yearly removal had risen to a high pitch. With the younger

families it was a pleasant excitement which might possibly be an

advantage. The Egypt of one family was the Land of Promise to the

family who saw it from a distance, till by residence there it became

it turn their Egypt also; and so they changed and changed.

However, all the mutations so increasingly discernible in village

life did not originate entirely in the agricultural unrest. A

depopulation was also going on. The village had formerly contained,

side by side with the argicultural labourers, an interesting and

better-informed class, ranking distinctly above the former--the class

to which Tess's father and mother had belonged--and including the

carpenter, the smith, the shoemaker, the huckster, together with

nondescript workers other than farm-labourers; a set of people

who owed a certain stability of aim and conduct to the fact of

their being lifeholders like Tess's father, or copyholders, or

occasionally, small freeholders. But as the long holdings fell

in, they were seldom again let to similar tenants, and were mostly

pulled down, if not absolutely required by the farmer for his hands.

Cottagers who were not directly employed on the land were looked

upon with disfavour, and the banishment of some starved the trade of

others, who were thus obliged to follow. These families, who had

formed the backbone of the village life in the past, who were the

depositaries of the village traditions, had to seek refuge in the

large centres; the process, humorously designated by statisticians as

"the tendency of the rural population towards the large towns", being

really the tendency of water to flow uphill when forced by machinery.

The cottage accommodation at Marlott having been in this manner

considerably curtailed by demolitions, every house which remained

standing was required by the agriculturist for his work-people. Ever

since the occurrence of the event which had cast such a shadow over

Tess's life, the Durbeyfield family (whose descent was not credited)

had been tacitly looked on as one which would have to go when their

lease ended, if only in the interests of morality. It was, indeed,

quite true that the household had not been shining examples either of

temperance, soberness, or chastity. The father, and even the mother,

had got drunk at times, the younger children seldom had gone to

church, and the eldest daughter had made queer unions. By some means

the village had to be kept pure. So on this, the first Lady-Day

on which the Durbeyfields were expellable, the house, being roomy,

was required for a carter with a large family; and Widow Joan,

her daughters Tess and 'Liza-Lu, the boy Abraham, and the younger

children had to go elsewhere.

On the evening preceding their removal it was getting dark betimes by

reason of a drizzling rain which blurred the sky. As it was the last

night they would spend in the village which had been their home and

birthplace, Mrs Durbeyfield, 'Liza-Lu, and Abraham had gone out to

bid some friends goodbye, and Tess was keeping house till they should

return.

She was kneeling in the window-bench, her face close to the casement,

where an outer pane of rain-water was sliding down the inner pane of

glass. Her eyes rested on the web of a spider, probably starved long

ago, which had been mistakenly placed in a corner where no flies

ever came, and shivered in the slight draught through the casement.

Tess was reflecting on the position of the household, in which she

perceived her own evil influence. Had she not come home, her mother

and the children might probably have been allowed to stay on as

weekly tenants. But she had been observed almost immediately on her

return by some people of scrupulous character and great influence:

they had seen her idling in the churchyard, restoring as well as she

could with a little trowel a baby's obliterated grave. By this means

they had found that she was living here again; her mother was scolded

for "harbouring" her; sharp retorts had ensued from Joan, who had

independently offered to leave at once; she had been taken at her

word; and here was the result.

"I ought never to have come home," said Tess to herself, bitterly.

She was so intent upon these thoughts that she hardly at first took

note of a man in a white mackintosh whom she saw riding down the

street. Possibly it was owing to her face being near to the pane

that he saw her so quickly, and directed his horse so close to the

cottage-front that his hoofs were almost upon the narrow border for

plants growing under the wall. It was not till he touched the window

with his riding-crop that she observed him. The rain had nearly

ceased, and she opened the casement in obedience to his gesture.

"Didn't you see me?" asked d'Urberville.

"I was not attending," she said. "I heard you, I believe, though I

fancied it was a carriage and horses. I was in a sort of dream."

"Ah! you heard the d'Urberville Coach, perhaps. You know the legend,

I suppose?"

"No. My--somebody was going to tell it me once, but didn't."

"If you are a genuine d'Urberville I ought not to tell you either,

I suppose. As for me, I'm a sham one, so it doesn't matter. It is

rather dismal. It is that this sound of a non-existent coach can

only be heard by one of d'Urberville blood, and it is held to be

of ill-omen to the one who hears it. It has to do with a murder,

committed by one of the family, centuries ago."

"Now you have begun it, finish it."

"Very well. One of the family is said to have abducted some

beautiful woman, who tried to escape from the coach in which he was

carrying her off, and in the struggle he killed her--or she killed

him--I forget which. Such is one version of the tale... I see that

your tubs and buckets are packed. Going away, aren't you?"

"Yes, to-morrow--Old Lady Day."

"I heard you were, but could hardly believe it; it seems so sudden.

Why is it?"

"Father's was the last life on the property, and when that dropped we

had no further right to stay. Though we might, perhaps, have stayed

as weekly tenants--if it had not been for me."

"What about you?"

"I am not a--proper woman."

D'Urberville's face flushed.

"What a blasted shame! Miserable snobs! May their dirty souls

be burnt to cinders!" he exclaimed in tones of ironic resentment.

"That's why you are going, is it? Turned out?"

"We are not turned out exactly; but as they said we should have to go

soon, it was best to go now everybody was moving, because there are

better chances."

"Where are you going to?"

"Kingsbere. We have taken rooms there. Mother is so foolish about

father's people that she will go there."

"But your mother's family are not fit for lodgings, and in a little

hole of a town like that. Now why not come to my garden-house at

Trantridge? There are hardly any poultry now, since my mother's

death; but there's the house, as you know it, and the garden. It

can be whitewashed in a day, and your mother can live there quite

comfortably; and I will put the children to a good school. Really

I ought to do something for you!"

"But we have already taken the rooms at Kingsbere!" she declared.

"And we can wait there--"

"Wait--what for? For that nice husband, no doubt. Now look here,

Tess, I know what men are, and, bearing in mind the _grounds_ of

your separation, I am quite positive he will never make it up with

you. Now, though I have been your enemy, I am your friend, even

if you won't believe it. Come to this cottage of mine. We'll get

up a regular colony of fowls, and your mother can attend to them

excellently; and the children can go to school."

Tess breathed more and more quickly, and at length she said--

"How do I know that you would do all this? Your views may

change--and then--we should be--my mother would be--homeless

again."

"O no--no. I would guarantee you against such as that in writing, if

necessary. Think it over."

Tess shook her head. But d'Urberville persisted; she had seldom seen

him so determined; he would not take a negative.

"Please just tell your mother," he said, in emphatic tones. "It is

her business to judge--not yours. I shall get the house swept out

and whitened to-morrow morning, and fires lit; and it will be dry by

the evening, so that you can come straight there. Now mind, I shall

expect you."

Tess again shook her head, her throat swelling with complicated

emotion. She could not look up at d'Urberville.

"I owe you something for the past, you know," he resumed. "And you

cured me, too, of that craze; so I am glad--"

"I would rather you had kept the craze, so that you had kept the

practice which went with it!"

"I am glad of this opportunity of repaying you a little. To-morrow I

shall expect to hear your mother's goods unloading... Give me your

hand on it now--dear, beautiful Tess!"

With the last sentence he had dropped his voice to a murmur, and put

his hand in at the half-open casement. With stormy eyes she pulled

the stay-bar quickly, and, in doing so, caught his arm between the

casement and the stone mullion.

"Damnation--you are very cruel!" he said, snatching out his arm.

"No, no!--I know you didn't do it on purpose. Well I shall expect

you, or your mother and children at least."

"I shall not come--I have plenty of money!" she cried.

"Where?"

"At my father-in-law's, if I ask for it."

"IF you ask for it. But you won't, Tess; I know you; you'll never

ask for it--you'll starve first!"

With these words he rode off. Just at the corner of the street he

met the man with the paint-pot, who asked him if he had deserted the

brethren.

"You go to the devil!" said d'Urberville.

Tess remained where she was a long while, till a sudden rebellious

sense of injustice caused the region of her eyes to swell with the

rush of hot tears thither. Her husband, Angel Clare himself, had,

like others, dealt out hard measure to her; surely he had! She had

never before admitted such a thought; but he had surely! Never

in her life--she could swear it from the bottom of her soul--had

she ever intended to do wrong; yet these hard judgements had

come. Whatever her sins, they were not sins of intention, but of

inadvertence, and why should she have been punished so persistently?

She passionately seized the first piece of paper that came to hand,

and scribbled the following lines:

O why have you treated me so monstrously, Angel! I do

not deserve it. I have thought it all over carefully,

and I can never, never forgive you! You know that I

did not intend to wrong you--why have you so wronged

me? You are cruel, cruel indeed! I will try to forget

you. It is all injustice I have received at your

hands!

T.

She watched till the postman passed by, ran out to him with

her epistle, and then again took her listless place inside the

window-panes.

It was just as well to write like that as to write tenderly. How

could he give way to entreaty? The facts had not changed: there was

no new event to alter his opinion.

It grew darker, the fire-light shining over the room. The two

biggest of the younger children had gone out with their mother; the

four smallest, their ages ranging from three-and-a-half years to

eleven, all in black frocks, were gathered round the hearth babbling

their own little subjects. Tess at length joined them, without

lighting a candle.

"This is the last night that we shall sleep here, dears, in the house

where we were born," she said quickly. "We ought to think of it,

oughtn't we?"

They all became silent; with the impressibility of their age they

were ready to burst into tears at the picture of finality she had

conjured up, though all the day hitherto they had been rejoicing in

the idea of a new place. Tess changed the subject.

"Sing to me, dears," she said.

"What shall we sing?"

"Anything you know; I don't mind."

There was a momentary pause; it was broken, first, in one little

tentative note; then a second voice strengthened it, and a third

and a fourth chimed in unison, with words they had learnt at the

Sunday-school--

Here we suffer grief and pain,

Here we meet to part again;

In Heaven we part no more.

The four sang on with the phlegmatic passivity of persons who had

long ago settled the question, and there being no mistake about it,

felt that further thought was not required. With features strained

hard to enunciate the syllables they continued to regard the centre

of the flickering fire, the notes of the youngest straying over into

the pauses of the rest.

Tess turned from them, and went to the window again. Darkness had

now fallen without, but she put her face to the pane as though to

peer into the gloom. It was really to hide her tears. If she could

only believe what the children were singing; if she were only sure,

how different all would now be; how confidently she would leave them

to Providence and their future kingdom! But, in default of that, it

behoved her to do something; to be their Providence; for to Tess,

as to not a few millions of others, there was ghastly satire in the

poet's lines--

Not in utter nakedness

But trailing clouds of glory do we come.

To her and her like, birth itself was an ordeal of degrading personal

compulsion, whose gratuitousness nothing in the result seemed to

justify, and at best could only palliate.

In the shades of the wet road she soon discerned her mother with tall

'Liza-Lu and Abraham. Mrs Durbeyfield's pattens clicked up to the

door, and Tess opened it.

"I see the tracks of a horse outside the window," said Joan. "Hev

somebody called?"

"No," said Tess.

The children by the fire looked gravely at her, and one murmured--

"Why, Tess, the gentleman a-horseback!"

"He didn't call," said Tess. "He spoke to me in passing."

"Who was the gentleman?" asked the mother. "Your husband?"

"No. He'll never, never come," answered Tess in stony hopelessness.

"Then who was it?"

"Oh, you needn't ask. You've seen him before, and so have I."

"Ah! What did he say?" said Joan curiously.

"I will tell you when we are settled in our lodging at Kingsbere

to-morrow--every word."

It was not her husband, she had said. Yet a consciousness that in a

physical sense this man alone was her husband seemed to weigh on her

more and more.

LII

During the small hours of the next morning, while it was still dark,

dwellers near the highways were conscious of a disturbance of their

night's rest by rumbling noises, intermittently continuing till

daylight--noises as certain to recur in this particular first week of

the month as the voice of the cuckoo in the third week of the same.

They were the preliminaries of the general removal, the passing of

the empty waggons and teams to fetch the goods of the migrating

families; for it was always by the vehicle of the farmer who required

his services that the hired man was conveyed to his destination.

That this might be accomplished within the day was the explanation

of the reverberation occurring so soon after midnight, the aim of

the carters being to reach the door of the outgoing households by

six o'clock, when the loading of their movables at once began.

But to Tess and her mother's household no such anxious farmer sent

his team. They were only women; they were not regular labourers;

they were not particularly required anywhere; hence they had to hire

a waggon at their own expense, and got nothing sent gratuitously.

It was a relief to Tess, when she looked out of the window that

morning, to find that though the weather was windy and louring, it

did not rain, and that the waggon had come. A wet Lady-Day was a

spectre which removing families never forgot; damp furniture, damp

bedding, damp clothing accompanied it, and left a train of ills.

Her mother, 'Liza-Lu, and Abraham were also awake, but the younger

children were let sleep on. The four breakfasted by the thin light,

and the "house-ridding" was taken in hand.

It proceeded with some cheerfulness, a friendly neighbour or two

assisting. When the large articles of furniture had been packed in

position, a circular nest was made of the beds and bedding, in which

Joan Durbeyfield and the young children were to sit through the

journey. After loading there was a long delay before the horses were

brought, these having been unharnessed during the ridding; but at

length, about two o'clock, the whole was under way, the cooking-pot

swinging from the axle of the waggon, Mrs Durbeyfield and family

at the top, the matron having in her lap, to prevent injury to its

works, the head of the clock, which, at any exceptional lurch of the

waggon, struck one, or one-and-a-half, in hurt tones. Tess and the

next eldest girl walked alongside till they were out of the village.

They had called on a few neighbours that morning and the previous

evening, and some came to see them off, all wishing them well,

though, in their secret hearts, hardly expecting welfare possible

to such a family, harmless as the Durbeyfields were to all except

themselves. Soon the equipage began to ascend to higher ground,

and the wind grew keener with the change of level and soil.

The day being the sixth of April, the Durbeyfield waggon met many

other waggons with families on the summit of the load, which was

built on a wellnigh unvarying principle, as peculiar, probably, to

the rural labourer as the hexagon to the bee. The groundwork of the

arrangement was the family dresser, which, with its shining handles,

and finger-marks, and domestic evidences thick upon it, stood

importantly in front, over the tails of the shaft-horses, in its

erect and natural position, like some Ark of the Covenant that they

were bound to carry reverently.

Some of the households were lively, some mournful; some were stopping

at the doors of wayside inns; where, in due time, the Durbeyfield

menagerie also drew up to bait horses and refresh the travellers.

During the halt Tess's eyes fell upon a three-pint blue mug, which

was ascending and descending through the air to and from the feminine

section of a household, sitting on the summit of a load that had also

drawn up at a little distance from the same inn. She followed one of

the mug's journeys upward, and perceived it to be clasped by hands

whose owner she well knew. Tess went towards the waggon.

"Marian and Izz!" she cried to the girls, for it was they, sitting

with the moving family at whose house they had lodged. "Are you

house-ridding to-day, like everybody else?"

They were, they said. It had been too rough a life for them at

Flintcomb-Ash, and they had come away, almost without notice,

leaving Groby to prosecute them if he chose. They told Tess their

destination, and Tess told them hers.

Marian leant over the load, and lowered her voice. "Do you know that

the gentleman who follows 'ee--you'll guess who I mean--came to ask

for 'ee at Flintcomb after you had gone? We didn't tell'n where you

was, knowing you wouldn't wish to see him."

"Ah--but I did see him!" Tess murmured. "He found me."

"And do he know where you be going?"

"I think so."

"Husband come back?"

"No."

She bade her acquaintance goodbye--for the respective carters had now

come out from the inn--and the two waggons resumed their journey in

opposite directions; the vehicle whereon sat Marian, Izz, and the

ploughman's family with whom they had thrown in their lot, being

brightly painted, and drawn by three powerful horses with shining

brass ornaments on their harness; while the waggon on which Mrs

Durbeyfield and her family rode was a creaking erection that would

scarcely bear the weight of the superincumbent load; one which had

known no paint since it was made, and drawn by two horses only.

The contrast well marked the difference between being fetched by a

thriving farmer and conveying oneself whither no hirer waited one's

coming.

The distance was great--too great for a day's journey--and it was

with the utmost difficulty that the horses performed it. Though they

had started so early, it was quite late in the afternoon when they

turned the flank of an eminence which formed part of the upland

called Greenhill. While the horses stood to stale and breathe

themselves Tess looked around. Under the hill, and just ahead of

them, was the half-dead townlet of their pilgrimage, Kingsbere,

where lay those ancestors of whom her father had spoken and sung to

painfulness: Kingsbere, the spot of all spots in the world which

could be considered the d'Urbervilles' home, since they had resided

there for full five hundred years.

A man could be seen advancing from the outskirts towards them, and

when he beheld the nature of their waggon-load he quickened his

steps.

"You be the woman they call Mrs Durbeyfield, I reckon?" he said to

Tess's mother, who had descended to walk the remainder of the way.

She nodded. "Though widow of the late Sir John d'Urberville, poor

nobleman, if I cared for my rights; and returning to the domain of

his forefathers."

"Oh? Well, I know nothing about that; but if you be Mrs Durbeyfield,

I am sent to tell 'ee that the rooms you wanted be let. We didn't

know that you was coming till we got your letter this morning--when

'twas too late. But no doubt you can get other lodgings somewhere."

The man had noticed the face of Tess, which had become ash-pale at

his intelligence. Her mother looked hopelessly at fault. "What

shall we do now, Tess?" she said bitterly. "Here's a welcome to

your ancestors' lands! However, let's try further."

They moved on into the town, and tried with all their might, Tess

remaining with the waggon to take care of the children whilst her

mother and 'Liza-Lu made inquiries. At the last return of Joan to

the vehicle, an hour later, when her search for accommodation had

still been fruitless, the driver of the waggon said the goods must be

unloaded, as the horses were half-dead, and he was bound to return

part of the way at least that night.

"Very well--unload it here," said Joan recklessly. "I'll get shelter

somewhere."

The waggon had drawn up under the churchyard wall, in a spot screened

from view, and the driver, nothing loth, soon hauled down the poor

heap of household goods. This done, she paid him, reducing herself

to almost her last shilling thereby, and he moved off and left them,

only too glad to get out of further dealings with such a family. It

was a dry night, and he guessed that they would come to no harm.

Tess gazed desperately at the pile of furniture. The cold sunlight

of this spring evening peered invidiously upon the crocks and

kettles, upon the bunches of dried herbs shivering in the breeze,

upon the brass handles of the dresser, upon the wicker-cradle they

had all been rocked in, and upon the well-rubbed clock-case, all of

which gave out the reproachful gleam of indoor articles abandoned to

the vicissitudes of a roofless exposure for which they were never

made. Round about were deparked hills and slopes--now cut up

into little paddocks--and the green foundations that showed where

the d'Urberville mansion once had stood; also an outlying stretch

of Egdon Heath that had always belonged to the estate. Hard by,

the aisle of the church called the d'Urberville Aisle looked on

imperturbably.

"Isn't your family vault your own freehold?" said Tess's mother, as

she returned from a reconnoitre of the church and graveyard. "Why,

of course 'tis, and that's where we will camp, girls, till the place

of your ancestors finds us a roof! Now, Tess and 'Liza and Abraham,

you help me. We'll make a nest for these children, and then we'll

have another look round."

Tess listlessly lent a hand, and in a quarter of an hour the old

four-post bedstead was dissociated from the heap of goods, and

erected under the south wall of the church, the part of the building

known as the d'Urberville Aisle, beneath which the huge vaults lay.

Over the tester of the bedstead was a beautiful traceried window, of

many lights, its date being the fifteenth century. It was called

the d'Urberville Window, and in the upper part could be discerned

heraldic emblems like those on Durbeyfield's old seal and spoon.

Joan drew the curtains round the bed so as to make an excellent tent

of it, and put the smaller children inside. "If it comes to the

worst we can sleep there too, for one night," she said. "But let us

try further on, and get something for the dears to eat! O, Tess,

what's the use of your playing at marrying gentlemen, if it leaves

us like this!"

Accompanied by 'Liza-Lu and the boy, she again ascended the little

lane which secluded the church from the townlet. As soon as they got

into the street they beheld a man on horseback gazing up and down.

"Ah--I'm looking for you!" he said, riding up to them. "This is

indeed a family gathering on the historic spot!"

It was Alec d'Urberville. "Where is Tess?" he asked.

Personally Joan had no liking for Alec. She cursorily signified the

direction of the church, and went on, d'Urberville saying that he

would see them again, in case they should be still unsuccessful in

their search for shelter, of which he had just heard. When they had

gone, d'Urberville rode to the inn, and shortly after came out on

foot.

In the interim Tess, left with the children inside the bedstead,

remained talking with them awhile, till, seeing that no more could

be done to make them comfortable just then, she walked about the

churchyard, now beginning to be embrowned by the shades of nightfall.

The door of the church was unfastened, and she entered it for the

first time in her life.

Within the window under which the bedstead stood were the tombs of

the family, covering in their dates several centuries. They were

canopied, altar-shaped, and plain; their carvings being defaced

and broken; their brasses torn from the matrices, the rivet-holes

remaining like martin-holes in a sandcliff. Of all the reminders

that she had ever received that her people were socially extinct,

there was none so forcible as this spoliation.

She drew near to a dark stone on which was inscribed:

OSTIUM SEPULCHRI ANTIQUAE FAMILIAE D'URBERVILLE

Tess did not read Church-Latin like a Cardinal, but she knew that

this was the door of her ancestral sepulchre, and that the tall

knights of whom her father had chanted in his cups lay inside.

She musingly turned to withdraw, passing near an altar-tomb, the

oldest of them all, on which was a recumbent figure. In the dusk she

had not noticed it before, and would hardly have noticed it now but

for an odd fancy that the effigy moved. As soon as she drew close

to it she discovered all in a moment that the figure was a living

person; and the shock to her sense of not having been alone was so

violent that she was quite overcome, and sank down nigh to fainting,

not, however, till she had recognized Alec d'Urberville in the form.

He leapt off the slab and supported her.

"I saw you come in," he said smiling, "and got up there not to

interrupt your meditations. A family gathering, is it not, with

these old fellows under us here? Listen."

He stamped with his heel heavily on the floor; whereupon there arose

a hollow echo from below.

"That shook them a bit, I'll warrant!" he continued. "And you

thought I was the mere stone reproduction of one of them. But no.

The old order changeth. The little finger of the sham d'Urberville

can do more for you than the whole dynasty of the real underneath...

Now command me. What shall I do?"

"Go away!" she murmured.

"I will--I'll look for your mother," said he blandly. But in passing

her he whispered: "Mind this; you'll be civil yet!"

When he was gone she bent down upon the entrance to the vaults, and

said--

"Why am I on the wrong side of this door!"

In the meantime Marian and Izz Huett had journeyed onward with the

chattels of the ploughman in the direction of their land of Canaan--

the Egypt of some other family who had left it only that morning.

But the girls did not for a long time think of where they were going.

Their talk was of Angel Clare and Tess, and Tess's persistent lover,

whose connection with her previous history they had partly heard and

partly guessed ere this.

"'Tisn't as though she had never known him afore," said Marian. "His

having won her once makes all the difference in the world. 'Twould

be a thousand pities if he were to tole her away again. Mr Clare can

never be anything to us, Izz; and why should we grudge him to her,

and not try to mend this quarrel? If he could on'y know what straits

she's put to, and what's hovering round, he might come to take care

of his own."

"Could we let him know?"

They thought of this all the way to their destination; but the bustle

of re-establishment in their new place took up all their attention

then. But when they were settled, a month later, they heard of

Clare's approaching return, though they had learnt nothing more of

Tess. Upon that, agitated anew by their attachment to him, yet

honourably disposed to her, Marian uncorked the penny ink-bottle they

shared, and a few lines were concocted between the two girls.

HONOUR'D SIR--

Look to your Wife if you do love her as much as she do

love you. For she is sore put to by an Enemy in the shape

of a Friend. Sir, there is one near her who ought to be

Away. A woman should not be try'd beyond her Strength,

and continual dropping will wear away a Stone--ay,

more--a Diamond.

FROM TWO WELL-WISHERS

This was addressed to Angel Clare at the only place they had ever

heard him to be connected with, Emminster Vicarage; after which they

continued in a mood of emotional exaltation at their own generosity,

which made them sing in hysterical snatches and weep at the same

time.

END OF PHASE THE SIXTH

Phase the Seventh: Fulfilment

LIII

It was evening at Emminster Vicarage. The two customary candles were

burning under their green shades in the Vicar's study, but he had not

been sitting there. Occasionally he came in, stirred the small fire

which sufficed for the increasing mildness of the spring, and went

out again; sometimes pausing at the front door, going on to the

drawing-room, then returning again to the front door.

It faced westward, and though gloom prevailed inside, there was still

light enough without to see with distinctness. Mrs Clare, who had

been sitting in the drawing-room, followed him hither.

"Plenty of time yet," said the Vicar. "He doesn't reach Chalk-Newton

till six, even if the train should be punctual, and ten miles of

country-road, five of them in Crimmercrock Lane, are not jogged over

in a hurry by our old horse."

"But he has done it in an hour with us, my dear."

"Years ago."

Thus they passed the minutes, each well knowing that this was only

waste of breath, the one essential being simply to wait.

At length there was a slight noise in the lane, and the old

pony-chaise appeared indeed outside the railings. They saw alight

therefrom a form which they affected to recognize, but would actually

have passed by in the street without identifying had he not got out

of their carriage at the particular moment when a particular person

was due.

Mrs Clare rushed through the dark passage to the door, and her

husband came more slowly after her.

The new arrival, who was just about to enter, saw their anxious faces

in the doorway and the gleam of the west in their spectacles because

they confronted the last rays of day; but they could only see his

shape against the light.

"O, my boy, my boy--home again at last!" cried Mrs Clare, who cared

no more at that moment for the stains of heterodoxy which had caused

all this separation than for the dust upon his clothes. What woman,

indeed, among the most faithful adherents of the truth, believes the

promises and threats of the Word in the sense in which she believes

in her own children, or would not throw her theology to the wind if

weighed against their happiness? As soon as they reached the room

where the candles were lighted she looked at his face.

"O, it is not Angel--not my son--the Angel who went away!" she cried

in all the irony of sorrow, as she turned herself aside.

His father, too, was shocked to see him, so reduced was that figure

from its former contours by worry and the bad season that Clare had

experienced, in the climate to which he had so rashly hurried in his

first aversion to the mockery of events at home. You could see the

skeleton behind the man, and almost the ghost behind the skeleton.

He matched Crivelli's dead _Christus_. His sunken eye-pits were of

morbid hue, and the light in his eyes had waned. The angular hollows

and lines of his aged ancestors had succeeded to their reign in his

face twenty years before their time.

"I was ill over there, you know," he said. "I am all right now."

As if, however, to falsify this assertion, his legs seemed to give

way, and he suddenly sat down to save himself from falling. It was

only a slight attack of faintness, resulting from the tedious day's

journey, and the excitement of arrival.

"Has any letter come for me lately?" he asked. "I received the

last you sent on by the merest chance, and after considerable delay

through being inland; or I might have come sooner."

"It was from your wife, we supposed?"

"It was."

Only one other had recently come. They had not sent it on to him,

knowing he would start for home so soon.

He hastily opened the letter produced, and was much disturbed to read

in Tess's handwriting the sentiments expressed in her last hurried

scrawl to him.

O why have you treated me so monstrously, Angel! I do

not deserve it. I have thought it all over carefully,

and I can never, never forgive you! You know that I

did not intend to wrong you--why have you so wronged

me? You are cruel, cruel indeed! I will try to forget

you. It is all injustice I have received at your

hands!

T.

"It is quite true!" said Angel, throwing down the letter. "Perhaps

she will never be reconciled to me!"

"Don't, Angel, be so anxious about a mere child of the soil!" said

his mother.

"Child of the soil! Well, we all are children of the soil. I wish

she were so in the sense you mean; but let me now explain to you what

I have never explained before, that her father is a descendant in the

male line of one of the oldest Norman houses, like a good many others

who lead obscure agricultural lives in our villages, and are dubbed

'sons of the soil.'"

He soon retired to bed; and the next morning, feeling exceedingly

unwell, he remained in his room pondering. The circumstances amid

which he had left Tess were such that though, while on the south of

the Equator and just in receipt of her loving epistle, it had seemed

the easiest thing in the world to rush back into her arms the moment

he chose to forgive her, now that he had arrived it was not so easy

as it had seemed. She was passionate, and her present letter,

showing that her estimate of him had changed under his delay--too

justly changed, he sadly owned,--made him ask himself if it would

be wise to confront her unannounced in the presence of her parents.

Supposing that her love had indeed turned to dislike during the last

weeks of separation, a sudden meeting might lead to bitter words.

Clare therefore thought it would be best to prepare Tess and her

family by sending a line to Marlott announcing his return, and his

hope that she was still living with them there, as he had arranged

for her to do when he left England. He despatched the inquiry that

very day, and before the week was out there came a short reply from

Mrs Durbeyfield which did not remove his embarrassment, for it bore

no address, though to his surprise it was not written from Marlott.

SIR,

J write these few lines to say that my Daughter is away

from me at present, and J am not sure when she will

return, but J will let you know as Soon as she do.

J do not feel at liberty to tell you Where she is

temperly biding. J should say that me and my Family

have left Marlott for some Time.--

Yours,

J. DURBEYFIELD

It was such a relief to Clare to learn that Tess was at least

apparently well that her mother's stiff reticence as to her

whereabouts did not long distress him. They were all angry with him,

evidently. He would wait till Mrs Durbeyfield could inform him of

Tess's return, which her letter implied to be soon. He deserved no

more. His had been a love "which alters when it alteration finds".

He had undergone some strange experiences in his absence; he had seen

the virtual Faustina in the literal Cornelia, a spiritual Lucretia in

a corporeal Phryne; he had thought of the woman taken and set in the

midst as one deserving to be stoned, and of the wife of Uriah being

made a queen; and he had asked himself why he had not judged Tess

constructively rather than biographically, by the will rather than

by the deed?

A day or two passed while he waited at his father's house for the

promised second note from Joan Durbeyfield, and indirectly to recover

a little more strength. The strength showed signs of coming back,

but there was no sign of Joan's letter. Then he hunted up the

old letter sent on to him in Brazil, which Tess had written from

Flintcomb-Ash, and re-read it. The sentences touched him now as

much as when he had first perused them.

... I must cry to you in my trouble--I have no one

else! ... I think I must die if you do not come

soon, or tell me to come to you... please, please,

not to be just--only a little kind to me ... If

you would come, I could die in your arms! I would

be well content to do that if so be you had forgiven

me! ... if you will send me one little line, and say,

"I am coming soon," I will bide on, Angel--O, so

cheerfully! ... think how it do hurt my heart not to

see you ever--ever! Ah, if I could only make your

dear heart ache one little minute of each day as mine

does every day and all day long, it might lead you to

show pity to your poor lonely one. ... I would be

content, ay, glad, to live with you as your servant,

if I may not as your wife; so that I could only be

near you, and get glimpses of you, and think of you

as mine. ... I long for only one thing in heaven

or earth or under the earth, to meet you, my own

dear! Come to me--come to me, and save me from what

threatens me!

Clare determined that he would no longer believe in her more recent

and severer regard of him, but would go and find her immediately. He

asked his father if she had applied for any money during his absence.

His father returned a negative, and then for the first time it

occurred to Angel that her pride had stood in her way, and that she

had suffered privation. From his remarks his parents now gathered

the real reason of the separation; and their Christianity was such

that, reprobates being their especial care, the tenderness towards

Tess which her blood, her simplicity, even her poverty, had not

engendered, was instantly excited by her sin.

Whilst he was hastily packing together a few articles for his journey

he glanced over a poor plain missive also lately come to hand--the

one from Marian and Izz Huett, beginning--

"Honour'd Sir, Look to your Wife if you do love her as much as she do

love you," and signed, "From Two Well-Wishers."

LIV

In a quarter of an hour Clare was leaving the house, whence his

mother watched his thin figure as it disappeared into the street.

He had declined to borrow his father's old mare, well knowing of

its necessity to the household. He went to the inn, where he hired

a trap, and could hardly wait during the harnessing. In a very few

minutes after, he was driving up the hill out of the town which,

three or four months earlier in the year, Tess had descended with

such hopes and ascended with such shattered purposes.

Benvill Lane soon stretched before him, its hedges and trees purple

with buds; but he was looking at other things, and only recalled

himself to the scene sufficiently to enable him to keep the way. In

something less than an hour-and-a-half he had skirted the south of

the King's Hintock estates and ascended to the untoward solitude of

Cross-in-Hand, the unholy stone whereon Tess had been compelled by

Alec d'Urberville, in his whim of reformation, to swear the strange

oath that she would never wilfully tempt him again. The pale and

blasted nettle-stems of the preceding year even now lingered nakedly

in the banks, young green nettles of the present spring growing from

their roots.

Thence he went along the verge of the upland overhanging the other

Hintocks, and, turning to the right, plunged into the bracing

calcareous region of Flintcomb-Ash, the address from which she had

written to him in one of the letters, and which he supposed to be

the place of sojourn referred to by her mother. Here, of course, he

did not find her; and what added to his depression was the discovery

that no "Mrs Clare" had ever been heard of by the cottagers or by

the farmer himself, though Tess was remembered well enough by her

Christian name. His name she had obviously never used during their

separation, and her dignified sense of their total severance was

shown not much less by this abstention than by the hardships she had

chosen to undergo (of which he now learnt for the first time) rather

than apply to his father for more funds.

From this place they told him Tess Durbeyfield had gone, without due

notice, to the home of her parents on the other side of Blackmoor,

and it therefore became necessary to find Mrs Durbeyfield. She had

told him she was not now at Marlott, but had been curiously reticent

as to her actual address, and the only course was to go to Marlott

and inquire for it. The farmer who had been so churlish with Tess

was quite smooth-tongued to Clare, and lent him a horse and man to

drive him towards Marlott, the gig he had arrived in being sent back

to Emminster; for the limit of a day's journey with that horse was

reached.

Clare would not accept the loan of the farmer's vehicle for a further

distance than to the outskirts of the Vale, and, sending it back with

the man who had driven him, he put up at an inn, and next day entered

on foot the region wherein was the spot of his dear Tess's birth.

It was as yet too early in the year for much colour to appear in the

gardens and foliage; the so-called spring was but winter overlaid

with a thin coat of greenness, and it was of a parcel with his

expectations.

The house in which Tess had passed the years of her childhood was

now inhabited by another family who had never known her. The new

residents were in the garden, taking as much interest in their own

doings as if the homestead had never passed its primal time in

conjunction with the histories of others, beside which the histories

of these were but as a tale told by an idiot. They walked about the

garden paths with thoughts of their own concerns entirely uppermost,

bringing their actions at every moment in jarring collision with the

dim ghosts behind them, talking as though the time when Tess lived

there were not one whit intenser in story than now. Even the spring

birds sang over their heads as if they thought there was nobody

missing in particular.

On inquiry of these precious innocents, to whom even the name of

their predecessors was a failing memory, Clare learned that John

Durbeyfield was dead; that his widow and children had left Marlott,

declaring that they were going to live at Kingsbere, but instead of

doing so had gone on to another place they mentioned. By this time

Clare abhorred the house for ceasing to contain Tess, and hastened

away from its hated presence without once looking back.

His way was by the field in which he had first beheld her at the

dance. It was as bad as the house--even worse. He passed on through

the churchyard, where, amongst the new headstones, he saw one of a

somewhat superior design to the rest. The inscription ran thus:

In memory of John Durbeyfield, rightly d'Urberville, of

the once powerful family of that Name, and Direct

Descendant through an illustrious Line from Sir Pagan

d'Urberville, one of the Knights of the Conqueror. Died

March 10th, 18--

HOW ARE THE MIGHTY FALLEN.

Some man, apparently the sexton, had observed Clare standing there,

and drew nigh. "Ah, sir, now that's a man who didn't want to lie

here, but wished to be carried to Kingsbere, where his ancestors be."

"And why didn't they respect his wish?"

"Oh--no money. Bless your soul, sir, why--there, I wouldn't wish to

say it everywhere, but--even this headstone, for all the flourish

wrote upon en, is not paid for."

"Ah, who put it up?"

The man told the name of a mason in the village, and, on leaving the

churchyard, Clare called at the mason's house. He found that the

statement was true, and paid the bill. This done, he turned in the

direction of the migrants.

The distance was too long for a walk, but Clare felt such a strong

desire for isolation that at first he would neither hire a conveyance

nor go to a circuitous line of railway by which he might eventually

reach the place. At Shaston, however, he found he must hire; but

the way was such that he did not enter Joan's place till about seven

o'clock in the evening, having traversed a distance of over twenty

miles since leaving Marlott.

The village being small he had little difficulty in finding Mrs

Durbeyfield's tenement, which was a house in a walled garden,

remote from the main road, where she had stowed away her clumsy old

furniture as best she could. It was plain that for some reason or

other she had not wished him to visit her, and he felt his call to

be somewhat of an intrusion. She came to the door herself, and the

light from the evening sky fell upon her face.

This was the first time that Clare had ever met her, but he was too

preoccupied to observe more than that she was still a handsome woman,

in the garb of a respectable widow. He was obliged to explain that

he was Tess's husband, and his object in coming there, and he did it

awkwardly enough. "I want to see her at once," he added. "You said

you would write to me again, but you have not done so."

"Because she've not come home," said Joan.

"Do you know if she is well?"

"I don't. But you ought to, sir," said she.

"I admit it. Where is she staying?"

From the beginning of the interview Joan had disclosed her

embarrassment by keeping her hand to the side of her cheek.

"I--don't know exactly where she is staying," she answered. "She

was--but--"

"Where was she?"

"Well, she is not there now."

In her evasiveness she paused again, and the younger children had by

this time crept to the door, where, pulling at his mother's skirts,

the youngest murmured--

"Is this the gentleman who is going to marry Tess?"

"He has married her," Joan whispered. "Go inside."

Clare saw her efforts for reticence, and asked--

"Do you think Tess would wish me to try and find her? If not, of

course--"

"I don't think she would."

"Are you sure?"

"I am sure she wouldn't."

He was turning away; and then he thought of Tess's tender letter.

"I am sure she would!" he retorted passionately. "I know her better

than you do."

"That's very likely, sir; for I have never really known her."

"Please tell me her address, Mrs Durbeyfield, in kindness to a lonely

wretched man!" Tess's mother again restlessly swept her cheek with

her vertical hand, and seeing that he suffered, she at last said, is

a low voice--

"She is at Sandbourne."

"Ah--where there? Sandbourne has become a large place, they say."

"I don't know more particularly than I have said--Sandbourne. For

myself, I was never there."

It was apparent that Joan spoke the truth in this, and he pressed her

no further.

"Are you in want of anything?" he said gently.

"No, sir," she replied. "We are fairly well provided for."

Without entering the house Clare turned away. There was a station

three miles ahead, and paying off his coachman, he walked thither.

The last train to Sandbourne left shortly after, and it bore Clare

on its wheels.

LV

At eleven o'clock that night, having secured a bed at one of the

hotels and telegraphed his address to his father immediately on his

arrival, he walked out into the streets of Sandbourne. It was too

late to call on or inquire for any one, and he reluctantly postponed

his purpose till the morning. But he could not retire to rest just

yet.

This fashionable watering-place, with its eastern and its western

stations, its piers, its groves of pines, its promenades, and its

covered gardens, was, to Angel Clare, like a fairy place suddenly

created by the stroke of a wand, and allowed to get a little dusty.

An outlying eastern tract of the enormous Egdon Waste was close at

hand, yet on the very verge of that tawny piece of antiquity such a

glittering novelty as this pleasure city had chosen to spring up.

Within the space of a mile from its outskirts every irregularity

of the soil was prehistoric, every channel an undisturbed British

trackway; not a sod having been turned there since the days of the

Caesars. Yet the exotic had grown here, suddenly as the prophet's

gourd; and had drawn hither Tess.

By the midnight lamps he went up and down the winding way of this new

world in an old one, and could discern between the trees and against

the stars the lofty roofs, chimneys, gazebos, and towers of the

numerous fanciful residences of which the place was composed. It

was a city of detached mansions; a Mediterranean lounging-place on

the English Channel; and as seen now by night it seemed even more

imposing than it was.

The sea was near at hand, but not intrusive; it murmured, and he

thought it was the pines; the pines murmured in precisely the same

tones, and he thought they were the sea.

Where could Tess possibly be, a cottage-girl, his young wife, amidst

all this wealth and fashion? The more he pondered, the more was he

puzzled. Were there any cows to milk here? There certainly were

no fields to till. She was most probably engaged to do something in

one of these large houses; and he sauntered along, looking at the

chamber-windows and their lights going out one by one, and wondered

which of them might be hers.

Conjecture was useless, and just after twelve o'clock he entered

and went to bed. Before putting out his light he re-read Tess's

impassioned letter. Sleep, however, he could not--so near her, yet

so far from her--and he continually lifted the window-blind and

regarded the backs of the opposite houses, and wondered behind which

of the sashes she reposed at that moment.

He might almost as well have sat up all night. In the morning he

arose at seven, and shortly after went out, taking the direction of

the chief post-office. At the door he met an intelligent postman

coming out with letters for the morning delivery.

"Do you know the address of a Mrs Clare?" asked Angel. The postman

shook his head.

Then, remembering that she would have been likely to continue the use

of her maiden name, Clare said--

"Of a Miss Durbeyfield?"

"Durbeyfield?"

This also was strange to the postman addressed.

"There's visitors coming and going every day, as you know, sir," he

said; "and without the name of the house 'tis impossible to find

'em."

One of his comrades hastening out at that moment, the name was

repeated to him.

"I know no name of Durbeyfield; but there is the name of d'Urberville

at The Herons," said the second.

"That's it!" cried Clare, pleased to think that she had reverted to

the real pronunciation. "What place is The Herons?"

"A stylish lodging-house. 'Tis all lodging-houses here, bless 'ee."

Clare received directions how to find the house, and hastened

thither, arriving with the milkman. The Herons, though an ordinary

villa, stood in its own grounds, and was certainly the last place

in which one would have expected to find lodgings, so private was

its appearance. If poor Tess was a servant here, as he feared, she

would go to the back-door to that milkman, and he was inclined to go

thither also. However, in his doubts he turned to the front, and

rang.

The hour being early, the landlady herself opened the door. Clare

inquired for Teresa d'Urberville or Durbeyfield.

"Mrs d'Urberville?"

"Yes."

Tess, then, passed as a married woman, and he felt glad, even though

she had not adopted his name.

"Will you kindly tell her that a relative is anxious to see her?"

"It is rather early. What name shall I give, sir?"

"Angel."

"Mr Angel?"

"No; Angel. It is my Christian name. She'll understand."

"I'll see if she is awake."

He was shown into the front room--the dining-room--and looked out

through the spring curtains at the little lawn, and the rhododendrons

and other shrubs upon it. Obviously her position was by no means so

bad as he had feared, and it crossed his mind that she must somehow

have claimed and sold the jewels to attain it. He did not blame her

for one moment. Soon his sharpened ear detected footsteps upon the

stairs, at which his heart thumped so painfully that he could hardly

stand firm. "Dear me! what will she think of me, so altered as I

am!" he said to himself; and the door opened.

Tess appeared on the threshold--not at all as he had expected to

see her--bewilderingly otherwise, indeed. Her great natural beauty

was, if not heightened, rendered more obvious by her attire. She

was loosely wrapped in a cashmere dressing-gown of gray-white,

embroidered in half-mourning tints, and she wore slippers of the same

hue. Her neck rose out of a frill of down, and her well-remembered

cable of dark-brown hair was partially coiled up in a mass at the

back of her head and partly hanging on her shoulder--the evident

result of haste.

He had held out his arms, but they had fallen again to his side;

for she had not come forward, remaining still in the opening of the

doorway. Mere yellow skeleton that he was now, he felt the contrast

between them, and thought his appearance distasteful to her.

"Tess!" he said huskily, "can you forgive me for going away? Can't

you--come to me? How do you get to be--like this?"

"It is too late," said she, her voice sounding hard through the room,

her eyes shining unnaturally.

"I did not think rightly of you--I did not see you as you were!" he

continued to plead. "I have learnt to since, dearest Tessy mine!"

"Too late, too late!" she said, waving her hand in the impatience of

a person whose tortures cause every instant to seem an hour. "Don't

come close to me, Angel! No--you must not. Keep away."

"But don't you love me, my dear wife, because I have been so pulled

down by illness? You are not so fickle--I am come on purpose for

you--my mother and father will welcome you now!"

"Yes--O, yes, yes! But I say, I say it is too late."

She seemed to feel like a fugitive in a dream, who tries to move

away, but cannot. "Don't you know all--don't you know it? Yet how

do you come here if you do not know?"

"I inquired here and there, and I found the way."

"I waited and waited for you," she went on, her tones suddenly

resuming their old fluty pathos. "But you did not come! And I wrote

to you, and you did not come! He kept on saying you would never come

any more, and that I was a foolish woman. He was very kind to me,

and to mother, and to all of us after father's death. He--"

"I don't understand."

"He has won me back to him."

Clare looked at her keenly, then, gathering her meaning, flagged

like one plague-stricken, and his glance sank; it fell on her hands,

which, once rosy, were now white and more delicate.

She continued--

"He is upstairs. I hate him now, because he told me a lie--that you

would not come again; and you HAVE come! These clothes are what he's

put upon me: I didn't care what he did wi' me! But--will you go

away, Angel, please, and never come any more?"

They stood fixed, their baffled hearts looking out of their eyes with

a joylessness pitiful to see. Both seemed to implore something to

shelter them from reality.

"Ah--it is my fault!" said Clare.

But he could not get on. Speech was as inexpressive as silence. But

he had a vague consciousness of one thing, though it was not clear

to him till later; that his original Tess had spiritually ceased to

recognize the body before him as hers--allowing it to drift, like a

corpse upon the current, in a direction dissociated from its living

will.

A few instants passed, and he found that Tess was gone. His face

grew colder and more shrunken as he stood concentrated on the moment,

and a minute or two after, he found himself in the street, walking

along he did not know whither.

LVI

Mrs Brooks, the lady who was the householder at The Herons and owner

of all the handsome furniture, was not a person of an unusually

curious turn of mind. She was too deeply materialized, poor woman,

by her long and enforced bondage to that arithmetical demon

Profit-and-Loss, to retain much curiousity for its own sake, and

apart from possible lodgers' pockets. Nevertheless, the visit of

Angel Clare to her well-paying tenants, Mr and Mrs d'Urberville, as

she deemed them, was sufficiently exceptional in point of time and

manner to reinvigorate the feminine proclivity which had been stifled

down as useless save in its bearings to the letting trade.

Tess had spoken to her husband from the doorway, without entering

the dining-room, and Mrs Brooks, who stood within the partly-closed

door of her own sitting-room at the back of the passage, could

hear fragments of the conversation--if conversation it could be

called--between those two wretched souls. She heard Tess re-ascend

the stairs to the first floor, and the departure of Clare, and the

closing of the front door behind him. Then the door of the room

above was shut, and Mrs Brooks knew that Tess had re-entered her

apartment. As the young lady was not fully dressed, Mrs Brooks knew

that she would not emerge again for some time.

She accordingly ascended the stairs softly, and stood at the door of

the front room--a drawing-room, connected with the room immediately

behind it (which was a bedroom) by folding-doors in the common

manner. This first floor, containing Mrs Brooks's best apartments,

had been taken by the week by the d'Urbervilles. The back room was

now in silence; but from the drawing-room there came sounds.

All that she could at first distinguish of them was one syllable,

continually repeated in a low note of moaning, as if it came from a

soul bound to some Ixionian wheel--

"O--O--O!"

Then a silence, then a heavy sigh, and again--

"O--O--O!"

The landlady looked through the keyhole. Only a small space of the

room inside was visible, but within that space came a corner of the

breakfast table, which was already spread for the meal, and also a

chair beside. Over the seat of the chair Tess's face was bowed, her

posture being a kneeling one in front of it; her hands were clasped

over her head, the skirts of her dressing-gown and the embroidery of

her night-gown flowed upon the floor behind her, and her stockingless

feet, from which the slippers had fallen, protruded upon the carpet.

It was from her lips that came the murmur of unspeakable despair.

Then a man's voice from the adjoining bedroom--

"What's the matter?"

She did not answer, but went on, in a tone which was a soliloquy

rather than an exclamation, and a dirge rather than a soliloquy.

Mrs Brooks could only catch a portion:

"And then my dear, dear husband came home to me ... and I did not

know it! ... And you had used your cruel persuasion upon me ... you

did not stop using it--no--you did not stop! My little sisters and

brothers and my mother's needs--they were the things you moved me

by ... and you said my husband would never come back--never; and you

taunted me, and said what a simpleton I was to expect him! ... And

at last I believed you and gave way! ... And then he came back!

Now he is gone. Gone a second time, and I have lost him now

for ever ... and he will not love me the littlest bit ever any

more--only hate me! ... O yes, I have lost him now--again because

of--you!" In writhing, with her head on the chair, she turned her

face towards the door, and Mrs Brooks could see the pain upon it,

and that her lips were bleeding from the clench of her teeth upon

them, and that the long lashes of her closed eyes stuck in wet tags

to her cheeks. She continued: "And he is dying--he looks as if he

is dying! ... And my sin will kill him and not kill me! ... O, you

have torn my life all to pieces ... made me be what I prayed you in

pity not to make me be again! ... My own true husband will never,

never--O God--I can't bear this!--I cannot!"

There were more and sharper words from the man; then a sudden rustle;

she had sprung to her feet. Mrs Brooks, thinking that the speaker

was coming to rush out of the door, hastily retreated down the

stairs.

She need not have done so, however, for the door of the sitting-room

was not opened. But Mrs Brooks felt it unsafe to watch on the

landing again, and entered her own parlour below.

She could hear nothing through the floor, although she listened

intently, and thereupon went to the kitchen to finish her interrupted

breakfast. Coming up presently to the front room on the ground floor

she took up some sewing, waiting for her lodgers to ring that she

might take away the breakfast, which she meant to do herself, to

discover what was the matter if possible. Overhead, as she sat, she

could now hear the floorboards slightly creak, as if some one were

walking about, and presently the movement was explained by the rustle

of garments against the banisters, the opening and the closing of

the front door, and the form of Tess passing to the gate on her way

into the street. She was fully dressed now in the walking costume

of a well-to-do young lady in which she had arrived, with the sole

addition that over her hat and black feathers a veil was drawn.

Mrs Brooks had not been able to catch any word of farewell, temporary

or otherwise, between her tenants at the door above. They might have

quarrelled, or Mr d'Urberville might still be asleep, for he was not

an early riser.

She went into the back room, which was more especially her own

apartment, and continued her sewing there. The lady lodger did not

return, nor did the gentleman ring his bell. Mrs Brooks pondered on

the delay, and on what probable relation the visitor who had called

so early bore to the couple upstairs. In reflecting she leant back

in her chair.

As she did so her eyes glanced casually over the ceiling till they

were arrested by a spot in the middle of its white surface which she

had never noticed there before. It was about the size of a wafer

when she first observed it, but it speedily grew as large as the palm

of her hand, and then she could perceive that it was red. The oblong

white ceiling, with this scarlet blot in the midst, had the

appearance of a gigantic ace of hearts.

Mrs Brooks had strange qualms of misgiving. She got upon the table,

and touched the spot in the ceiling with her fingers. It was damp,

and she fancied that it was a blood stain.

Descending from the table, she left the parlour, and went upstairs,

intending to enter the room overhead, which was the bedchamber at

the back of the drawing-room. But, nerveless woman as she had now

become, she could not bring herself to attempt the handle. She

listened. The dead silence within was broken only by a regular beat.

Drip, drip, drip.

Mrs Brooks hastened downstairs, opened the front door, and ran into

the street. A man she knew, one of the workmen employed at an

adjoining villa, was passing by, and she begged him to come in and go

upstairs with her; she feared something had happened to one of her

lodgers. The workman assented, and followed her to the landing.

She opened the door of the drawing-room, and stood back for him

to pass in, entering herself behind him. The room was empty; the

breakfast--a substantial repast of coffee, eggs, and a cold ham--lay

spread upon the table untouched, as when she had taken it up,

excepting that the carving-knife was missing. She asked the man to

go through the folding-doors into the adjoining room.

He opened the doors, entered a step or two, and came back almost

instantly with a rigid face. "My good God, the gentleman in bed is

dead! I think he has been hurt with a knife--a lot of blood had run

down upon the floor!"

The alarm was soon given, and the house which had lately been so

quiet resounded with the tramp of many footsteps, a surgeon among the

rest. The wound was small, but the point of the blade had touched

the heart of the victim, who lay on his back, pale, fixed, dead, as

if he had scarcely moved after the infliction of the blow. In a

quarter of an hour the news that a gentleman who was a temporary

visitor to the town had been stabbed in his bed, spread through every

street and villa of the popular watering-place.

LVII

Meanwhile Angel Clare had walked automatically along the way by which

he had come, and, entering his hotel, sat down over the breakfast,

staring at nothingness. He went on eating and drinking unconsciously

till on a sudden he demanded his bill; having paid which, he took his

dressing-bag in his hand, the only luggage he had brought with him,

and went out.

At the moment of his departure a telegram was handed to him--a few

words from his mother, stating that they were glad to know his

address, and informing him that his brother Cuthbert had proposed to

and been accepted by Mercy Chant.

Clare crumpled up the paper and followed the route to the station;

reaching it, he found that there would be no train leaving for an

hour and more. He sat down to wait, and having waited a quarter of

an hour felt that he could wait there no longer. Broken in heart and

numbed, he had nothing to hurry for; but he wished to get out of a

town which had been the scene of such an experience, and turned to

walk to the first station onward, and let the train pick him up

there.

The highway that he followed was open, and at a little distance

dipped into a valley, across which it could be seen running from edge

to edge. He had traversed the greater part of this depression, and

was climbing the western acclivity when, pausing for breath, he

unconsciously looked back. Why he did so he could not say, but

something seemed to impel him to the act. The tape-like surface of

the road diminished in his rear as far as he could see, and as he

gazed a moving spot intruded on the white vacuity of its perspective.

It was a human figure running. Clare waited, with a dim sense that

somebody was trying to overtake him.

The form descending the incline was a woman's, yet so entirely was

his mind blinded to the idea of his wife's following him that even

when she came nearer he did not recognize her under the totally

changed attire in which he now beheld her. It was not till she was

quite close that he could believe her to be Tess.

"I saw you--turn away from the station--just before I got there--and

I have been following you all this way!"

She was so pale, so breathless, so quivering in every muscle, that he

did not ask her a single question, but seizing her hand, and pulling

it within his arm, he led her along. To avoid meeting any possible

wayfarers he left the high road and took a footpath under some

fir-trees. When they were deep among the moaning boughs he stopped

and looked at her inquiringly.

"Angel," she said, as if waiting for this, "do you know what I have

been running after you for? To tell you that I have killed him!"

A pitiful white smile lit her face as she spoke.

"What!" said he, thinking from the strangeness of her manner that she

was in some delirium.

"I have done it--I don't know how," she continued. "Still, I owed it

to you, and to myself, Angel. I feared long ago, when I struck him

on the mouth with my glove, that I might do it some day for the trap

he set for me in my simple youth, and his wrong to you through me.

He has come between us and ruined us, and now he can never do it any

more. I never loved him at all, Angel, as I loved you. You know it,

don't you? You believe it? You didn't come back to me, and I was

obliged to go back to him. Why did you go away--why did you--when I

loved you so? I can't think why you did it. But I don't blame you;

only, Angel, will you forgive me my sin against you, now I have

killed him? I thought as I ran along that you would be sure to

forgive me now I have done that. It came to me as a shining light

that I should get you back that way. I could not bear the loss of

you any longer--you don't know how entirely I was unable to bear your

not loving me! Say you do now, dear, dear husband; say you do, now I

have killed him!"

"I do love you, Tess--O, I do--it is all come back!" he said,

tightening his arms round her with fervid pressure. "But how do you

mean--you have killed him?"

"I mean that I have," she murmured in a reverie.

"What, bodily? Is he dead?"

"Yes. He heard me crying about you, and he bitterly taunted me; and

called you by a foul name; and then I did it. My heart could not

bear it. He had nagged me about you before. And then I dressed

myself and came away to find you."

By degrees he was inclined to believe that she had faintly attempted,

at least, what she said she had done; and his horror at her impulse

was mixed with amazement at the strength of her affection for

himself, and at the strangeness of its quality, which had apparently

extinguished her moral sense altogether. Unable to realize the

gravity of her conduct, she seemed at last content; and he looked

at her as she lay upon his shoulder, weeping with happiness, and

wondered what obscure strain in the d'Urberville blood had led to

this aberration--if it were an aberration. There momentarily flashed

through his mind that the family tradition of the coach and murder

might have arisen because the d'Urbervilles had been known to do

these things. As well as his confused and excited ideas could

reason, he supposed that in the moment of mad grief of which she

spoke, her mind had lost its balance, and plunged her into this

abyss.

It was very terrible if true; if a temporary hallucination, sad. But,

anyhow, here was this deserted wife of his, this passionately-fond

woman, clinging to him without a suspicion that he would be anything

to her but a protector. He saw that for him to be otherwise was

not, in her mind, within the region of the possible. Tenderness was

absolutely dominant in Clare at last. He kissed her endlessly with

his white lips, and held her hand, and said--

"I will not desert you! I will protect you by every means in my

power, dearest love, whatever you may have done or not have done!"

They then walked on under the trees, Tess turning her head every now

and then to look at him. Worn and unhandsome as he had become, it

was plain that she did not discern the least fault in his appearance.

To her he was, as of old, all that was perfection, personally and

mentally. He was still her Antinous, her Apollo even; his sickly

face was beautiful as the morning to her affectionate regard on

this day no less than when she first beheld him; for was it not the

face of the one man on earth who had loved her purely, and who had

believed in her as pure!

With an instinct as to possibilities, he did not now, as he had

intended, make for the first station beyond the town, but plunged

still farther under the firs, which here abounded for miles. Each

clasping the other round the waist they promenaded over the dry bed

of fir-needles, thrown into a vague intoxicating atmosphere at the

consciousness of being together at last, with no living soul between

them; ignoring that there was a corpse. Thus they proceeded for

several miles till Tess, arousing herself, looked about her, and

said, timidly--

"Are we going anywhere in particular?"

"I don't know, dearest. Why?"

"I don't know."

"Well, we might walk a few miles further, and when it is evening find

lodgings somewhere or other--in a lonely cottage, perhaps. Can you

walk well, Tessy?"

"O yes! I could walk for ever and ever with your arm round me!"

Upon the whole it seemed a good thing to do. Thereupon they

quickened their pace, avoiding high roads, and following obscure

paths tending more or less northward. But there was an unpractical

vagueness in their movements throughout the day; neither one of them

seemed to consider any question of effectual escape, disguise, or

long concealment. Their every idea was temporary and unforefending,

like the plans of two children.

At mid-day they drew near to a roadside inn, and Tess would have

entered it with him to get something to eat, but he persuaded

her to remain among the trees and bushes of this half-woodland,

half-moorland part of the country till he should come back. Her

clothes were of recent fashion; even the ivory-handled parasol that

she carried was of a shape unknown in the retired spot to which they

had now wandered; and the cut of such articles would have attracted

attention in the settle of a tavern. He soon returned, with food

enough for half-a-dozen people and two bottles of wine--enough to

last them for a day or more, should any emergency arise.

They sat down upon some dead boughs and shared their meal. Between

one and two o'clock they packed up the remainder and went on again.

"I feel strong enough to walk any distance," said she.

"I think we may as well steer in a general way towards the interior

of the country, where we can hide for a time, and are less likely to

be looked for than anywhere near the coast," Clare remarked. "Later

on, when they have forgotten us, we can make for some port."

She made no reply to this beyond that of grasping him more tightly,

and straight inland they went. Though the season was an English May,

the weather was serenely bright, and during the afternoon it was

quite warm. Through the latter miles of their walk their footpath

had taken them into the depths of the New Forest, and towards

evening, turning the corner of a lane, they perceived behind a brook

and bridge a large board on which was painted in white letters, "This

desirable Mansion to be Let Furnished"; particulars following, with

directions to apply to some London agents. Passing through the gate

they could see the house, an old brick building of regular design and

large accommodation.

"I know it," said Clare. "It is Bramshurst Court. You can see that

it is shut up, and grass is growing on the drive."

"Some of the windows are open," said Tess.

"Just to air the rooms, I suppose."

"All these rooms empty, and we without a roof to our heads!"

"You are getting tired, my Tess!" he said. "We'll stop soon." And

kissing her sad mouth, he again led her onwards.

He was growing weary likewise, for they had wandered a dozen or

fifteen miles, and it became necessary to consider what they should

do for rest. They looked from afar at isolated cottages and little

inns, and were inclined to approach one of the latter, when their

hearts failed them, and they sheered off. At length their gait

dragged, and they stood still.

"Could we sleep under the trees?" she asked.

He thought the season insufficiently advanced.

"I have been thinking of that empty mansion we passed," he said.

"Let us go back towards it again."

They retraced their steps, but it was half an hour before they stood

without the entrance-gate as earlier. He then requested her to stay

where she was, whilst he went to see who was within.

She sat down among the bushes within the gate, and Clare crept

towards the house. His absence lasted some considerable time, and

when he returned Tess was wildly anxious, not for herself, but for

him. He had found out from a boy that there was only an old woman in

charge as caretaker, and she only came there on fine days, from the

hamlet near, to open and shut the windows. She would come to shut

them at sunset. "Now, we can get in through one of the lower

windows, and rest there," said he.

Under his escort she went tardily forward to the main front, whose

shuttered windows, like sightless eyeballs, excluded the possibility

of watchers. The door was reached a few steps further, and one of

the windows beside it was open. Clare clambered in, and pulled Tess

in after him.

Except the hall, the rooms were all in darkness, and they ascended

the staircase. Up here also the shutters were tightly closed,

the ventilation being perfunctorily done, for this day at least,

by opening the hall-window in front and an upper window behind.

Clare unlatched the door of a large chamber, felt his way across

it, and parted the shutters to the width of two or three inches.

A shaft of dazzling sunlight glanced into the room, revealing heavy,

old-fashioned furniture, crimson damask hangings, and an enormous

four-post bedstead, along the head of which were carved running

figures, apparently Atalanta's race.

"Rest at last!" said he, setting down his bag and the parcel of

viands.

They remained in great quietness till the caretaker should have come

to shut the windows: as a precaution, putting themselves in total

darkness by barring the shutters as before, lest the woman should

open the door of their chamber for any casual reason. Between six

and seven o'clock she came, but did not approach the wing they

were in. They heard her close the windows, fasten them, lock the

door, and go away. Then Clare again stole a chink of light from

the window, and they shared another meal, till by-and-by they

were enveloped in the shades of night which they had no candle to

disperse.

LVIII

The night was strangely solemn and still. In the small hours she

whispered to him the whole story of how he had walked in his sleep

with her in his arms across the Froom stream, at the imminent risk of

both their lives, and laid her down in the stone coffin at the ruined

abbey. He had never known of that till now.

"Why didn't you tell me next day?" he said. "It might have prevented

much misunderstanding and woe."

"Don't think of what's past!" said she. "I am not going to think

outside of now. Why should we! Who knows what to-morrow has in

store?"

But it apparently had no sorrow. The morning was wet and foggy, and

Clare, rightly informed that the caretaker only opened the windows

on fine days, ventured to creep out of their chamber and explore the

house, leaving Tess asleep. There was no food on the premises, but

there was water, and he took advantage of the fog to emerge from the

mansion and fetch tea, bread, and butter from a shop in a little

place two miles beyond, as also a small tin kettle and spirit-lamp,

that they might get fire without smoke. His re-entry awoke her; and

they breakfasted on what he had brought.

They were indisposed to stir abroad, and the day passed, and the

night following, and the next, and next; till, almost without their

being aware, five days had slipped by in absolute seclusion, not a

sight or sound of a human being disturbing their peacefulness, such

as it was. The changes of the weather were their only events, the

birds of the New Forest their only company. By tacit consent they

hardly once spoke of any incident of the past subsequent to their

wedding-day. The gloomy intervening time seemed to sink into chaos,

over which the present and prior times closed as if it never had

been. Whenever he suggested that they should leave their shelter,

and go forwards towards Southampton or London, she showed a strange

unwillingness to move.

"Why should we put an end to all that's sweet and lovely!" she

deprecated. "What must come will come." And, looking through the

shutter-chink: "All is trouble outside there; inside here content."

He peeped out also. It was quite true; within was affection, union,

error forgiven: outside was the inexorable.

"And--and," she said, pressing her cheek against his, "I fear that

what you think of me now may not last. I do not wish to outlive your

present feeling for me. I would rather not. I would rather be dead

and buried when the time comes for you to despise me, so that it may

never be known to me that you despised me."

"I cannot ever despise you."

"I also hope that. But considering what my life has been, I cannot

see why any man should, sooner or later, be able to help despising

me.... How wickedly mad I was! Yet formerly I never could bear to

hurt a fly or a worm, and the sight of a bird in a cage used often to

make me cry."

They remained yet another day. In the night the dull sky cleared,

and the result was that the old caretaker at the cottage awoke early.

The brilliant sunrise made her unusually brisk; she decided to open

the contiguous mansion immediately, and to air it thoroughly on such

a day. Thus it occurred that, having arrived and opened the lower

rooms before six o'clock, she ascended to the bedchambers, and was

about to turn the handle of the one wherein they lay. At that moment

she fancied she could hear the breathing of persons within. Her

slippers and her antiquity had rendered her progress a noiseless one

so far, and she made for instant retreat; then, deeming that her

hearing might have deceived her, she turned anew to the door and

softly tried the handle. The lock was out of order, but a piece of

furniture had been moved forward on the inside, which prevented her

opening the door more than an inch or two. A stream of morning light

through the shutter-chink fell upon the faces of the pair, wrapped in

profound slumber, Tess's lips being parted like a half-opened flower

near his cheek. The caretaker was so struck with their innocent

appearance, and with the elegance of Tess's gown hanging across a

chair, her silk stockings beside it, the pretty parasol, and the

other habits in which she had arrived because she had none else, that

her first indignation at the effrontery of tramps and vagabonds gave

way to a momentary sentimentality over this genteel elopement, as it

seemed. She closed the door, and withdrew as softly as she had come,

to go and consult with her neighbours on the odd discovery.

Not more than a minute had elapsed after her withdrawal when Tess

woke, and then Clare. Both had a sense that something had disturbed

them, though they could not say what; and the uneasy feeling which

it engendered grew stronger. As soon as he was dressed he narrowly

scanned the lawn through the two or three inches of shutter-chink.

"I think we will leave at once," said he. "It is a fine day. And I

cannot help fancying somebody is about the house. At any rate, the

woman will be sure to come to-day."

She passively assented, and putting the room in order, they took up

the few articles that belonged to them, and departed noiselessly.

When they had got into the Forest she turned to take a last look at

the house.

"Ah, happy house--goodbye!" she said. "My life can only be a

question of a few weeks. Why should we not have stayed there?"

"Don't say it, Tess! We shall soon get out of this district

altogether. We'll continue our course as we've begun it, and keep

straight north. Nobody will think of looking for us there. We shall

be looked for at the Wessex ports if we are sought at all. When we

are in the north we will get to a port and away."

Having thus persuaded her, the plan was pursued, and they kept a

bee-line northward. Their long repose at the manor-house lent them

walking power now; and towards mid-day they found that they were

approaching the steepled city of Melchester, which lay directly in

their way. He decided to rest her in a clump of trees during the

afternoon, and push onward under cover of darkness. At dusk Clare

purchased food as usual, and their night march began, the boundary

between Upper and Mid-Wessex being crossed about eight o'clock.

To walk across country without much regard to roads was not new

to Tess, and she showed her old agility in the performance. The

intercepting city, ancient Melchester, they were obliged to pass

through in order to take advantage of the town bridge for crossing a

large river that obstructed them. It was about midnight when they

went along the deserted streets, lighted fitfully by the few lamps,

keeping off the pavement that it might not echo their footsteps.

The graceful pile of cathedral architecture rose dimly on their left

hand, but it was lost upon them now. Once out of the town they

followed the turnpike-road, which after a few miles plunged across an

open plain.

Though the sky was dense with cloud, a diffused light from some

fragment of a moon had hitherto helped them a little. But the moon

had now sunk, the clouds seemed to settle almost on their heads, and

the night grew as dark as a cave. However, they found their way

along, keeping as much on the turf as possible that their tread might

not resound, which it was easy to do, there being no hedge or fence

of any kind. All around was open loneliness and black solitude, over

which a stiff breeze blew.

They had proceeded thus gropingly two or three miles further when

on a sudden Clare became conscious of some vast erection close in

his front, rising sheer from the grass. They had almost struck

themselves against it.

"What monstrous place is this?" said Angel.

"It hums," said she. "Hearken!"

He listened. The wind, playing upon the edifice, produced a booming

tune, like the note of some gigantic one-stringed harp. No other

sound came from it, and lifting his hand and advancing a step or

two, Clare felt the vertical surface of the structure. It seemed to

be of solid stone, without joint or moulding. Carrying his fingers

onward he found that what he had come in contact with was a colossal

rectangular pillar; by stretching out his left hand he could feel a

similar one adjoining. At an indefinite height overhead something

made the black sky blacker, which had the semblance of a vast

architrave uniting the pillars horizontally. They carefully entered

beneath and between; the surfaces echoed their soft rustle; but they

seemed to be still out of doors. The place was roofless. Tess drew

her breath fearfully, and Angel, perplexed, said--

"What can it be?"

Feeling sideways they encountered another tower-like pillar, square

and uncompromising as the first; beyond it another and another. The

place was all doors and pillars, some connected above by continuous

architraves.

"A very Temple of the Winds," he said.

The next pillar was isolated; others composed a trilithon; others

were prostrate, their flanks forming a causeway wide enough for a

carriage; and it was soon obvious that they made up a forest of

monoliths grouped upon the grassy expanse of the plain. The couple

advanced further into this pavilion of the night till they stood in

its midst.

"It is Stonehenge!" said Clare.

"The heathen temple, you mean?"

"Yes. Older than the centuries; older than the d'Urbervilles! Well,

what shall we do, darling? We may find shelter further on."

But Tess, really tired by this time, flung herself upon an oblong

slab that lay close at hand, and was sheltered from the wind by a

pillar. Owing to the action of the sun during the preceding day, the

stone was warm and dry, in comforting contrast to the rough and chill

grass around, which had damped her skirts and shoes.

"I don't want to go any further, Angel," she said, stretching out her

hand for his. "Can't we bide here?"

"I fear not. This spot is visible for miles by day, although it does

not seem so now."

"One of my mother's people was a shepherd hereabouts, now I think of

it. And you used to say at Talbothays that I was a heathen. So now

I am at home."

He knelt down beside her outstretched form, and put his lips upon

hers.

"Sleepy are you, dear? I think you are lying on an altar."

"I like very much to be here," she murmured. "It is so solemn and

lonely--after my great happiness--with nothing but the sky above my

face. It seems as if there were no folk in the world but we two;

and I wish there were not--except 'Liza-Lu."

Clare though she might as well rest here till it should get a little

lighter, and he flung his overcoat upon her, and sat down by her

side.

"Angel, if anything happens to me, will you watch over 'Liza-Lu for

my sake?" she asked, when they had listened a long time to the wind

among the pillars.

"I will."

"She is so good and simple and pure. O, Angel--I wish you would

marry her if you lose me, as you will do shortly. O, if you would!"

"If I lose you I lose all! And she is my sister-in-law."

"That's nothing, dearest. People marry sister-laws continually about

Marlott; and 'Liza-Lu is so gentle and sweet, and she is growing

so beautiful. O, I could share you with her willingly when we are

spirits! If you would train her and teach her, Angel, and bring her

up for your own self! ... She had all the best of me without the bad

of me; and if she were to become yours it would almost seem as if

death had not divided us... Well, I have said it. I won't mention

it again."

She ceased, and he fell into thought. In the far north-east sky he

could see between the pillars a level streak of light. The uniform

concavity of black cloud was lifting bodily like the lid of a pot,

letting in at the earth's edge the coming day, against which the

towering monoliths and trilithons began to be blackly defined.

"Did they sacrifice to God here?" asked she.

"No," said he.

"Who to?"

"I believe to the sun. That lofty stone set away by itself is in the

direction of the sun, which will presently rise behind it."

"This reminds me, dear," she said. "You remember you never would

interfere with any belief of mine before we were married? But I knew

your mind all the same, and I thought as you thought--not from any

reasons of my own, but because you thought so. Tell me now, Angel,

do you think we shall meet again after we are dead? I want to know."

He kissed her to avoid a reply at such a time.

"O, Angel--I fear that means no!" said she, with a suppressed sob.

"And I wanted so to see you again--so much, so much! What--not even

you and I, Angel, who love each other so well?"

Like a greater than himself, to the critical question at the critical

time he did not answer; and they were again silent. In a minute or

two her breathing became more regular, her clasp of his hand relaxed,

and she fell asleep. The band of silver paleness along the east

horizon made even the distant parts of the Great Plain appear dark

and near; and the whole enormous landscape bore that impress of

reserve, taciturnity, and hesitation which is usual just before day.

The eastward pillars and their architraves stood up blackly against

the light, and the great flame-shaped Sun-stone beyond them; and the

Stone of Sacrifice midway. Presently the night wind died out, and

the quivering little pools in the cup-like hollows of the stones lay

still. At the same time something seemed to move on the verge of the

dip eastward--a mere dot. It was the head of a man approaching them

from the hollow beyond the Sun-stone. Clare wished they had gone

onward, but in the circumstances decided to remain quiet. The figure

came straight towards the circle of pillars in which they were.

He heard something behind him, the brush of feet. Turning, he saw

over the prostrate columns another figure; then before he was aware,

another was at hand on the right, under a trilithon, and another on

the left. The dawn shone full on the front of the man westward, and

Clare could discern from this that he was tall, and walked as if

trained. They all closed in with evident purpose. Her story then

was true! Springing to his feet, he looked around for a weapon,

loose stone, means of escape, anything. By this time the nearest

man was upon him.

"It is no use, sir," he said. "There are sixteen of us on the Plain,

and the whole country is reared."

"Let her finish her sleep!" he implored in a whisper of the men as

they gathered round.

When they saw where she lay, which they had not done till then, they

showed no objection, and stood watching her, as still as the pillars

around. He went to the stone and bent over her, holding one poor

little hand; her breathing now was quick and small, like that of a

lesser creature than a woman. All waited in the growing light, their

faces and hands as if they were silvered, the remainder of their

figures dark, the stones glistening green-gray, the Plain still a

mass of shade. Soon the light was strong, and a ray shone upon her

unconscious form, peering under her eyelids and waking her.

"What is it, Angel?" she said, starting up. "Have they come for me?"

"Yes, dearest," he said. "They have come."

"It is as it should be," she murmured. "Angel, I am almost glad--yes,

glad! This happiness could not have lasted. It was too much. I

have had enough; and now I shall not live for you to despise me!"

She stood up, shook herself, and went forward, neither of the men

having moved.

"I am ready," she said quietly.

LIX

The city of Wintoncester, that fine old city, aforetime capital

of Wessex, lay amidst its convex and concave downlands in all the

brightness and warmth of a July morning. The gabled brick, tile, and

freestone houses had almost dried off for the season their integument

of lichen, the streams in the meadows were low, and in the sloping

High Street, from the West Gateway to the medival cross, and from

the medival cross to the bridge, that leisurely dusting and sweeping

was in progress which usually ushers in an old-fashioned market-day.

From the western gate aforesaid the highway, as every Wintoncestrian

knows, ascends a long and regular incline of the exact length of a

measured mile, leaving the houses gradually behind. Up this road

from the precincts of the city two persons were walking rapidly,

as if unconscious of the trying ascent--unconscious through

preoccupation and not through buoyancy. They had emerged upon this

road through a narrow, barred wicket in a high wall a little lower

down. They seemed anxious to get out of the sight of the houses and

of their kind, and this road appeared to offer the quickest means

of doing so. Though they were young, they walked with bowed heads,

which gait of grief the sun's rays smiled on pitilessly.

One of the pair was Angel Clare, the other a tall budding

creature--half girl, half woman--a spiritualized image of Tess,

slighter than she, but with the same beautiful eyes--Clare's

sister-in-law, 'Liza-Lu. Their pale faces seemed to have shrunk

to half their natural size. They moved on hand in hand, and never

spoke a word, the drooping of their heads being that of Giotto's

"Two Apostles".

When they had nearly reached the top of the great West Hill the

clocks in the town struck eight. Each gave a start at the notes,

and, walking onward yet a few steps, they reached the first

milestone, standing whitely on the green margin of the grass, and

backed by the down, which here was open to the road. They entered

upon the turf, and, impelled by a force that seemed to overrule their

will, suddenly stood still, turned, and waited in paralyzed suspense

beside the stone.

The prospect from this summit was almost unlimited. In the valley

beneath lay the city they had just left, its more prominent buildings

showing as in an isometric drawing--among them the broad cathedral

tower, with its Norman windows and immense length of aisle and nave,

the spires of St Thomas's, the pinnacled tower of the College, and,

more to the right, the tower and gables of the ancient hospice,

where to this day the pilgrim may receive his dole of bread and ale.

Behind the city swept the rotund upland of St Catherine's Hill;

further off, landscape beyond landscape, till the horizon was lost

in the radiance of the sun hanging above it.

Against these far stretches of country rose, in front of the other

city edifices, a large red-brick building, with level gray roofs,

and rows of short barred windows bespeaking captivity, the whole

contrasting greatly by its formalism with the quaint irregularities

of the Gothic erections. It was somewhat disguised from the road in

passing it by yews and evergreen oaks, but it was visible enough up

here. The wicket from which the pair had lately emerged was in the

wall of this structure. From the middle of the building an ugly

flat-topped octagonal tower ascended against the east horizon, and

viewed from this spot, on its shady side and against the light, it

seemed the one blot on the city's beauty. Yet it was with this blot,

and not with the beauty, that the two gazers were concerned.

Upon the cornice of the tower a tall staff was fixed. Their eyes

were riveted on it. A few minutes after the hour had struck

something moved slowly up the staff, and extended itself upon the

breeze. It was a black flag.

"Justice" was done, and the President of the Immortals, in Aeschylean

phrase, had ended his sport with Tess. And the d'Urberville knights

and dames slept on in their tombs unknowing. The two speechless

gazers bent themselves down to the earth, as if in prayer, and

remained thus a long time, absolutely motionless: the flag continued

to wave silently. As soon as they had strength, they arose, joined

hands again, and went on.

***END OF THE PROJECT GUTENBERG EBOOK TESS OF THE D'URBERVILLES***

******* This file should be named 110-8.txt or 110-8.zip *******

This and all associated files of various formats will be found in:

http://www.gutenberg.org/dirs/1/1/110

Updated editions will replace the previous one--the old editions

will be renamed.

Creating the works from public domain print editions means that no

one owns a United States copyright in these works, so the Foundation

(and you!) can copy and distribute it in the United States without

permission and without paying copyright royalties. Special rules,

set forth in the General Terms of Use part of this license, apply to

copying and distributing Project Gutenberg-tm electronic works to

protect the PROJECT GUTENBERG-tm concept and trademark. Project

Gutenberg is a registered trademark, and may not be used if you

charge for the eBooks, unless you receive specific permission. If you

do not charge anything for copies of this eBook, complying with the

rules is very easy. You may use this eBook for nearly any purpose

such as creation of derivative works, reports, performances and

research. They may be modified and printed and given away--you may do

practically ANYTHING with public domain eBooks. Redistribution is

subject to the trademark license, especially commercial

redistribution.

*** START: FULL LICENSE ***

THE FULL PROJECT GUTENBERG LICENSE

PLEASE READ THIS BEFORE YOU DISTRIBUTE OR USE THIS WORK

To protect the Project Gutenberg-tm mission of promoting the free

distribution of electronic works, by using or distributing this work

(or any other work associated in any way with the phrase "Project

Gutenberg"), you agree to comply with all the terms of the Full Project

Gutenberg-tm License (available with this file or online at

http://gutenberg.net/license).

Section 1. General Terms of Use and Redistributing Project Gutenberg-tm

electronic works

1.A. By reading or using any part of this Project Gutenberg-tm

electronic work, you indicate that you have read, understand, agree to

and accept all the terms of this license and intellectual property

(trademark/copyright) agreement. If you do not agree to abide by all

the terms of this agreement, you must cease using and return or destroy

all copies of Project Gutenberg-tm electronic works in your possession.

If you paid a fee for obtaining a copy of or access to a Project

Gutenberg-tm electronic work and you do not agree to be bound by the

terms of this agreement, you may obtain a refund from the person or

entity to whom you paid the fee as set forth in paragraph 1.E.8.

1.B. "Project Gutenberg" is a registered trademark. It may only be

used on or associated in any way with an electronic work by people who

agree to be bound by the terms of this agreement. There are a few

things that you can do with most Project Gutenberg-tm electronic works

even without complying with the full terms of this agreement. See

paragraph 1.C below. There are a lot of things you can do with Project

Gutenberg-tm electronic works if you follow the terms of this agreement

and help preserve free future access to Project Gutenberg-tm electronic

works. See paragraph 1.E below.

1.C. The Project Gutenberg Literary Archive Foundation ("the Foundation"

or PGLAF), owns a compilation copyright in the collection of Project

Gutenberg-tm electronic works. Nearly all the individual works in the

collection are in the public domain in the United States. If an

individual work is in the public domain in the United States and you are

located in the United States, we do not claim a right to prevent you from

copying, distributing, performing, displaying or creating derivative

works based on the work as long as all references to Project Gutenberg

are removed. Of course, we hope that you will support the Project

Gutenberg-tm mission of promoting free access to electronic works by

freely sharing Project Gutenberg-tm works in compliance with the terms of

this agreement for keeping the Project Gutenberg-tm name associated with

the work. You can easily comply with the terms of this agreement by

keeping this work in the same format with its attached full Project

Gutenberg-tm License when you share it without charge with others.

1.D. The copyright laws of the place where you are located also govern

what you can do with this work. Copyright laws in most countries are in

a constant state of change. If you are outside the United States, check

the laws of your country in addition to the terms of this agreement

before downloading, copying, displaying, performing, distributing or

creating derivative works based on this work or any other Project

Gutenberg-tm work. The Foundation makes no representations concerning

the copyright status of any work in any country outside the United

States.

1.E. Unless you have removed all references to Project Gutenberg:

1.E.1. The following sentence, with active links to, or other immediate

access to, the full Project Gutenberg-tm License must appear prominently

whenever any copy of a Project Gutenberg-tm work (any work on which the

phrase "Project Gutenberg" appears, or with which the phrase "Project

Gutenberg" is associated) is accessed, displayed, performed, viewed,

copied or distributed:

This eBook is for the use of anyone anywhere at no cost and with

almost no restrictions whatsoever. You may copy it, give it away or

re-use it under the terms of the Project Gutenberg License included

with this eBook or online at www.gutenberg.net

1.E.2. If an individual Project Gutenberg-tm electronic work is derived

from the public domain (does not contain a notice indicating that it is

posted with permission of the copyright holder), the work can be copied

and distributed to anyone in the United States without paying any fees

or charges. If you are redistributing or providing access to a work

with the phrase "Project Gutenberg" associated with or appearing on the

work, you must comply either with the requirements of paragraphs 1.E.1

through 1.E.7 or obtain permission for the use of the work and the

Project Gutenberg-tm trademark as set forth in paragraphs 1.E.8 or

1.E.9.

1.E.3. If an individual Project Gutenberg-tm electronic work is posted

with the permission of the copyright holder, your use and distribution

must comply with both paragraphs 1.E.1 through 1.E.7 and any additional

terms imposed by the copyright holder. Additional terms will be linked

to the Project Gutenberg-tm License for all works posted with the

permission of the copyright holder found at the beginning of this work.

1.E.4. Do not unlink or detach or remove the full Project Gutenberg-tm

License terms from this work, or any files containing a part of this

work or any other work associated with Project Gutenberg-tm.

1.E.5. Do not copy, display, perform, distribute or redistribute this

electronic work, or any part of this electronic work, without

prominently displaying the sentence set forth in paragraph 1.E.1 with

active links or immediate access to the full terms of the Project

Gutenberg-tm License.

1.E.6. You may convert to and distribute this work in any binary,

compressed, marked up, nonproprietary or proprietary form, including any

word processing or hypertext form. However, if you provide access to or

distribute copies of a Project Gutenberg-tm work in a format other than

"Plain Vanilla ASCII" or other format used in the official version

posted on the official Project Gutenberg-tm web site (www.gutenberg.net),

you must, at no additional cost, fee or expense to the user, provide a

copy, a means of exporting a copy, or a means of obtaining a copy upon

request, of the work in its original "Plain Vanilla ASCII" or other

form. Any alternate format must include the full Project Gutenberg-tm

License as specified in paragraph 1.E.1.

1.E.7. Do not charge a fee for access to, viewing, displaying,

performing, copying or distributing any Project Gutenberg-tm works

unless you comply with paragraph 1.E.8 or 1.E.9.

1.E.8. You may charge a reasonable fee for copies of or providing

access to or distributing Project Gutenberg-tm electronic works provided

that

- You pay a royalty fee of 20% of the gross profits you derive from

the use of Project Gutenberg-tm works calculated using the method

you already use to calculate your applicable taxes. The fee is

owed to the owner of the Project Gutenberg-tm trademark, but he

has agreed to donate royalties under this paragraph to the

Project Gutenberg Literary Archive Foundation. Royalty payments

must be paid within 60 days following each date on which you

prepare (or are legally required to prepare) your periodic tax

returns. Royalty payments should be clearly marked as such and

sent to the Project Gutenberg Literary Archive Foundation at the

address specified in Section 4, "Information about donations to

the Project Gutenberg Literary Archive Foundation."

- You provide a full refund of any money paid by a user who notifies

you in writing (or by e-mail) within 30 days of receipt that s/he

does not agree to the terms of the full Project Gutenberg-tm

License. You must require such a user to return or

destroy all copies of the works possessed in a physical medium

and discontinue all use of and all access to other copies of

Project Gutenberg-tm works.

- You provide, in accordance with paragraph 1.F.3, a full refund of any

money paid for a work or a replacement copy, if a defect in the

electronic work is discovered and reported to you within 90 days

of receipt of the work.

- You comply with all other terms of this agreement for free

distribution of Project Gutenberg-tm works.

1.E.9. If you wish to charge a fee or distribute a Project Gutenberg-tm

electronic work or group of works on different terms than are set

forth in this agreement, you must obtain permission in writing from

both the Project Gutenberg Literary Archive Foundation and Michael

Hart, the owner of the Project Gutenberg-tm trademark. Contact the

Foundation as set forth in Section 3 below.

1.F.

1.F.1. Project Gutenberg volunteers and employees expend considerable

effort to identify, do copyright research on, transcribe and proofread

public domain works in creating the Project Gutenberg-tm

collection. Despite these efforts, Project Gutenberg-tm electronic

works, and the medium on which they may be stored, may contain

"Defects," such as, but not limited to, incomplete, inaccurate or

corrupt data, transcription errors, a copyright or other intellectual

property infringement, a defective or damaged disk or other medium, a

computer virus, or computer codes that damage or cannot be read by

your equipment.

1.F.2. LIMITED WARRANTY, DISCLAIMER OF DAMAGES - Except for the "Right

of Replacement or Refund" described in paragraph 1.F.3, the Project

Gutenberg Literary Archive Foundation, the owner of the Project

Gutenberg-tm trademark, and any other party distributing a Project

Gutenberg-tm electronic work under this agreement, disclaim all

liability to you for damages, costs and expenses, including legal

fees. YOU AGREE THAT YOU HAVE NO REMEDIES FOR NEGLIGENCE, STRICT

LIABILITY, BREACH OF WARRANTY OR BREACH OF CONTRACT EXCEPT THOSE

PROVIDED IN PARAGRAPH F3. YOU AGREE THAT THE FOUNDATION, THE

TRADEMARK OWNER, AND ANY DISTRIBUTOR UNDER THIS AGREEMENT WILL NOT BE

LIABLE TO YOU FOR ACTUAL, DIRECT, INDIRECT, CONSEQUENTIAL, PUNITIVE OR

INCIDENTAL DAMAGES EVEN IF YOU GIVE NOTICE OF THE POSSIBILITY OF SUCH

DAMAGE.

1.F.3. LIMITED RIGHT OF REPLACEMENT OR REFUND - If you discover a

defect in this electronic work within 90 days of receiving it, you can

receive a refund of the money (if any) you paid for it by sending a

written explanation to the person you received the work from. If you

received the work on a physical medium, you must return the medium with

your written explanation. The person or entity that provided you with

the defective work may elect to provide a replacement copy in lieu of a

refund. If you received the work electronically, the person or entity

providing it to you may choose to give you a second opportunity to

receive the work electronically in lieu of a refund. If the second copy

is also defective, you may demand a refund in writing without further

opportunities to fix the problem.

1.F.4. Except for the limited right of replacement or refund set forth

in paragraph 1.F.3, this work is provided to you 'AS-IS', WITH NO OTHER

WARRANTIES OF ANY KIND, EXPRESS OR IMPLIED, INCLUDING BUT NOT LIMITED TO

WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTIBILITY OR FITNESS FOR ANY PURPOSE.

1.F.5. Some states do not allow disclaimers of certain implied

warranties or the exclusion or limitation of certain types of damages.

If any disclaimer or limitation set forth in this agreement violates the

law of the state applicable to this agreement, the agreement shall be

interpreted to make the maximum disclaimer or limitation permitted by

the applicable state law. The invalidity or unenforceability of any

provision of this agreement shall not void the remaining provisions.

1.F.6. INDEMNITY - You agree to indemnify and hold the Foundation, the

trademark owner, any agent or employee of the Foundation, anyone

providing copies of Project Gutenberg-tm electronic works in accordance

with this agreement, and any volunteers associated with the production,

promotion and distribution of Project Gutenberg-tm electronic works,

harmless from all liability, costs and expenses, including legal fees,

that arise directly or indirectly from any of the following which you do

or cause to occur: (a) distribution of this or any Project Gutenberg-tm

work, (b) alteration, modification, or additions or deletions to any

Project Gutenberg-tm work, and (c) any Defect you cause.

Section 2. Information about the Mission of Project Gutenberg-tm

Project Gutenberg-tm is synonymous with the free distribution of

electronic works in formats readable by the widest variety of computers

including obsolete, old, middle-aged and new computers. It exists

because of the efforts of hundreds of volunteers and donations from

people in all walks of life.

Volunteers and financial support to provide volunteers with the

assistance they need, is critical to reaching Project Gutenberg-tm's

goals and ensuring that the Project Gutenberg-tm collection will

remain freely available for generations to come. In 2001, the Project

Gutenberg Literary Archive Foundation was created to provide a secure

and permanent future for Project Gutenberg-tm and future generations.

To learn more about the Project Gutenberg Literary Archive Foundation

and how your efforts and donations can help, see Sections 3 and 4

and the Foundation web page at http://www.gutenberg.net/fundraising/pglaf.

Section 3. Information about the Project Gutenberg Literary Archive

Foundation

The Project Gutenberg Literary Archive Foundation is a non profit

501(c)(3) educational corporation organized under the laws of the

state of Mississippi and granted tax exempt status by the Internal

Revenue Service. The Foundation's EIN or federal tax identification

number is 64-6221541. Contributions to the Project Gutenberg

Literary Archive Foundation are tax deductible to the full extent

permitted by U.S. federal laws and your state's laws.

The Foundation's principal office is located at 4557 Melan Dr. S.

Fairbanks, AK, 99712., but its volunteers and employees are scattered

throughout numerous locations. Its business office is located at

809 North 1500 West, Salt Lake City, UT 84116, (801) 596-1887, email

business@pglaf.org. Email contact links and up to date contact

information can be found at the Foundation's web site and official

page at http://www.gutenberg.net/about/contact

For additional contact information:

Dr. Gregory B. Newby

Chief Executive and Director

gbnewby@pglaf.org

Section 4. Information about Donations to the Project Gutenberg

Literary Archive Foundation

Project Gutenberg-tm depends upon and cannot survive without wide

spread public support and donations to carry out its mission of

increasing the number of public domain and licensed works that can be

freely distributed in machine readable form accessible by the widest

array of equipment including outdated equipment. Many small donations

($1 to $5,000) are particularly important to maintaining tax exempt

status with the IRS.

The Foundation is committed to complying with the laws regulating

charities and charitable donations in all 50 states of the United

States. Compliance requirements are not uniform and it takes a

considerable effort, much paperwork and many fees to meet and keep up

with these requirements. We do not solicit donations in locations

where we have not received written confirmation of compliance. To

SEND DONATIONS or determine the status of compliance for any

particular state visit http://www.gutenberg.net/fundraising/donate

While we cannot and do not solicit contributions from states where we

have not met the solicitation requirements, we know of no prohibition

against accepting unsolicited donations from donors in such states who

approach us with offers to donate.

International donations are gratefully accepted, but we cannot make

any statements concerning tax treatment of donations received from

outside the United States. U.S. laws alone swamp our small staff.

Please check the Project Gutenberg Web pages for current donation

methods and addresses. Donations are accepted in a number of other

ways including including checks, online payments and credit card

donations. To donate, please visit:

http://www.gutenberg.net/fundraising/donate

Section 5. General Information About Project Gutenberg-tm electronic

works.

Professor Michael S. Hart is the originator of the Project Gutenberg-tm

concept of a library of electronic works that could be freely shared

with anyone. For thirty years, he produced and distributed Project

Gutenberg-tm eBooks with only a loose network of volunteer support.

Project Gutenberg-tm eBooks are often created from several printed

editions, all of which are confirmed as Public Domain in the U.S.

unless a copyright notice is included. Thus, we do not necessarily

keep eBooks in compliance with any particular paper edition.

Most people start at our Web site which has the main PG search facility:

http://www.gutenberg.net

This Web site includes information about Project Gutenberg-tm,

including how to make donations to the Project Gutenberg Literary

Archive Foundation, how to help produce our new eBooks, and how to

subscribe to our email newsletter to hear about new eBooks.